<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>DOI:10.6245/JLIS.2014.402/638 <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">圖書館學與資訊科學 40(2) ：23 -46(民一○三年十月) </note>
				
				<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<front>知識管理與競爭智慧課程內容比較研究 <lb/>─以美國圖書館學會認證之圖書館 <lb/>與資訊學碩士課程為例 <lb/>黃元鶴 <lb/>輔仁大學圖書資訊學系副教授 <lb/>E-mail：yuanho@lins.fju.edu.tw <lb/>關鍵詞： 課程設計；知識管理；競爭智慧；圖書資訊學教育 <lb/></front>

			<front>【摘要】 <lb/>知識管理已發展數十年，首由管理學院開 <lb/>始關注課程設計及教育相關議題，圖書館與 <lb/>資訊科學系所亦陸續開設相關課程，先前已 <lb/>有多篇研究探索知識管理課程設計議題。本 <lb/>研究檢視美國圖書館學會認證之圖書館與資 <lb/>訊學碩士課程，由 2006 年之 3 所學校成長 <lb/>至今之 20 所學校提供知識管理相關課程。本 <lb/>研究比較知識管理與競爭智慧課程名稱、圖 <lb/>書資訊學程定位、學分數、目標、內容及課 <lb/>程單元、教學設計等議題，亦探索了兩課程 <lb/>間關連。本研究以內容分析法綜整其中 14 校 <lb/>之知識管理課程目標及大綱，區分為理論、 <lb/>範疇、組織文化與人力、流程、分享與網絡、 <lb/>評鑑、資訊科技與系統、實務與個案、競爭 <lb/>智慧與知識服務等九項構面，與先前研究之 <lb/>核心要項差異不大。競爭智慧之概念早於知 <lb/>識管理，臺灣學者較少論及其相關概念。本 <lb/>研究亦綜整 6 校之競爭智慧課程內容呈現如 <lb/>下 13 項構面：策略理論、組織定位與角色及 <lb/>任務、智慧產品及週期、利害關係人之競合 <lb/>關係、法律倫理與環境、價值與需求、新技 <lb/>術、評鑑、問題解決方案與決策、系統安全、 <lb/>國家安全、危機與威脅、認識論與有限的理 <lb/>性等。競爭智慧主要為因應外部及未來的情 <lb/>境而形成的策略性活動，而知識管理則在於 <lb/>內部管理改善而提出改革方案或配套措施， <lb/>其課程各有其特色，建議可輪流於不同學期 <lb/>開設課程以提供互補資源。兩種課程都強調 <lb/>實務及個案研究的重要性，未來可為圖書館 <lb/>與資訊科學系所教師提供「哈佛式個案教學」 <lb/>工作坊，以增進教學技能。 <lb/></front>
				
			<body>前言 <lb/>知識管理首由管理學領域提出其重要性，圖書館 <lb/>與資訊科學(Library and Information Science, LIS) <lb/>[1]領域亦自九○年代開始推展其概念，並思索如何 <lb/>融入於圖書資訊學教育。然而，Davenport 與 Cronin <lb/>(2000)提出大部分資訊專業人員仍無法區辨資訊 <lb/>管理與知識管理的差異，而近年則有 Roknuzzaman <lb/>與 Umemoto(2009)之調查發現，館員對於知識管 <lb/>理的認識仍停留在整理外顯知識之膚淺認知。因 <lb/>此，知識管理課程於圖書資訊學相關學校之設置狀 <lb/>況，以及其相關課程設計內容相當重要。 <lb/>若干研究著眼於知識管理課程規劃與設計於圖書 <lb/>資訊學相關學校(王心裁、呂元智，2003；邱子 <lb/>恒，2006；孫曉甯、儲節旺，2013；盛小平，2010； <lb/>儲節旺、郭春俠、朱永，2008；Hazeri, Martin, &amp; <lb/>Sarrafzadeh, 2009; Kigongo-Bukenya &amp; Kaddu, 2011; <lb/>Rehman &amp; Chaudhry, 2005) ，部分研究檢視學校網站 <lb/></body>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Library and Information Science 40(2) ：23 -46(October, 2014) <lb/></note>

			<body>資訊，部分研究進行問卷調查分析，地區範圍偏布 <lb/>各洲之圖書資訊學相關學校。 <lb/>競爭智慧之概念雖早於知識管理，然而臺灣學者 <lb/>較少關注其議題發展，西方學者 (Bouthillier &amp; Dalkir, <lb/>2005; McGonagle, 2012; Ghannay &amp; Mamlouk, 2012 <lb/>Shelfer &amp; Goodrum, 2000)曾綜整比較知識管理與競 <lb/>爭智慧概念重點，中國學者則首先由邱均平與段宇 <lb/>峰(2000)探索知識管理與競爭智慧之異同，至今 <lb/>約二百餘篇研究探索相關主題(張慧杰，2011) 。 <lb/>競爭智慧課程相關研究，若干中國學者(張翠英、 <lb/>亢臨，1997；蔣貴凰、李艷、宋維翔，2006；張翠 <lb/>英、姚志廣，2008)由圖書資訊學科角度思索競爭 <lb/>智慧課程設置要素。美國大學開設競爭智慧課程相 <lb/>關研究，王瑤(2005)比較美國之圖書資訊學相關 <lb/>學 校 與 商 學 院 課 程 設 置 情 形 ， Jin 與 Bouthillier <lb/>(2012)則檢視美國圖書館學會認證之圖書館與資 <lb/>訊學碩士課程之開設課程中，融入競爭智慧相關概 <lb/>念情況。 <lb/>中國與臺灣之圖書館學校發展，深受美國圖書資 <lb/>訊學相關學校的影響，而創立於 1876 年之美國圖書 <lb/>館學會(American Library Association, ALA) ，具有 <lb/>引領圖書資訊學專業發展方向的主要任務，經由美 <lb/>國圖書館學會認證之圖書館與資訊學碩士課程，具 <lb/>有辦學優良的品質保證。他山之石，可以攻錯，因 <lb/>此，本研究藉由檢視知識管理與競爭智慧相關課程 <lb/>內容於美國圖書資訊學相關學校開設概況，以思考 <lb/>未來課程改革方向。本研究目的為檢視知識管理與 <lb/>競爭智慧兩項課程於圖書資訊學相關學校之開課概 <lb/>況、課程定位與內容要素，以及該兩課程間之定位 <lb/>與關係。 <lb/>本研究欲探討的問題如下： (一)美國圖書館學會 <lb/>認證之圖書館與資訊學碩士課程中，哪些學校開設 <lb/>知識管理、競爭智慧相關課程？相關課程名稱為 <lb/>何？(二)近十年之知識管理課程開設態樣是否有 <lb/>差異？(三)知識管理與競爭智慧課程兩項課程之 <lb/>目標、單元內容、教學方法與作業設計等有何異同？ <lb/>(四)知識管理與競爭智慧課程關係為何？其於圖 <lb/>書資訊學教育定位為何？ <lb/>文獻探討 <lb/>知識管理與競爭智慧概念關係比較 <lb/>知識管理是跨學科的領域，不少學者由不同面向 <lb/>為其定義，本研究整合不同觀點，定義如下：知識 <lb/>管理為應用有系統的方法為獲取、組織、管理、分享 <lb/>與散播組織之內隱及外顯知識，增加最佳實務的再 <lb/>用性，降低專案間的重複性，以促進有效率與效能 <lb/>的工作及決策最佳化(Nonaka &amp; Takeuchi, 1995; Wiig, <lb/>1997; Davenport &amp; Prusak, 1998; Townley, 2001) 。 <lb/>競爭智慧之原文為 Competitive Intelligence，然而 <lb/>Intelligence 之中譯文不易精簡表達其意涵。Intelligence <lb/>於 Merriam-Webster 字典之定義主要有其二：其一為 <lb/>「可學習或知曉相關事務以面臨新環境或處理困境 <lb/>的能力(the ability to learn or understand things or to <lb/>deal with new or difficult situations) 」 。其二為「政府 <lb/>收集敵人或潛在敵人的機密資訊(secret information <lb/>that a government collects about an enemy or possible <lb/>enemy) 」 。依前述的內容，其一簡稱「智慧」 ，其二 <lb/>簡稱「情報」是適當的。 <lb/>另外，依據 Kent(1949)對於 strategic intelligence <lb/>之定義為： 「可確保任務不因政治家或軍人犯無心之 <lb/>過而失敗的知識(kind of knowledge a state must <lb/>possess regarding other states in order to assure itself <lb/>that its causes will not suffer nor its undertakings fail <lb/>because its statesmen and soldiers plan and act in <lb/>ignorance) 」 ，依前述之意，本研究將 Intelligence 譯 <lb/>為「智慧」 。 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">圖書館學與資訊科學 40(2) ：23 -46(民一○三年十月) </note>
				
				<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<body>表 1 知識管理與競爭智慧概念比較表 <lb/>比較項目 <lb/>知識管理 <lb/>競爭智慧 <lb/>驅力來源 <lb/>內在驅力(組織內部成員之意願與投入) 外在驅力(政治、經濟、社會、科技) <lb/>主要焦點 <lb/>理論：內外部知識 <lb/>實務：大部分是內部 <lb/>利用內外部資源以因應外部環境變化 <lb/>實務：大部分使用外部資源 <lb/>主要目標 <lb/>理論：策略型及操作型 <lb/>短期：將有價值之知識做最佳化之運用以 <lb/>達組織學習與創新 <lb/>長期：改善組織績效 <lb/>實務：資料倉儲 <lb/>理論：策略型 <lb/>短期：支援策略型決策以因應外部環境之 <lb/>威脅與機會 <lb/>長期：改善競爭力 <lb/>實務：獲取資訊以備不時之需 <lb/>主要使用者 <lb/>個人、群體、組織 <lb/>高層經營者、決策者 <lb/>重要價值 <lb/>發展組織記憶系統以確保組織累積經驗 <lb/>之取得與再用 <lb/>創建決策資訊以利在最佳時機提供智慧 <lb/>給決策者 <lb/>主要支持的管理功能 <lb/>策略規劃、行銷、生產製造、人力資源管 <lb/>理、研發 <lb/>策略規劃、行銷 <lb/>達成目標的主要技巧 <lb/>知識資產盤點、增加價值與知識再包裝、 <lb/>驗證知識價值、標竿學習、創建分類 <lb/>分析性技巧，如 SWOT、標竿學習、競爭 <lb/>者分析檔、產業分析 <lb/>主要技術 <lb/>知識萃取的工具、組織分享與應用(如群 <lb/>組軟體、內容管理軟體、線上學習平台、 <lb/>電子績效支援平台、知識典藏平台、分類 <lb/>系統、人工智慧等) <lb/>競爭智慧特定軟體與特定工具，以搜尋與 <lb/>獲 取 資 訊 ， 如 智 慧 代 理 人 、 分 析 技 術 <lb/>(profiling technology) 、網頁搜尋工具、 <lb/>內容管理工具等。 <lb/>適用情境及問題 <lb/>管理及擴展現行知識庫，問題： 「明天我 <lb/>們如何做得比昨天更好？」 <lb/>為尚未具體形成的問題找尋相關資料，問 <lb/>題： 「下一步將發生何事？」 <lb/>主要資料來源： <lb/>Bouthillier, F. &amp; Dalkir, K. (2005). Knowledge management and competitive intelligence: Examination of similarities, <lb/>differences and intersections. In Knowledge management: nurturing culture, innovation and technology : Proceedings <lb/>of the 2005 International Conference on Knowledge Management (Hawamdeh, S. Ed, pp. 603-610). New Jersey: <lb/>World Scientific Publishing. <lb/>競爭智慧崛起於 80 年代，Porter(1980)的著作， <lb/>促進此學科發展，相關專業學會如美國競爭智慧專 <lb/>業人學會(The Society of Competitive Intelligence <lb/>Professionals，現已改名為 The Strategic and Competitive <lb/>Intelligence Professionals，簡稱 SCIP) ，創立於 1986 <lb/>年，其概念之推展，早於知識管理。綜整多位學者 <lb/>對於兩概念之比較如表 1，Bouthillier 與 Dalkir <lb/>(2005) 之研究為表 1 之主要資料來源， 「驅力來源」 <lb/>與「適用情境及問題面向」 ，則分別由 Shelfer 與 <lb/>Goodrum(2000) ，以及 McGonagle(2012)的觀點 <lb/>補充於此表。表 1 呈現競爭智慧主要在因應外部及 <lb/>未來的情境而形成的策略性活動，而知識管理則主 <lb/>要在於內部管理改善而提出改革方案或配套措施。 <lb/>兩概念有重疊的部分，然各自亦有其重點。 <lb/>競爭智慧之概念雖早於知識管理，臺灣較少文獻 <lb/>於競爭智慧相關主題，然而知識管理文獻數量相當 <lb/>多，且分布於不同領域。臺灣學者未曾就競爭智慧 <lb/>於圖書資訊學之發展撰文，知識管理則有林珊如 <lb/>(2002)由知識管理的目的、對象、範圍、知識類 <lb/>型與流程等面向，闡述圖書資訊學界與企業界的異 <lb/>同，並提出關於圖書資訊學可結合知識管理於理論 <lb/>及實務的建議。 <lb/>中國學者慣用「競爭情報」名稱，為求本文名詞 <lb/>統一，本文仍以「競爭智慧」稱之。中國學者討論 <lb/>知識管理議題者相當多，由於臺灣關於競爭智慧主 <lb/>題文獻較少，因此本段以中國學者之觀點來補述競 <lb/>爭智慧內容。中國學者包昌火、李艷與包琰(2012) <lb/>完整論述競爭智慧學科的起源、該學科引入中國的 <lb/>歷史貢獻、發展紀實、定位問題、研究內容(包括 <lb/>資訊轉化理論等不同主題) 、競爭智慧與知識管理融 <lb/>合議題，以及競爭智慧與其他學科及中國圖書資訊 <lb/>學的關連。中國最早討論競爭智慧與知識管理兩者 <lb/></body>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Library and Information Science 40(2) ：23 -46(October, 2014) <lb/></note>

			<body>關連為邱均平與段宇峰(2000) ，近年亦有張旭、孫 <lb/>雪蓮與張修文(2013)以知識管理觀點探討中國圖 <lb/>書資訊學的發展，提出若有效整合競爭智慧與知識 <lb/>管理概念，可提高知識資源的共享程度並有利於提 <lb/>高資訊服務的效率之觀點。此外，若干研究以文獻 <lb/>計量方法分析競爭智慧文獻(胡笑梅、李文玉， <lb/>2012；張璐、趙輝，2012；秦振飛，2014) ，亦有人 <lb/>整合競爭智慧與知識管理兩主題之文獻計量分析 <lb/>(張慧杰，2011) ，該研究綜整兩概念研究文獻於 <lb/>2000-2003 年間共計 34 篇，2004-2010 年共計 173 <lb/>篇，顯示自邱均平與段宇峰(2000)研究之後，仍 <lb/>持續有相關研究於探析兩概念間的關係。近年，西 <lb/>方亦有相關研究(Ghannay &amp; Mamlouk, 2012)探索 <lb/>兩概念間之綜效。因此，本研究由課程內容來檢視 <lb/>競爭智慧與知識管理的關連及異同。 <lb/>知識管理課程規劃研究 <lb/>知識管理首由管理學院開始關注課程設計及教育 <lb/>相關議題，圖書資訊學相關系所亦陸續開設相關課 <lb/>程，除了探索課程規劃設計內容之外，亦探討知識 <lb/>管理專業人才培育之相關問題。以下分述大學之知 <lb/>識管理課程規劃架構、跨學科領域設置知識管理課 <lb/>程概況，以及圖書資訊學相關系所探索如何規劃與 <lb/>設計知識管理課程。 <lb/>George Mason University 於 1999 年即提出大學碩 <lb/>士班開設知識管理課程之七大核心模組，包括知識 <lb/>創造、知識管理歷史與理論、信任的重要、策略議 <lb/>題、知識編碼、軟硬體系統、知識報酬率與評鑑、 <lb/>國際議題等。此外，該研究亦建議四種導論的方式， <lb/>如產業實例個案、野中郁次郎的知識螺旋模型理 <lb/>論、人力資源相關議題、軟硬體相關議題，並以策 <lb/>略方格矩陣列舉各議題的重要程度，以及網站資源 <lb/>與必備圖書相關資源(Ruth, Theobald, &amp; Frizzell, <lb/>1999) 。此研究泛指大學所有相關科系開設知識管理 <lb/>課程於內容規劃的建議及教材資源。 <lb/>更多研究整合不同學科領域之知識管理課程設置 <lb/>概況如下：一項於 2000-2002 年間進行兩階段之調 <lb/>查研究，檢視澳大利亞、加拿大、新加坡、英國、 <lb/>美國等五國之 37 所大學開設知識管理課程概況。研 <lb/>究結果顯示各專業學院之知識管理課程重點不同， <lb/>商管學院較重視如智慧資本、衡量及企業個案；資 <lb/>訊系統及資訊研究學院較重視知識庫、發展、組織 <lb/>及管理知識內容；電腦科學系則著重於資訊科技工 <lb/>具的發展，顯示知識管理課程之跨學科特色，建議 <lb/>可合作開課以平衡不同的取向(Chaudhry &amp; Higgins, <lb/>2003) 。另一項研究為調查《2006 年世界大學科研 <lb/>競爭力排行榜》之排行前 50 所大學，由學校網站檢 <lb/>視知識管理課程設置概況。研究結果顯示 21 所大學 <lb/>設置知識管理相關課程，分布於圖書情報與檔案、 <lb/>經濟與管理學、計算機科學與電子科學、媒體藝術 <lb/>與科學、政治學、電子商務、知識管理、航空航太 <lb/>學、土木與環境工程、教育、法學等不同專業系所。 <lb/>該研究亦深入介紹美國麻省理工學院、美國華盛頓 <lb/>大學、英國愛丁堡大學、中國北京大學及中國武漢 <lb/>大學等 6 校之課程特色，並分析其教學模式、課程 <lb/>內容、課程性質、教學目標、教學方法等項目(王 <lb/>翠波、張玉峰、吳金紅、艾丹祥，2007；張玉峰、 <lb/>王翠波、吳金紅、艾丹祥，2008) 。另一項研究由雅 <lb/>虎(Yahoo)之教育名錄搜尋開設知識管理課程之大 <lb/>學，27 所學校當中 13 所為碩士課程，以課程關鍵 <lb/>字做內容分析，研究結果呈現多元化的知識管理相 <lb/>關課程名稱，及其內容之多樣性，綜整之課程模組， <lb/>包括倫理、資訊管理、知識管理、智慧資本、知識 <lb/>分享與合作及文化、知識組織、學習型組織、競爭 <lb/>智慧、電子商務、知識管理科技工具，管理、研究 <lb/>方法等主題，其下再詳列其次主題(Rehman &amp; <lb/>Sumait, 2010) 。 <lb/>若干研究曾針對圖書資訊學相關系所探索如何規 <lb/>劃與設計知識管理課程，Rehman 與 Chaudhry (2005) <lb/>調查 12 所圖書資訊學相關學校主管，遍布於北美、 <lb/>歐洲、太平洋等地區，關於知識管理教育於圖書資 <lb/>訊學相關學校施行狀況，其結果如下：多數主管認 <lb/>為畢業生投入知識管理相關行業仍相當有限，多數 <lb/>學校提供該課程於碩士課程，少數學校融入該課程 <lb/>內容於大學部課程中，若干教師配合開設新課程之 <lb/>意願不高，策略聯盟相關資源可找尋商管及電腦學 <lb/>系，並需多多結合產業界實務經驗，促使課程發揮 <lb/>較大效益。另一項相關研究為 Hazeri、Martin 與 <lb/>Sarrafzadeh(2009)於圖書館專業學會等之線上論 <lb/>壇(如 IFLA KMDG-L)散播線上問卷網址，調查知 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">圖書館學與資訊科學 40(2) ：23 -46(民一○三年十月) </note>
				
				<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<body>識管理教育於圖書資訊學課程現況及主軸發展方 <lb/>向，研究結果為近 3 成者對於目前圖書資訊學課程 <lb/>是否符合知識管理教育需求之狀況不清楚，且認為 <lb/>知識管理相關能力之訓練不足。未來主軸發展議題 <lb/>依重要性程度如下次序：知識相關議題(如知識經 <lb/>濟、知識創造、知識分享) 、實務及案例、組織管理、 <lb/>資訊相關議題(如資訊社會、資訊行為) 、研究與評 <lb/>鑑、人際關係(如團隊合作、領導力) 、資訊通訊技 <lb/>術等。另外，近年則有相關研究為非洲圖書館學會 <lb/>提出知識管理課程規劃，內容包括定義、角色及任 <lb/>務、程序(過程與方法) 、資訊及知識能力、資訊及 <lb/>知識網絡、資訊及知識技術、人力因素、衡量議題 <lb/>(評估導入效能)等八項主題(Kigongo-Bukenya &amp; <lb/>Kaddu, 2011) 。 <lb/>中國之信息管理相關學院亦有若干關於知識管理 <lb/>課程規劃及專業碩士學位之研究，王心裁與呂元智 <lb/>(2003)建議應整合信息管理、企業管理、資訊科 <lb/>技、其他綜合相關內容於知識管理課程設計，並提 <lb/>出三階段逐步課程設置建議：增開知識管理課程、 <lb/>增設知識管理專業學位 (含大學至博士) 、另設 MKA <lb/>(Master of Knowledge Administration)碩士學位課 <lb/>程，以培養知識主管人才。儲節旺、郭春俠與朱永 <lb/>(2008)則比較中外知識管理教育概況，檢視澳大 <lb/>利亞、加拿大、新加坡、美國、英國等國家之大學 <lb/>設置知識管理課程概況，指出國外知識管理之正規 <lb/>課程較成熟，亦重視過程教育，甚至有證書培訓， <lb/>以及學習型組織的實踐社團。由國外的實例分析結 <lb/>果，為中國信息管理相關學校提出課程改革建議。 <lb/>最新研究是孫曉甯與儲節旺(2013)詳細分析中國 <lb/>之知識管理專業碩士及博士學位狀況，結果呈現僅 <lb/>於管理學領域中，若干學校設置知識管理專業碩士 <lb/>學位課程，而圖書情報學領域，僅開設相關課程， <lb/>未設置知識管理專業碩士學位。該研究並區辨圖書 <lb/>情報學與管理學領域之知識管理課程個別的特色， <lb/>前者重知識組織、圖書館知識服務、資源共享、知 <lb/>識圖譜等；後者重知識資本、知識網絡、知識產權、 <lb/>知識型員工、知識移轉等議題。最後並列舉美國若 <lb/>干圖書資訊學相關學校設置之知識管理碩士課程為 <lb/>例，期許未來可進一步於信息管理學院設置知識管 <lb/>理專業碩博士學位。 <lb/>前述研究多為分析網站資訊，僅少數進行調查研 <lb/>究，盛小平(2010)綜整多位學者所提之知識管理 <lb/>課程內容要項為基礎理論、戰略與方法、過程、實 <lb/>踐與應用、關鍵技術等項。以前述項目為架構來設 <lb/>計問卷，收集大學生對於知識管理課程內容需求的 <lb/>優先序。研究結果顯示其優先序為實踐與應用(如 <lb/>案例分析) 、戰略與方法(如知識創新與經營戰略) 、 <lb/>過程(如知識創造、應用、共享等，及智力資本價 <lb/>值鏈) 、基礎理論、關鍵技術(如隱性知識至顯性知 <lb/>識轉化技術) 。 <lb/>此外，若干研究則由知識管理所需技能與圖書資 <lb/>訊學相關學校課程配合度之觀點著手，Lai(2005) <lb/>曾經於 2000-2001 年在 Lycos、Alta Vista、Google <lb/>等三個搜尋引擎，關鍵詞以 knowledge manager、 <lb/>knowledge analyst、knowledge management consult <lb/>等查找知識工作者之求才廣告所列能力要求，共計 <lb/>分析 27 個工作職缺要求。研究結果顯示圖書資訊學 <lb/>系所之教育背景曾列於部分工作職缺要求，知識工 <lb/>作者之工作需求的前三項排行為資訊科技、內容分 <lb/>類與管理、團隊合作經驗等，而圖書資訊所課程也 <lb/>已融入前述要素於課程內容中。另一項研究則由知 <lb/>識管理之跨學科本質來反思圖書資訊學相關學校如 <lb/>何訓練知識工作者，並以新加坡南洋理工科技大學 <lb/>(Nanyang Technological University)為例，該校之 <lb/>傳播及資訊學院發展之知識管理碩士學位招生之第 <lb/>1 屆學生意見及背景分析，除了區辨資訊管理與知 <lb/>識管理之差異，以及回饋於課程改善設計，並提出 <lb/>知識管理專業人力的認證議題(Al-Hawamdeh, 2005) 。 <lb/>臺灣圖書資訊學相關系所大多設有知識管理課 <lb/>程，多為探討知識管理專業人才核心技能(陳雪華、 <lb/>邱子恆、范中威，2000) ，或由實務工作反思專業人 <lb/>才培育要素(劉欣蓓、楊美華，2003) 。較少文獻針 <lb/>對知識管理課程內容規劃與設計來論述。邱子恒 <lb/>(2006)曾收集美國圖書館學會認證之圖書資訊學 <lb/>研究所開設之知識組織與知識管理相關課程，18 門 <lb/>課中僅 3 門課為「知識管理」課程，來自於下列 3 <lb/>所 學 校 ： University of Hawaii 、 University of <lb/>Michigan、University of Pittsburgh，其餘 15 門課程 <lb/>為「知識組織」 ，內容為書目記述與主題分析。由此 <lb/>可見，當時知識管理課程於美國圖書資訊學相關系 <lb/></body>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Library and Information Science 40(2) ：23 -46(October, 2014) <lb/></note>

			<body>所開設比率仍偏低。目前時空背景已與當時環境不 <lb/>同，因此，可再加以探索美國圖書資訊學相關系所 <lb/>開設知識管理相關課程的現況。 <lb/>競爭智慧課程規劃研究 <lb/>競爭智慧課程強調以策略的觀點來收集外部資 <lb/>訊，並依機構營運目標綜整與分析資訊，轉化為較 <lb/>接近決策者所需資訊，相關活動包括應用合法及符 <lb/>合倫理的方法，有效率地發掘、發展、綜整分析並 <lb/>即時傳送外部新知，以利整合企業趨勢、管理公共 <lb/>關係、危機處理，以促進有效的決策。目前多由管 <lb/>理或商學院設置相關課程，然而，亦有相關研究由 <lb/>圖書資訊學相關系所設置競爭智慧相關課程的角度。 <lb/>臺灣學者多為商學相關系所探討競爭智慧相關議 <lb/>題，圖書資訊相關系所雖亦曾設置相關課程，但無 <lb/>學者撰文刊登於臺灣出版品。 <lb/>不少中國學者探索競爭智慧課程設置問題，張翠 <lb/>英與亢臨生(1997)建議大陸圖書資訊相關系所應 <lb/>增設競爭智慧課程，開設此課程需經濟學、計算機 <lb/>基礎、行銷、資訊計量等相關知識，為達傳授其基 <lb/>本技能之目的，需重視實踐的環節。近年，蔣貴凰、 <lb/>李艷與宋維翔(2006)提出競爭智慧專業知識體系 <lb/>框架，呈現該課程與其他學科之關連及結合圖書資 <lb/>訊系所訓練之核心技能，綜整管理理論、技術理論、 <lb/>競爭智慧導論、競爭智慧系統、競爭智慧工作、智 <lb/>慧應用等六方面的課程設置。此外，張翠英與姚志廣 <lb/>(2008)亦就競爭智慧之應用技術及技能、法律及道 <lb/>德等提出相關意見，並呼籲應確認課程評估指標。 <lb/>美 國 大 學 開 設 競 爭 智 慧 課 程 相 關 研 究 ， 王 瑤 <lb/>(2005)曾檢視圖書資訊學相關學校與商學院排名 <lb/>前 15 名的大學其開設競爭智慧相關課程設置情 <lb/>形，研究結果呈現商學院開設相關課程數為圖書資 <lb/>訊學相關學校的近 2 倍；圖書資訊學相關學校多列 <lb/>為選修，而商學院列為必修比例(40.5%)較高；圖 <lb/>書資訊學相關學校課程內容著重介紹資訊資源，而 <lb/>商學院的課程則重視經濟學、金融、行銷等方面的 <lb/>知識。Jin 與 Bouthillier(2012)亦曾檢視美國圖書 <lb/>館學會認證之圖書資訊學研究所之開設課程當中， <lb/>融入智慧分析(Intelligence Analysis, IA)的情形。 <lb/>研究結果呈現約有 47%的圖書資訊學相關學校至少 <lb/>有提供一門課程融入智慧分析相關概念，相關開課 <lb/>名稱包括競爭智慧、策略智慧、商業智慧等等不同 <lb/>課程名稱。該研究並比較智慧分析師與圖書館員於 <lb/>工作職稱、資訊環境、資料處理的形態、業務急迫 <lb/>性、典型的活動類型等不同面向之內容差異。圖書 <lb/>資訊學與智慧分析有其互補性的連結，該研究建議 <lb/>未來可有系統性地研究智慧分析如何有效地融入圖 <lb/>書資訊學教育，以促進兩者結合的綜效。 <lb/>研究方法 <lb/>當今美國圖書館學會認證核可之圖書館與資訊學 <lb/>(Library and Information Studies)學校總數為 63 校 <lb/>[2]，遍及美國、加拿大、及波多黎各等國家。美國 <lb/>圖書館學會提供線上資料庫[3]，可供查詢經認證核 <lb/>可的圖書館與資訊學課程符合各主題專業(Areas of <lb/>concentration)課程的學校清單，本研究於 2014 年 1 <lb/>月於該資料庫中查詢提供知識管理相關課程，共計 <lb/>20 所學校，再逐一到各學校網站查詢相關課程詳細 <lb/>資訊資料。其中 University of California、Los Angeles <lb/>與 University of North Texas 兩校之當今網頁資訊並 <lb/>未提供知識管理相關課程。然而，另外由提供「專 <lb/>門／企業圖書館」之學校清單中查得 Simmons College <lb/>與 University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign 開設知識 <lb/>管理課程，因此亦將此兩校加入分析，本研究最終 <lb/>呈現 20 所學校之相關課程資訊，完整清單請見表 1。 <lb/>關於課程內容單元分析，本研究採取內容分析 <lb/>法，分析資料來源主要來自各校之課程目標文字內 <lb/>容，若該校之相關課程可獲取詳細課程大綱，則該 <lb/>課程大綱內容文字亦加入分析。本研究逐字檢視課 <lb/>程目標之內容，並一一提取英文關鍵詞，翻譯為中 <lb/>文詞，整併關鍵詞之同義或相關語，再為相同概念 <lb/>之關鍵詞群命名其構面名稱。此外，兩課程間之關 <lb/>係及其於圖書資訊學程之定位，則輔以文獻分析法。 <lb/>內容分析資訊來自於 20 所圖書資訊學相關學校 <lb/>網站之課程資訊。知識管理課程內容分析資訊來自 <lb/>於 14 所提供知識管理相關課程之學校課程網頁資 <lb/>訊，大部分是課程簡述(Course Description)資訊 <lb/>(各校之文字長度介於 17 字至 233 字間) ，僅 2 校 <lb/>提供課程大綱，Louisiana State University 提供 2 頁 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">圖書館學與資訊科學 40(2) ：23 -46(民一○三年十月) </note>
				
				<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<body>pdf 檔內容，Rutgers, The State University of New <lb/>Jersey 提供詳細課程大綱網頁(4380 字) 。另外，競 <lb/>爭智慧課程內容分析資訊來自 6 所提供競爭智慧相 <lb/>關課程之學校課程網資訊，多為課程簡述資訊(介 <lb/>於 30 字至 60 字間) ，僅 Indiana University 提供 2 份 <lb/>課程大綱詳細資訊，分別是 6 頁及 15 頁 pdf 檔。 <lb/>本研究之範圍與限制如下：第一、課程名稱為知 <lb/>識組織(Knowledge Organization) ，其內容聚焦於分 <lb/>類法與編目規則之課程，知識組織雖為知識管理之 <lb/>一環，然而，將原為知識管理課程單元之一的「知 <lb/>識組織」與「知識管理」課程來對等分析不太適宜， <lb/>因其內容重點之廣度與深度為不同層級，因此，本 <lb/>研究未將課程名稱為「知識組織」納入內容分析。 <lb/>第二、由於美國圖書館學會之各主題專業課程主題 <lb/>未提供「競爭智慧」領域，本研究由知識管理領域 <lb/>中彙整「競爭智慧」 ，可能無法呈現圖書資訊學相關 <lb/>學校開設「競爭智慧」相關課程的全貌。第三、僅 <lb/>少數學校提供完整的課程大綱內容，大部分學校僅 <lb/>提供課程目標的敘述，因此，本研究資料來源為各 <lb/>校相關課程的課程目標內容及納入少許課程的完整 <lb/>課程大綱，少數學校僅提供課程名稱列表，本研究 <lb/>則無法進一步做該課程之內容分析。第四、本研究 <lb/>由作者 1 人進行課程內容分析，難免落入個人主觀 <lb/>判斷，然而由於課程資訊文字，語意明確，幾乎無 <lb/>隱晦內容，較能達到詮釋與解讀文本之一致性。 <lb/>研究結果 <lb/>本研究結果首先呈現各校開設知識管理相關課程 <lb/>的總覽概況，其次提供知識管理碩士學位課程之兩 <lb/>所學校於該專業學位學程之開課概況。最後由各校 <lb/>開設知識管理相關課程當中，選定至少兩所學校開 <lb/>設之課程，並整併課程名稱雖不完全相同，但課程 <lb/>內容實相同，最終呈現知識管理與競爭智慧二種課 <lb/>程內容分析表，綜整各校之課程目標文字內容，列 <lb/>舉相關關鍵詞及對應之學校，分別於表 3 至表 5 呈 <lb/>現其綜整結果。 <lb/>各校開設知識管理與競爭智慧相關課程概況 <lb/>經美國圖書館學會認證核可之 63 所學校當中，共 <lb/>計 20 所學校開設知識管理相關課程，相較於邱子恒 <lb/>(2006)之研究結果，開設「知識管理」之學校數， <lb/>由 3 所成長至 20 所學校，可見近十年課程變動幅度 <lb/>不少。由各校網頁查詢知識管理相關課程開課狀 <lb/>況，綜整如表 2。大部分學校僅提供課程名稱、學 <lb/>分數、課程內容簡述，少數學校提供詳細的課程大 <lb/>綱。經一一檢視及整併課程名稱及內容後，歸類為 <lb/>知識管理、知識資產管理、競爭智慧、策略智慧、 <lb/>智慧資本等課程。 <lb/>「知識管理」為最多學校開設的課程名稱，共計 <lb/>13 所學校，但若干學校之名稱含微幅變動，詳細名 <lb/>稱於表中註記，其中兩所學校特地將資訊專業人員 <lb/>(Information professionals)包含於課程名稱當中， <lb/>以顯示與商學院開設相關課程之差異，而 University <lb/>of North Carolina 之課程亦特地加上專門圖書館 <lb/>(Special libraries) 。 <lb/>「知識資產管理」共有 2 校開設相關課程，著眼 <lb/>於組織當中的知識資產。其他相關課程尚有知識網 <lb/>絡(Knowledge Networks) 、知識架構與資訊專業人 <lb/>員、知識管理與系統等。 <lb/>「競爭智慧」相關課程，共計 5 校以「競爭智慧」 <lb/>名稱開課，其中較為特別的是 University of Illinois <lb/>開設應用企業研究課程，但整合競爭智慧與知識管 <lb/>理於該課程中，另一特殊處為此課程為 4 學分，表 <lb/>1 中其他所有課程都是 3 學分。Dominican University <lb/>將競爭智慧課程名稱加入「巨量資料」 (Big Data) ， <lb/>以符合時代趨勢。另外與此系列課程相近似的課 <lb/>程尚有 2 校開設「策略智慧」 ，1 校開設「智慧資 <lb/>本」 。 <lb/>其他相關課程名稱包含知識與資訊理論、資訊知 <lb/>識與社會、資訊科技與知識等，以及 University of <lb/>Toronto 開 設 的 資 訊 與 知 識 實 踐 研 究 ( Studying <lb/>Information and Knowledge Practices) 。 <lb/>前述資訊呈現知識管理相關課程多元化名稱，開 <lb/>課系所除了典型的圖書館與資訊科學所或學院之 <lb/>外，另有資訊科學與技術(Information Science and <lb/>Technology ) 、資 訊 學 與 計 算 學 ( Informatics and <lb/>Computing)等名稱之學院，顯示近年結合資訊科技 <lb/>趨勢愈加密切。 <lb/></body>

			<page>30 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Library and Information Science 40(2) ：23 -46(October, 2014) <lb/></note>

			<body>表 2 知識管理相關課程於各校開課狀況及課程名稱列表 <lb/>學校名稱 <lb/>開課系所名稱 <lb/>課程名稱 <lb/>知識管理 <lb/>(Knowledge <lb/>management) <lb/>知識資產管理 <lb/>(Knowledge <lb/>Assets <lb/>Management in <lb/>Organizations) <lb/>知識管理 <lb/>相關課程 <lb/>競爭智慧 <lb/>(Competitive <lb/>Intelligence) <lb/>策略智慧 <lb/>(Strategic <lb/>Intelligence) <lb/>智慧資本 <lb/>(Intellectual <lb/>Capital) <lb/>其他 <lb/>相關課程 <lb/>Dominican <lb/>University <lb/>Graduate School of <lb/>Library and <lb/>Information Science <lb/>(GSLIS) <lb/>○△ <lb/>○□ <lb/>(Big Data and <lb/>Competitive <lb/>Intelligence) <lb/>Drexel <lb/>University <lb/>College of <lb/>Information Science <lb/>and Technology <lb/>○△ <lb/>○□ <lb/>Indiana <lb/>University <lb/>School of Informatics <lb/>and Computing[1] <lb/>○□ <lb/>Kent State <lb/>University <lb/>School of Library &amp; <lb/>Information Science <lb/>○ <lb/>Louisiana <lb/>State <lb/>University <lb/>School of library &amp; <lb/>information science <lb/>○△ <lb/>(Management <lb/>of <lb/>Knowledge-B <lb/>ased Assets in <lb/>Organizations) <lb/>McGill <lb/>University <lb/>School of <lb/>Information Studies <lb/>○△ <lb/>Knowledge <lb/>Networks <lb/>○□ <lb/>○ <lb/>Rutgers, The <lb/>State <lb/>University <lb/>of New <lb/>Jersey <lb/>School of <lb/>Communication and <lb/>information <lb/>○△ <lb/>(Knowledge <lb/>Management <lb/>in <lb/>Organizations) <lb/>Knowledge <lb/>Structures and <lb/>the <lb/>Information <lb/>Professions <lb/>○□ <lb/>Simmons <lb/>College <lb/>Graduate School of <lb/>Library and <lb/>Information Science <lb/>○△ <lb/>Universite <lb/>de Montreal <lb/>School of Library <lb/>and Information <lb/>Science <lb/>○△ <lb/>University <lb/>of Alabama <lb/>School of Library &amp; <lb/>Information Studies <lb/>○△ <lb/>Knowledge <lb/>and <lb/>Information <lb/>Theory <lb/>University <lb/>of Alberta <lb/>School of Library <lb/>and information <lb/>studies <lb/>○△ <lb/>(Introduction <lb/>to KM) <lb/>University <lb/>of Illinois, <lb/>Urbana-<lb/>Champaign <lb/>Graduate School of <lb/>Library and <lb/>Information Science <lb/>Applied <lb/>Business <lb/>Research [...: <lb/>Competitive <lb/>Intelligence &amp; <lb/>Knowledge <lb/>Management] <lb/>Applied <lb/>Business <lb/>Research [...: <lb/>Competitive <lb/>Intelligence &amp; <lb/>Knowledge <lb/>Management] <lb/>University <lb/>of Maryland <lb/>College of <lb/>Information Studies <lb/>(CLIS) <lb/>○△ <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">圖書館學與資訊科學 40(2) ：23 -46(民一○三年十月) </note>
				
				<page>31 <lb/></page>

			<body>表 2 知識管理相關課程於各校開課狀況及課程名稱列表(續) <lb/>學校名稱 <lb/>開課系所名稱 <lb/>課程名稱 <lb/>知識管理 <lb/>(Knowledge <lb/>management) <lb/>知識資產管理 <lb/>(Knowledge <lb/>Assets <lb/>Management in <lb/>Organizations) <lb/>知識管理 <lb/>相關課程 <lb/>競爭智慧 <lb/>(Competitive <lb/>Intelligence) <lb/>策略智慧 <lb/>(Strategic <lb/>Intelligence) <lb/>智慧資本 <lb/>(Intellectual <lb/>Capital) <lb/>其他 <lb/>相關課程 <lb/>University <lb/>of Michigan <lb/>School of <lb/>information <lb/>Network <lb/>Thinking; <lb/>Contextual <lb/>Inquiry and <lb/>Project <lb/>Management <lb/>University <lb/>of North <lb/>Carolina at <lb/>Chapel Hill <lb/>School of <lb/>information and <lb/>Library Science <lb/>○△ <lb/>(Special <lb/>Libraries and <lb/>Knowledge <lb/>Management) <lb/>University <lb/>of Ottawa <lb/>School of <lb/>information studies <lb/>Knowledge in <lb/>Organization <lb/>University <lb/>of Puerto <lb/>Rico <lb/>Graduate School of <lb/>Science and <lb/>Information <lb/>Technology School <lb/>(EGCTI) <lb/>Information, <lb/>knowledge <lb/>and society/ <lb/>Information <lb/>technology <lb/>and <lb/>knowledge <lb/>University <lb/>of South <lb/>Carolina <lb/>School of Library <lb/>and Information <lb/>Science <lb/>○△ <lb/>(Knowledge <lb/>Management <lb/>for Library <lb/>and <lb/>Information <lb/>Professionals) <lb/>○□ <lb/>(Strategic <lb/>Intelligence for <lb/>Information <lb/>Professionals) <lb/>University <lb/>of Tennessee <lb/>School of <lb/>Information Sciences <lb/>○△ <lb/>(Knowledge <lb/>Management <lb/>for <lb/>Information <lb/>Professionals) <lb/>University <lb/>of Toronto <lb/>Faculty of <lb/>information <lb/>△ <lb/>Knowledge <lb/>Management <lb/>and Systems <lb/>Studying <lb/>Information <lb/>and <lb/>Knowledge <lb/>Practices <lb/>註 1： 印第安那大學系所名稱變更資訊如下：Our school merges two leading Indiana University schools: the <lb/>School of Informatics and the School of Library and Information Science。 <lb/>註 2： 表格中註記「○」表示開設相關課程，若課程名稱有些微差異，即在括弧中標註完整課程名稱。表格 <lb/>中註記「△」 ，表示該課程資訊納入知識管理課程內容分析。表格中註記「□」 ，表示該課程資訊納入 <lb/>競爭智慧課程內容分析。 <lb/></body>

			<page>32 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Library and Information Science 40(2) ：23 -46(October, 2014) <lb/></note>

			<body>知識管理碩士學位課程內容 <lb/>「知識管理」除了是各校開設之典型課程名稱之 <lb/>外，本研究選定之 20 所學校中，其中有兩校不僅開 <lb/>設「知識管理」課程，進一步提供專業學程或學位。 <lb/>Dominican University 提供圖書資訊科學碩士學位之 <lb/>知識管理專業學程 (Master of Library and Information <lb/>Science, Knowledge Management Certificate)[4]，而 <lb/>Kent State University 不僅提供知識管理專業學程 <lb/>[5]，更進一步提供知識管理碩士學位(Master of <lb/>Science, Knowledge Management)[6]。 <lb/>Dominican University 之知識管理學程科目包括網 <lb/>際 網 路 基 礎 與 設 計 ( Internet Fundamentals and <lb/>Design) 、資訊政策(Information Policy) 、組織分析 <lb/>(Organizational Analysis) 、知識管理、巨量資料與 <lb/>競爭智慧(Big Data and Competitive Intelligence)等 <lb/>課程。並於學程介紹中提及未來可擔任的職位為知 <lb/>識管理師、分類師、內容管理師、競爭智慧專業人 <lb/>員、資料管理師。 <lb/>Kent State University 開設之課程科目包括知識管 <lb/>理基礎原則(Foundational Principles of Knowledge <lb/>Management )、 知 識 評 價 及 評 鑑 ( Knowledge <lb/>Assessment and Evaluation) 、企業流程管理 (Business <lb/>Process Management )、 知 識 稽 核 ( Knowledge <lb/>Audit) 、知識管理成熟模型 (Knowledge Management <lb/>Maturity Modeling) 、組織文化評估(Organizational <lb/>Culture Assessment) 、社群實踐(Communities of <lb/>Practice) 、商業故事敘述(Business Narrative and <lb/>Storytelling ) 、知識社會之知識城市(Knowledge <lb/>Cities for a Knowledge Society) 。課程內容多元且將 <lb/>知識管理之各項課程單元以個別課程講授，可較深 <lb/>入探索其要素。 <lb/>盛小平與劉泳潔(2009)曾比較前述兩所學校及 <lb/>University of Oklahoma 之知識管理碩士學位課程差 <lb/>異，並說明如下數項特色： (1)美國大學認同知識 <lb/>管理為一門專業學科，且落實於教育體系中。 (2) <lb/>課程體系包括核心課程、限選修課程、任選課程等 <lb/>三大系列。 (3)領域範圍廣泛，包括管理、組織行 <lb/>為、人工智慧、系統工程、知識技術、心理學等多 <lb/>樣化的面向。 <lb/>知識管理相關課程定位及課程目標內容 <lb/>分析 <lb/>圖書資訊學教育重視訓練資訊專業人員，如何在 <lb/>最佳時間給予適合的讀者最合用的資訊。在此科際 <lb/>整合與知識經濟時代，傳統資訊資源的服務方式與 <lb/>內容已面臨挑戰，首當其衝的是專門或企業圖書館 <lb/>員，當服務機構已導入知識管理，勢必要因應組織 <lb/>環境的變革，更何況，當今倡導知識管理已不限於 <lb/>商業機構，政府、學術等非營利型機構亦為提升效 <lb/>能而導入知識管理，設置知識管理課程於圖書資訊 <lb/>學相關學校實有其必要性，如何將資訊服務轉型為 <lb/>知識服務應為其主要目標。此外，圖書館管理與行 <lb/>政也應融入知識管理概念，以提升人員創新力與組 <lb/>織整體效益。因此，知識管理於圖書資訊學教育之 <lb/>定位主要為強化資訊服務深度，亦為圖書館(資訊 <lb/>服務機構)管理提供轉型與質變的方法。 <lb/>課程內容分析資料來源來自 14 校之「知識管理」 <lb/>(共 12 校)與「知識資產管理」 (共 2 校)課程簡 <lb/>述及大綱資訊，其他相關課程名稱如「知識網絡」 、 <lb/>「知識結構與資訊專業人員」等課程資訊未納入內 <lb/>容分析。共計 14 所學校開設「知識管理」 、 「專門圖 <lb/>書館與知識管理」 、 「資訊專業人員的知識管理」 、 <lb/>「知識管理與系統」 等課程，但 Kent State University <lb/>為知識管理碩士學位課程，為知識管理之各項單 <lb/>元獨立開不同課程，而 University of Illinois 課程名 <lb/>稱同時包含 competitive intelligence 與 knowledge <lb/>management，因此前述 2 校未列入課程資訊內容分 <lb/>析。Drexel University 與 Louisiana State University <lb/>等 2 校未開設「知識管理」 ，另外開設「知識資產管 <lb/>理」 ，然而，經檢視其課程目標後，發現其「知識資 <lb/>產管理」課程內容雷同於「知識管理」 。因此，整併 <lb/>該兩校之「知識資產管理」課程內容於「知識管理」 <lb/>課程內容分析，結果呈現如表 3，本研究將內容區 <lb/>分為理論、範疇、組織文化與人力、流程、分享與 <lb/>網絡、評鑑、資訊科技與系統、實務與個案、競爭 <lb/>智 慧 與 知 識 服 務 等 九 項 構 面 。 相 較 於 先 前 研 究 <lb/>(Hazeri, Martin, &amp; Sarrafzadeh, 2009; 盛小平，2010) <lb/>之建議主軸方向一致，但構面分群方式略異。除了 <lb/>知識管理理論是多數學校提及的課程內容之外，知 <lb/>識分享與移轉，以及資訊科技等內容是較多學校(8 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">圖書館學與資訊科學 40(2) ：23 -46(民一○三年十月) </note>
				
				<page>33 <lb/></page>

			<body>至 11 校)於課程目標中提及的內容，其次是知識創 <lb/>造、獲取及編碼，亦分別有 5 至 6 校之課程簡述包 <lb/>含該主題。顯示系統應用、知識分享及知識流程等 <lb/>議題獲取多數學校認同其內容重要性。另外，加拿 <lb/>大 University of Toronto 的課程取向，延伸至企業管 <lb/>理、電子商務、醫療保健等領域之應用，較像是孫 <lb/>曉甯與儲節旺(2013)提及之管理學領域知識管理 <lb/>課程之特色。 <lb/>相較於資訊管理領域中，學者 Alavi 與 Leidner <lb/>(2001)為知識管理與知識管理系統提出不同觀點 <lb/>之意涵：心理狀態觀點、物件觀點、流程觀點、資 <lb/>訊存取觀點、能力觀點等。本研究所呈現之構面， <lb/>同樣重視流程之要素，而 Alavi 與 Leidner(2001) <lb/>較著重於資訊系統與能力建構之觀點，本研究則 <lb/>另提及分享與網絡、評鑑、實務與個案等構面的重 <lb/>要性。 <lb/>表 3 各校之知識管理課程目標內容分析表 <lb/>構 <lb/>面 <lb/>課程目標之內容 <lb/>原始文字 <lb/>課程目標包含該內容的學校 <lb/>理 <lb/>論 <lb/>知識管理理論 <lb/>theories and foundation of knowledge <lb/>management <lb/>Dominican, Simmons, Montreal, Alabama, <lb/>Alberta, Maryland, South Carolina, <lb/>Tennessee, Rutgers <lb/>知識管理資訊學 <lb/>KM informatics <lb/>Alberta <lb/>知識資產本質與使用 <lb/>nature and uses of knowledge-based assets; <lb/>fundamentals of KM <lb/>Drexel, LSU <lb/>範 <lb/>疇 <lb/>營利及非營利型組織 profit and non-profit organizations <lb/>Dominican, Maryland, North Carolina, <lb/>Rutgers <lb/>跨國企業 <lb/>multinationals <lb/>Rutgers <lb/>組 <lb/>織 <lb/>文 <lb/>化 <lb/>與 <lb/>人 <lb/>力 <lb/>組織文化 <lb/>organizational culture <lb/>McGill, Montreal, Alberta, Rutgers <lb/>知識管理、組織 <lb/>knowledge management and organization <lb/>Dominican, Maryland <lb/>組織學習 <lb/>organizational learning <lb/>Tennessee, LSU, Rutgers <lb/>組織改善 <lb/>organizational improvement <lb/>Simmons <lb/>群體知識 <lb/>collective knowledge <lb/>Montreal <lb/>人力資本 <lb/>human capital <lb/>Montreal <lb/>資訊專業人員 <lb/>information professionals, KM Profession <lb/>McGill, Montreal, Tennessee, Drexel, <lb/>LSU <lb/>流 <lb/>程 <lb/>知識資產相關產品、 <lb/>程序、市場及服務 <lb/>knowledge assets and their value to <lb/>organizations in terms of products, processes, <lb/>market and services. tangible and intangible <lb/>knowledge assets <lb/>Dominican, Rutgers, Maryland <lb/>隱性知識、顯性知識 tacit and explicit forms <lb/>McGill, Toronto, Rutgers <lb/>知識生命周期 <lb/>knowledge lifecycle <lb/>Tennessee <lb/>知識生態、資訊生態 knowledge ecologies, information ecology <lb/>Tennessee, LSU <lb/>知識創造 <lb/>knowledge creation <lb/>McGill, Simmons, Alabama, <lb/>Maryland, LSU, Rutgers <lb/>知識獲取 <lb/>knowledge acquisition, knowledge capture <lb/>Dominican, McGill, Simmons, <lb/>Maryland, LSU, Rutgers <lb/>知識編碼 <lb/>knowledge codification <lb/>McGill, Simmons, Toronto, LSU, Rutgers <lb/>知識保存 <lb/>knowledge preserve <lb/>Montreal <lb/>知識庫、知識資產 <lb/>Knowledge repositories, knowledge storage, <lb/>knowledge assets <lb/>Rutgers, Alberta, Drexel, LSU <lb/>知識散播 <lb/>knowledge dissemination <lb/>Dominican, Montreal <lb/></body>

			<page>34 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Library and Information Science 40(2) ：23 -46(October, 2014) <lb/></note>

			<body>表 3 各校之知識管理課程目標內容分析表(續) <lb/>構 <lb/>面 <lb/>課程目標之內容 <lb/>原始文字 <lb/>課程目標包含該內容的學校 <lb/>分 <lb/>享 <lb/>與 <lb/>網 <lb/>絡 <lb/>知識分享、知識移轉 <lb/>knowledge sharing and knowledge <lb/>transferring <lb/>McGill, Rutgers, Montreal, Alabama, <lb/>Maryland, Tennessee, LSU, Rutgers <lb/>知識整合 <lb/>how knowledge is synthesized <lb/>Alabama <lb/>實務社群 <lb/>communities of practice <lb/>Simmons, Tennessee, LSU, Rutgers <lb/>社會網絡 <lb/>social network <lb/>Simmons, Rutgers <lb/>評 <lb/>鑑 <lb/>知識稽核 <lb/>knowledge audits <lb/>Tennessee <lb/>知識評估與評鑑 <lb/>assessment, evaluation <lb/>Dominican, <lb/>資 <lb/>訊 <lb/>科 <lb/>技 <lb/>與 <lb/>系 <lb/>統 <lb/>資 訊 系 統 、 資 訊 科 <lb/>技、科技 <lb/>information systems, information <lb/>technology, technologies <lb/>McGill, Alabama, Alberta, Maryland, <lb/>South Carolina, Tennessee, Toronto, <lb/>Drexel, LSU, Rutgers <lb/>正式及非正式知識管 <lb/>理系統 <lb/>formal and informal knowledge <lb/>management systems <lb/>Drexel <lb/>商用資料庫及應用軟 <lb/>體 <lb/>analysis of commercially available <lb/>documents, databases and applications <lb/>packages; contemporary knowledge <lb/>management software; intranet and <lb/>groupware <lb/>Dominican, Simmons, Maryland, North <lb/>Carolina <lb/>特定資訊系統(法律 <lb/>資訊系統、健康資訊 <lb/>系 統 、 人 類 社 會 系 <lb/>統) 、決策支援系統 <lb/>legal information systems, health <lb/>information systems, human social systems <lb/>Maryland, Toronto, Rutgers <lb/>本體論、語意網 <lb/>Ontologies and the semantic web <lb/>Toronto <lb/>實 <lb/>務 <lb/>與 <lb/>個 <lb/>案 <lb/>最佳實務 <lb/>best practices <lb/>Dominican, Montreal, Alabama, Maryland <lb/>知識管理專案設計及 <lb/>導入 <lb/>the design and execution of knowledge <lb/>management projects. <lb/>Dominican, Maryland <lb/>個案研究 <lb/>case study <lb/>Simmons, Montreal, Alabama, Alberta, <lb/>Rutgers <lb/>競 <lb/>爭 <lb/>智 <lb/>慧 <lb/>與 <lb/>知 <lb/>識 <lb/>服 <lb/>務 <lb/>競爭智慧 <lb/>competitive intelligence <lb/>Alabama <lb/>智慧資本 <lb/>intellectual capital <lb/>Maryland, North Carolina, Tennessee, <lb/>LSU, Rutgers <lb/>策略規劃 <lb/>Strategic planning <lb/>North Carolina <lb/>加值手段 <lb/>Value-added measures <lb/>North Carolina <lb/>客製服務 <lb/>Tailoring services <lb/>North Carolina <lb/>其 他 應 用 ( 企 業 管 <lb/>理、電子商務、醫療 <lb/>保健、媒體、教育) <lb/>enterprise management, e-commerce, <lb/>healthcare, media, and education <lb/>Toronto <lb/>註 1：Alabama 之知識管理課程先修課為必修課「Information Technology」 。 <lb/>註 2：Alberta 需先修 3 門必修課。 <lb/>註 3： KSU 為知識管理碩士學位課程，為知識管理之各項單元獨立開不同課程，因此未列入本表分析。 <lb/>University of Illinois 課程名稱同時包含 competitive intelligence 與 knowledge management，亦未列入本 <lb/>表分析。 <lb/>註 4：North Carolina at Chapel Hill 之知識管理先修課為「Management for Information Professionals」 。 <lb/>註 5：Drexel University 之知識資產管理先修課為「Information Services Organizations」 。 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">圖書館學與資訊科學 40(2) ：23 -46(民一○三年十月) </note>
				
				<page>35 <lb/></page>

			<body>表 4 競爭智慧與圖書資訊工作範疇比較表 <lb/>項目 <lb/>競爭智慧[1] <lb/>圖書資訊 <lb/>職稱 <lb/>競爭智慧分析師 <lb/>圖書館員、檔案管理員、文件管理員、資訊 <lb/>專門人員、編目員、資訊科學家，研究員 <lb/>資訊環境 <lb/>不穩定 <lb/>相對穩定 <lb/>資料型態 <lb/>不穩定與穩定 <lb/>動態與靜態 <lb/>非結構化與結構化 <lb/>大部分穩定 <lb/>大部分靜態 <lb/>大部分結構化 <lb/>資料可信度 <lb/>低 <lb/>高 <lb/>資料處理風格 <lb/>直覺／主觀 <lb/>傳統／客觀 <lb/>急迫性 <lb/>高 <lb/>低 <lb/>典型的活動 <lb/>分析 <lb/>摘要 <lb/>聯結 <lb/>分類 <lb/>組裝與綜整 <lb/>(assembling/synthesizing) <lb/>資料處理與管理 <lb/>評鑑與分級 <lb/>資料探勘 <lb/>推理 <lb/>索引 <lb/>假設檢定 <lb/>組織 <lb/>組織 <lb/>查詢 <lb/>選取 <lb/>存取 <lb/>搜尋與探源(sourcing) <lb/>翻譯與機器翻譯 <lb/>確認與驗證 <lb/>文字辨識 <lb/>1： 原文用語雖為 Intelligence analysis (IA)，但該文作者提及競爭智慧為最多圖書資訊相關學校採納的課 <lb/>程名稱(詳見 Jin and Bouthillier (2012)文中圖 3) ，因此，本表格改以競爭智慧稱之。 <lb/>前一節提及兩校提供知識管理專業學程或碩士學 <lb/>位，其中 Dominican University 的知識管理課程於表 <lb/>2 中顯示其包括面向相當完整，但未包納競爭智慧 <lb/>與知識服務、分享與網絡等構面，該兩構面的內容 <lb/>應包納於其他獨立開設的課程內容，如巨量資料與 <lb/>競爭智慧等課程。而 Kent State University 之網站僅 <lb/>提供課程名稱列表，未提供課程目標內容或大綱， <lb/>因此無法針對有無設置知識管理碩士學位之學校所 <lb/>開設之知識管理課程內容比較其異同。但由前一節 <lb/>所述之 Kent State University(KSU)的課程列表， <lb/>實已將表 2 呈現之分項課程單元分別開授專門課 <lb/>程，KSU 更著重於知識評鑑，開設了 2 門相關課程。 <lb/>另外，表 3 並未呈現說故事內容於知識管理課程 <lb/>中，而 KSU 卻開了一門「商業故事敘述」課程，顯 <lb/>示 KSU 之知識管理碩士學位課程之特色。 <lb/>競爭智慧課程定位與課程目標內容分析 <lb/>圖書資訊學教育偏重於靜態且結構化的資訊處 <lb/>理，而競爭智慧觸及的範疇多為動態且非結構化的 <lb/>資訊，表 4 呈現 Jin 與 Bouthillier(2012)於競爭智 <lb/>慧與圖書資訊工作範疇比較，顯示圖書資訊重客觀 <lb/>與正確，但較缺時效，而競爭智慧重時效，往往以 <lb/>直覺與主觀來判定資訊的有用性。當今提供靜態資 <lb/>訊已無法滿足所有資訊需求，資訊專業人員需更進 <lb/>一步綜整分析，提供即時之動態資訊以利機構主管 <lb/>決策。因此，競爭智慧課程於圖書資訊學校課程定 <lb/>位即在於以圖書資訊學教育為其基石，強化資訊專 <lb/>業人員將資訊快速轉化為決策資訊的能力，以補充 <lb/>其動態資訊處理能力。 <lb/>合計 5 所學校開設「競爭智慧」與 2 所學校開設 <lb/>「策略智慧」 ，但因 University of Illinois 開設課程名 <lb/>稱同時包含 knowledge management 與 competitive <lb/>intelligence，因此未納入該校課程資訊於內容分析。 <lb/>本研究依 6 校之課程目標及大綱內容分析結果詳見 <lb/>表 5。本研究綜整如下構面：策略理論、組織定位、 <lb/>角色及任務、智慧產品及週期、時效、利害關係人 <lb/>之競合關係、法律倫理與環境、價值與需求、新技 <lb/>術、評鑑、問題解決方案與決策、趨勢、系統安全、 <lb/>國家安全、危機與威脅、認識論與有限的理性等。 <lb/></body>

			<page>36 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Library and Information Science 40(2) ：23 -46(October, 2014) <lb/></note>

			<body>其中法律倫理與環境、評鑑、問題解決方案與決策 <lb/>等構面是較多校重複提及的內容，顯示多數學校認 <lb/>同前述議題之重要性。 <lb/>相較於知識管理課程，相近的主題如下：如智慧 <lb/>產品及週期等流程構面、新技術、評鑑、實務與個 <lb/>案等議題。然而，競爭智慧課程範疇更廣，不僅包 <lb/>含個人或組織之策略管理議題，亦論及資訊戰與國 <lb/>家安全；除了個案實務外，強調問題解決方案，以 <lb/>更接近決策。甚至進一步提醒人類犯錯的可能性等 <lb/>負面因素，避免落入認知偏誤。 <lb/>表 5 各校之競爭智慧課程目標內容分析表 <lb/>構 <lb/>面 <lb/>課程目標之內容 <lb/>原始文字 <lb/>課程目標包含該內容的學校 <lb/>策 <lb/>略 <lb/>理 <lb/>論 <lb/>理論綜覽 <lb/>overview of CI theories; the nature, <lb/>evolution and purpose of modern <lb/>intelligence services, <lb/>Dominican, Indiana <lb/>競爭策略 <lb/>the fundamentals of competitive strategy <lb/>Indiana <lb/>波特的五力競爭分析 <lb/>模型 <lb/>Porter&apos;s Five Forces Model of competition <lb/>Indiana <lb/>瓦解 <lb/>disruption(The Innovator&apos;s Dilemma) <lb/>Indiana <lb/>破壞式創造之創業者 Disruptive Entrepreneurs <lb/>Indiana <lb/>策略的驚奇 <lb/>Strategic Surprise <lb/>Indiana <lb/>智慧力 <lb/>Intelligence Power <lb/>Indiana <lb/>系統理論 <lb/>systems theory <lb/>Indiana <lb/>組 <lb/>織 <lb/>定 <lb/>位 <lb/>、 <lb/>角 <lb/>色 <lb/>及 <lb/>任 <lb/>務 <lb/>角色及任務 <lb/>the role played by intelligence-be it <lb/>operational, tactical or strategic-in <lb/>everyday life <lb/>Indiana <lb/>組織結構 <lb/>organizational structure <lb/>Indiana <lb/>營利及非營利型組織 profit and non-profit organizations <lb/>McGill <lb/>智 <lb/>慧 <lb/>產 <lb/>品 <lb/>及 <lb/>週 <lb/>期 <lb/>與 <lb/>時 <lb/>效 <lb/>現行資訊分析 <lb/>analysis of existing information; competitor <lb/>intelligence analysis <lb/>Drexel, Indiana <lb/>開放資訊 <lb/>open source information <lb/>South Carolina <lb/>分析及整合不同類型 <lb/>資訊 <lb/>analyze and integrate various types of <lb/>information(patents, financial, production, <lb/>market) <lb/>Drexel <lb/>定義、類型、產品與 <lb/>服務 <lb/>Definitions of intelligence. Forms of <lb/>intelligence. Intelligence goods and services. <lb/>Indiana <lb/>獲取、組織與貯存資 <lb/>訊 <lb/>acquiring, organizing and storing <lb/>information; <lb/>McGill, Rutgers <lb/>發展與散播智慧產品 <lb/>developing and distributing intelligence <lb/>products <lb/>McGill <lb/>智慧週期 <lb/>The intelligence cycle: functions, structures, <lb/>roles, techniques, tasks, and products <lb/>Indiana <lb/>即時處理新知識 <lb/>efficiently discovering, developing and <lb/>delivering timely, relevant new knowledge <lb/>Dominican <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">圖書館學與資訊科學 40(2) ：23 -46(民一○三年十月) </note>
				
				<page>37 <lb/></page>

			<body>表 5 各校之競爭智慧課程目標內容分析表(續) <lb/>構 <lb/>面 <lb/>課程目標之內容 <lb/>原始文字 <lb/>課程目標包含該內容的學校 <lb/>利 <lb/>害 <lb/>關 <lb/>係 <lb/>人 <lb/>之 <lb/>競 <lb/>合 <lb/>關 <lb/>係 <lb/>個人、公司、社群、 <lb/>國家 <lb/>individual citizen, company, community, or <lb/>country <lb/>Indiana <lb/>分析競爭者、顧客、 <lb/>市場、趨勢、新興技 <lb/>術 <lb/>Analyzing competitors, customers, markets, <lb/>trends, emergent technologies. <lb/>Indiana <lb/>公司競爭 <lb/>corporate competition <lb/>Indiana <lb/>合作式智慧 <lb/>cooperative intelligence <lb/>McGill <lb/>法 <lb/>律 <lb/>倫 <lb/>理 <lb/>、 <lb/>環 <lb/>境 <lb/>與 <lb/>趨 <lb/>勢 <lb/>法律及倫理議題 <lb/>Legal and ethical aspects <lb/>Drexel, McGill, Dominican <lb/>環境掃描 <lb/>environmental scanning; external environment South Carolina, Dominican, Indiana <lb/>企業趨勢 <lb/>spotting business trends <lb/>Dominican, Indiana <lb/>價 <lb/>值 <lb/>與 <lb/>需 <lb/>求 <lb/>資訊服務價值 <lb/>value of information services <lb/>Rutgers <lb/>辨識需求 <lb/>identifying competitive intelligence needs <lb/>McGill, Rutgers <lb/>新 <lb/>技 <lb/>術 <lb/>新興技術 <lb/>emergent technologies <lb/>Indiana <lb/>視覺化技術 <lb/>visualization techniques <lb/>Dominican <lb/>巨量資料分析 <lb/>big data analytics <lb/>Dominican <lb/>社群網路科技與革命 <lb/>Social Networking Technology and <lb/>Revolutions <lb/>Indiana <lb/>評 <lb/>鑑 <lb/>品質評估 <lb/>assessment of quality; determining quality <lb/>of research/education <lb/>Rutgers, Dominican <lb/>資訊稽核 <lb/>information audits <lb/>McGill, Rutgers <lb/>資訊評鑑與綜整 <lb/>information evaluation and synthesis; ways <lb/>to assess the credibility of evidence and <lb/>determine <lb/>the reliability of sources and channels, <lb/>South Carolina, Indiana <lb/>問 <lb/>題 <lb/>解 <lb/>決 <lb/>方 <lb/>案 <lb/>與 <lb/>決 <lb/>策 <lb/>問題管理 <lb/>issues management <lb/>South Carolina <lb/>最佳實務 <lb/>best practices <lb/>Dominican <lb/>個案研究 <lb/>casestudy project <lb/>Indiana <lb/>複雜商業需求之解決 <lb/>方案；有效決策 <lb/>solutions to complex business needs; <lb/>effective decision making <lb/>Illinois; Dominican <lb/>決策 <lb/>decision-making <lb/>Drexel, Rutgers <lb/>標竿 <lb/>benchmarking <lb/>Indiana <lb/></body>

			<page>38 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Library and Information Science 40(2) ：23 -46(October, 2014) <lb/></note>

			<body>表 5 <lb/>構 <lb/>面 <lb/>課程目標之內容 <lb/>原始文字 <lb/>課程目標包含該內容的學校 <lb/>系 <lb/>統 <lb/>全 <lb/>資訊戰爭；非對稱資 <lb/>訊戰；虛擬戰 <lb/>information warfare, asymmetric warfare, <lb/>cyber war <lb/>Indiana <lb/>系統安全 <lb/>systems security <lb/>Indiana <lb/>國 <lb/>家 <lb/>安 <lb/>全 <lb/>國家安全 <lb/>national security <lb/>Indiana <lb/>恐怖主義；反恐主義 <lb/>terrorism and counterterrorism intelligence <lb/>to national security <lb/>Indiana <lb/>政府政策 <lb/>government policy <lb/>Indiana <lb/>預防疾病 <lb/>preventing diseases <lb/>Dominican <lb/>策略性軍事智慧 <lb/>strategic military intelligence <lb/>Indiana <lb/>危 <lb/>機 <lb/>與 <lb/>威 <lb/>脅 <lb/>對企業及國家經濟的 <lb/>威脅 <lb/>Threats to corporate and national economic <lb/>wellbeing <lb/>Indiana <lb/>打擊犯罪 <lb/>combating crimes, globalization of crime <lb/>Dominican, Indiana <lb/>產業間諜 <lb/>Industrial Espionage <lb/>Indiana <lb/>網路間碟 <lb/>cyber-espionage <lb/>Indiana <lb/>公共關係危機 <lb/>managing public relations crises <lb/>Dominican <lb/>認 <lb/>識 <lb/>論 <lb/>與 <lb/>有 <lb/>限 <lb/>的 <lb/>理 <lb/>性 <lb/>認識論 <lb/>Epistemology <lb/>Indiana <lb/>失誤；人類判斷力極 <lb/>限 <lb/>Intelligence failures and pathology; the <lb/>limitations of human judgment <lb/>Indiana <lb/>認知偏誤與文化盲點 Cognitive biases and cultural blind-spots <lb/>Indiana <lb/>黑天鵝本質，專家知 <lb/>識的似非而是 <lb/>The nature of &apos;black swans&apos; and the paradox <lb/>of expertise. <lb/>Indiana <lb/>註 1：South Carolina 先修課為 Online information services 或 Business information sources and services。 <lb/>註 2：合併 Indiana 與 South Carolina 之策略智慧(Strategic Intelligence)課程目標內容分析於本表。 <lb/>註 3： Indiana 提供較詳細的課程大綱內容，亦併入本表分析。2011-2012 年開課之課程大綱資料來源： <lb/>http://www.ils.indiana.edu/syllabi/fall_2011/S555_Choksy.pdf, <lb/>http://www.ils.indiana.edu/syllabi/fall_2012/S555_Cronin.pdf(上網日期：2014 年 2 月 24 日) 。 <lb/>註 4： University of Illinois 課程名稱同時包含 competitive intelligence 與 knowledge management，未列入本表 <lb/>分析。 <lb/>知識管理與競爭智慧課程關係 <lb/>競爭智慧課程內容著重於外在驅力之資訊整合， <lb/>而知識管理則肇因於內在驅力之知識綜效，圖 1 之 <lb/>核心圓內容為 Shelfer 與 Goodrum(2000)界定兩課 <lb/>程間重點與關係，競爭智慧整合外部資訊投入知識 <lb/>管理，知識管理達成內部綜效後，再引領競爭智慧 <lb/>之策略議題，由內外在驅力達成其策略連結之關 <lb/>係。本研究延伸該兩課程關係於圖書資訊其他相關 <lb/>課程之關連分析，以圖 1 方型區域之漸層色表達該 <lb/>兩項課程與其他課程之強弱關連，強相關為圖書館 <lb/>管理與行政、企業資訊服務、專門／企業圖書館， <lb/>弱相關為學術、公共、法律圖書館，以及資訊行為、 <lb/>資訊系統。 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">圖書館學與資訊科學 40(2) ：23 -46(民一○三年十月) </note>
				
				<page>39 <lb/></page>

			<body>圖 1 知識管理與競爭智慧課程之關係，及其與圖書資訊學相關課程之關連程度 <lb/>核心圓之資訊來源：Shelfer, K. &amp; Goodrum, A. (2000). Competitive intelligence as an extension of library education, <lb/>Journal of Education for Library and Information Science, 41(4), 357. Figure 1. The KMCI <lb/>relationship. <lb/>綜合討論 <lb/>整體而言，美國圖書資訊學相關學校之知識管理 <lb/>課程目標於各主題分布均勻，未如孫曉甯與儲節旺 <lb/>(2013)提及中國圖書資訊學相關學校重知識組 <lb/>織、圖書館知識服務、資源共享、知識圖譜等現象。 <lb/>本研究綜整知識管理課程內容為九項構面，與先 <lb/>前 Kigongo-Bukenya 與 Kaddu(2011)及盛小平 <lb/>(2010)之研究比較如表 6。Kigongo-Bukenya 與 <lb/>Kaddu(2011)之研究未特別提及實務及個案，而盛 <lb/>小平(2010)則提及該單元為最高優先。然而，盛 <lb/>小平(2010)未特別提及組織文化與人力、競爭智 <lb/>慧與知識服務之兩構面。 <lb/>本研究綜整知識管理與競爭智慧課程名稱、圖書 <lb/>資訊學程定位、學分數、目標、內容及課程單元、 <lb/>教學設計等項目比較於表 7。因開設知識管理系所 <lb/>數較多，其課程名稱較競爭智慧多元。圖書資訊學 <lb/>教育之定位議題中，兩項課程都著重於強化資訊服 <lb/>務的深度及速度，但知識管理亦可做為圖書館管理 <lb/>轉型之法。兩項課程於美國圖書資訊相關系所都是 <lb/>3 學分，唯 University of Illinois 開設應用企業研究課 <lb/>程(合併競爭智慧與知識管理)為 4 學分。課程目標 <lb/>於知識管理著重於組織知識之創造至再利用等議 <lb/>題，而競爭智慧強調整合外部新知以轉化決策資訊。 <lb/>競爭智慧課程之 13 項構面中，無法對應知識管理 <lb/>課程構面為認識論與有限的理性、法律倫理、環境 <lb/>與趨勢、國家安全、危機與威脅等構面，除了呼應 <lb/>表 1 綜整之競爭智慧重外部環境分析之重點之外， <lb/>亦重視需意識到人類有限的智慧等議題。 <lb/>可對應之構面中，其內容不全然相同，競爭智慧 <lb/>強調策略理論，知識管理另有其核心理論。知識管 <lb/>理強調組織文化的營造，建立學習型組織，競爭智 <lb/>慧並未強調組織內部文化經營的因素。知識管理的 <lb/>流程，並未特別強調價值與需求，競爭智慧則重時 <lb/>效。知識管理的「分享與網絡」雖對應了競爭智慧 <lb/>的「利害關係人之競合關係」 ，然而其重點不同，前 <lb/>者重分享與合作，後者重覺察內外部關係人，不僅 <lb/>合作，亦重競爭關係。因此，導入新技術之議題， <lb/>更重視系統安全，以避免競爭者伺機竊取重要資 <lb/>訊。知識管理之「實務與個案」雖對應了競爭智慧 <lb/>之「問題解決方案與決策」 ，然而後者更接近主管所 <lb/>需的決策資訊。 <lb/></body>

			<page>40 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Library and Information Science 40(2) ：23 -46(October, 2014) <lb/></note>

			<body>由於僅少數學校提供完整課程大綱資訊，教學方 <lb/>法與作業設計項目參照內容極少，知識管理課程來 <lb/>自 3 校(詳見表 7 下方註解) ，競爭智慧來自 Indiana <lb/>University 之 2 份課程大綱，顯示知識管理重個案與 <lb/>最佳實務之討論，作業除了書面報告，另有資料庫 <lb/>系統相關作業，方式多元。 <lb/>表 6 知識管理課程單元比較表 <lb/>本研究 <lb/>Kaddu, 2011 <lb/>盛小平，2010 <lb/>理論 <lb/>定義 <lb/>4_基礎理論、2_戰略與方法(如 <lb/>知識創新與經營戰略) <lb/>範疇 <lb/>角色及任務 <lb/>組織文化與人力 <lb/>資訊及知識能力、人力因素 <lb/>流程 <lb/>程序(過程與方法) <lb/>3_過程(如知識創造、應用、共 <lb/>享等，及智力資本價值鏈) <lb/>分享與網絡 <lb/>資訊及知識網絡 <lb/>評鑑 <lb/>衡量議題(評估導入效能) <lb/>資訊科技與系統 <lb/>資訊及知識技術 <lb/>5_關鍵技術 (如隱性知識至顯性 <lb/>知識轉化技術) <lb/>實務與個案 <lb/>1_實踐與應用(如案例分析) 、 <lb/>競爭智慧與知識服務 <lb/>註：盛小平(2010)之各課程單元前加註之數字為該研究調查結果之需求優先序。 <lb/>表 7 知識管理與競爭智慧課程名稱、圖書資訊學程定位、學分數、目標、內容及課程單元、教學設計比較表 <lb/>項目 <lb/>知識管理 <lb/>競爭智慧 <lb/>其他相關 <lb/>課程名稱 <lb/>組織中的知識管理、知識資產管理、知識網 <lb/>絡、知識結構與資訊專業人員、專門圖書館 <lb/>與知識管理、圖書館資訊專業人員知識管 <lb/>理、知識管理與系統 <lb/>策略智慧、巨量資料與競爭智慧、資訊專業人員 <lb/>策略智慧 <lb/>圖書資訊 <lb/>學程定位 <lb/>主要為強化資訊服務的深度，亦為圖書館 <lb/>(資訊服務機構) 管理提供轉型與質變的方 <lb/>法。 <lb/>以圖書資訊學教育為其基石，強化資訊專業人員 <lb/>將資訊快速轉化為決策資訊的能力，以補充其動 <lb/>態資訊處理能力。 <lb/>學分數[1] 3 學分 <lb/>3 學分 <lb/>目標 <lb/>了解組織中顯性及隱性知識之創造、獲取、 <lb/>分享、再造、保存、再利用等過程，重視組 <lb/>織成員的知識成長，以適應內外部環境之變 <lb/>化。 <lb/>應用合法及符合倫理的方法，有效率地發掘、發 <lb/>展、綜整分析並即時傳送外部新知，以利整合企 <lb/>業趨勢、管理公共關係、危機處理，以促進有效 <lb/>的決策。 <lb/>內容／課程 <lb/>單元(整合 <lb/>表 3 與表 5 <lb/>之構面)[2] <lb/>認識論與有限的理性 <lb/>理論 <lb/>策略理論 <lb/>範疇(含營利及非營利型組織) <lb/>組織定位(含營利及非營利型組織) <lb/>組織文化與人力 <lb/>組織定位、角色及任務 <lb/>流程 <lb/>價值與需求 <lb/>智慧產品及週期與時效 <lb/>分享與網絡(知識分享、社會網絡) <lb/>利害關係人(個人、公司、社群、國家；競爭者、 <lb/>顧客、市場、趨勢、新興技術)之競合關係 <lb/>評鑑 <lb/>評鑑 <lb/>資訊科技與系統 <lb/>新技術 <lb/>系統安全 <lb/>實務與個案 <lb/>問題解決方案與決策 <lb/>競爭智慧與知識服務 <lb/>法律倫理、環境與趨勢 <lb/>國家安全 <lb/>危機與威脅 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">圖書館學與資訊科學 40(2) ：23 -46(民一○三年十月) </note>
				
				<page>41 <lb/></page>

			<body>表 7 知識管理與競爭智慧課程名稱、圖書資訊學程定位、學分數、目標、內容及課程單元、教學設計比較表 <lb/>(續) <lb/>項目 <lb/>知識管理 <lb/>競爭智慧 <lb/>教學方法／ <lb/>作業設計[3] <lb/>教學方法包括提供講義、講授、書報討論、 <lb/>個案研究、最佳實務個案及組織經驗討論。 <lb/>作業設計包含主題論文、應用資料庫管理系 <lb/>統建立課堂成員之黃頁薄 (含閱讀興趣等資 <lb/>訊) 、決策支援系統分析之組別報告、線上 <lb/>學習之優缺點分析報告等。 <lb/>教學方法包括講授、課堂討論、團體討論、校外 <lb/>活動等。作業設計為解題書目作業、期末報告 (可 <lb/>自選以學術論文、競爭者分析或顧問報告等不同 <lb/>之報告形式) 。 <lb/>註 1： 僅 University of Illinois 開設應用企業研究課程(合併競爭智慧與知識管理)為 4 學分，其他學校均為 <lb/>3 學分課程。 <lb/>註 2： 內容／課程單元之部分文字以斜體與底線表示無法直接對應其概念。 <lb/>註 3： 多數學校未提供教學設計等資訊，僅少數學校提供教學方法及作業設計等內容。知識管理課程之教學 <lb/>方法內容，合併 University of Alberta 與 Universite de Montreal 提供教學方法之相關資訊。作業設計內 <lb/>容，僅 Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey 提供詳細課程大綱，摘錄其作業設計相關資訊。競爭 <lb/>智慧課程之教學方法／作業設計內容來自 Indiana University 提供之 2 份課程大綱內容。 <lb/>結論 <lb/>綜整美國圖書館學會認可之 63 所圖書資訊學相 <lb/>關學校中，共計 20 所提供知識管理與競爭智慧相關 <lb/>課程。近 10 年開設知識管理課程數增加，此外， <lb/>Dominican University 與 Kent State University 更進 <lb/>一步設置知識管理專業學程及專業碩士學位，顯示 <lb/>知識管理於圖書資訊學相關學校之重視程度日益 <lb/>增加。 <lb/>本研究綜整 14 所學校之知識管理課程目標內容 <lb/>分析，研究結果區分為理論、範疇、組織文化與人 <lb/>力、流程、分享與網絡、評鑑、資訊科技與系統、 <lb/>實務與個案、競爭智慧與知識服務等九項構面，與 <lb/>先前研究之核心要項差異不大。 <lb/>提供競爭智慧相關課程學校共計 7 所，本研究綜 <lb/>整其 6 校之課程內容呈現如下構面：策略理論、組 <lb/>織定位、角色及任務、智慧產品及週期、利害關係 <lb/>人之競合關係、法律倫理與環境、價值與需求、新 <lb/>技術、評鑑、問題解決方案與決策、系統安全、國 <lb/>家安全、危機與威脅、認識論與有限的理性等。相 <lb/>較於知識管理課程內容，競爭智慧更重外部環境分 <lb/>析，強調問題解決方案，以更接近決策。 <lb/>知 識 管 理 與 競 爭 智 慧 課 程 內 容 各 有 其 特 色 ， <lb/>University of Alabama 曾將若干競爭智慧要素融入 <lb/>知識管理課程中(詳見表 3) ，建議圖書資訊學相關 <lb/>學校於兩種課程可輪流於不同學期開課，求其互補 <lb/>性，以增強圖書資訊學相關學校畢業生具備相關能 <lb/>力以因應現今多變的社會環境。 <lb/>本研究比較知識管理與競爭智慧課程名稱、圖書 <lb/>資訊學程定位、學分數、目標、內容及課程單元、 <lb/>教學設計等議題，亦探索了兩項課程間關係，可提 <lb/>供圖書資訊學相關系所課程設計之參考資訊。 <lb/>儘管先前曾多篇研究探討知識管理於圖書資訊學 <lb/>相關學校設置的問題，結論往往呈現教育工作者之 <lb/>樂觀心態，即理應加入知識管理各面向之重要課題 <lb/>於課程設計中。然而，Rehman 與 Chaudhry(2005) <lb/>曾指出一個關鍵議題，即圖書館相關專業人員往往 <lb/>較為保守，並非真心想投入知識管理，只因競爭對 <lb/>手也投入相關事務，他不得不如此做，而不是真心 <lb/>地想要了解知識管理的價值，以致於產生文化的掙 <lb/>扎。因此，教育工作者常於理想層面去考慮相關議 <lb/>題，然而，理想與實際往往有差距，如何將理想落 <lb/>實於教育現場，而教育的成效又能進一步應用於改 <lb/>善職場實務，實為身為圖書資訊學教育工作者之課 <lb/>題與終身志業。 <lb/>本研究建議知識管理與競爭智慧都不應紙上談 <lb/>兵，可由個案來引領學員體會該課程議題並可具體 <lb/>於日常生活中實踐。建議每堂課可以設計一個針對 <lb/></body>

			<page>42 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Library and Information Science 40(2) ：23 -46(October, 2014) <lb/></note>

			<body>該課程議題的個案討論，首先帶入該個案討論，誘 <lb/>發學員對於該課程單元主動學習的心態，以提升學 <lb/>習效益。另外，也建議圖書館學會未來辦理研習活 <lb/>動，除了為圖書館工作人員提供「知識管理個案」 <lb/>研習課程之外，也可為圖書資訊學教育工作者提供 <lb/>「哈佛式個案教學」工作坊，以增進教學技能。 <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">附註 <lb/>[1] 為兼顧用語一致性及忠於原文，文中若提及圖 <lb/>書館與資訊科學(Library and Information Science, <lb/>LIS) ，本文以「圖書資訊學」用語稱之，但若提及 <lb/>ALA-accredited Master&apos;s Programs in Library and <lb/>Information Studies，則以「美國圖書館學會認證之 <lb/>圖書館與資訊學碩士課程」 。 <lb/>[2] 63 所 學 校 清 單 請 見 http://www.ala.org/ <lb/>accreditedprograms/，上網日期：2014 年 3 月 12 日。 <lb/>[3] 查詢各主題專業課程於 ALA 認證學校之線上 <lb/>資料庫網址：http://www.ala.org/CFApps/lisdir/index. <lb/>cfm，上網日期：2014 年 3 月 12 日。 <lb/>[4] 請詳見 http://gslis.dom.edu/academics/certificates/ <lb/>knowledgemanagement ，上網日期：2014 年 3 月 12 日。 <lb/>[5] 請詳見 http://www.kent.edu/slis/km/km-certificate. <lb/>cfm，上網日期：2014 年 3 月 12 日。 <lb/>[6] 請詳見 http://www.kent.edu/slis/km/km-master-of <lb/>-science.cfm，上網日期：2014 年 3 月 12 日。 <lb/></div>
				
			<listBibl>參考文獻 <lb/>Al-Hawamdeh, S. (2005). Designing an interdisciplinary <lb/>graduate program in knowledge management. Journal <lb/>of the American Society for Information Science and <lb/>Technology, 56(11), 1200-1206. <lb/>Alavi, M. &amp; Leidner, D. E. (2001). Review: Knowledge <lb/>management and knowledge management systems: <lb/>conceptual foundations and research issues. MIS Quarterly, <lb/>25(1), 107-136. <lb/>Bouthillier, F. &amp; Dalkir, K. (2005). Knowledge management <lb/>and competitive intelligence: Examination of similarities, <lb/>differences and intersections. In Knowledge management: <lb/>Nurturing culture, innovation and technology: Proceedings <lb/>of the 2005 international conference on knowledge <lb/>management (Hawamdeh, S. Ed, pp. 603-610). New <lb/>Jersey: World Scientific Publishing. <lb/>Chaudhry, A.S. &amp; Higgins, S. (2003). On the need for <lb/>a multidisciplinary approach to education for <lb/>knowledge management. Library Review, 52(2), <lb/>65-69. <lb/>Davenport E., &amp; Cronin, B. (2000). Knowledge <lb/>management: Semantic drift or conceptual shift? <lb/>Journal of Education for Library and Information <lb/>Science, 41(4), 294-306. <lb/>Davenport, T. H., &amp; Prusak, L. (1998). Working <lb/>knowledge: How organizations manage what they <lb/>know. Boston: Harvard Business School Press. <lb/>Ghannay, J. C., &amp; Mamlouk, Z. B. A., (2012). Synergy <lb/>between competitive intelligence and knowledge <lb/>management. Journal of Intelligence Studies in <lb/>Business, 2(2), 23-34. <lb/>Hazeri, A., Martin, B. &amp; Sarrafzadeh, M. (2009). <lb/>Integration of knowledge management with the <lb/>library and information science curriculum: Some <lb/>professional perspectives. Journal of Education for <lb/>Library and Information Science, 50(3), 152-163. <lb/>Jin, T., &amp; Bouthillier, F. (2012). The integration of <lb/>intelligence analysis into LIS education. Journal of <lb/>Education for Library and Information Science, 53 <lb/>(2), 130-148. <lb/>Kent, S. (1949). Strategic intelligence for american <lb/>world policy, princeton: Princeton university press. <lb/>As cited in Cronin, B. (2012). Course syllabus for <lb/>Strategic Intelligence. Retrieved at Feb. 24, 2014 from <lb/>http://www.ils.indiana.edu/syllabi/fall_2012/S555_ <lb/>Cronin.pdf. <lb/>Kigongo-Bukenya, I. M. N., &amp; Kaddu, S. (2011). Enhancing <lb/>democracy and good governance -a curriculum proposal <lb/>for information/knowledge management professionals <lb/>(IKMPs) in the SCECSAL region. Library Review, <lb/>60(5), 362-369. <lb/>Lai, Ling-Ling. (2005). Educating knowledge professionals <lb/>in library and information science schools. Journal <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">圖書館學與資訊科學 40(2) ：23 -46(民一○三年十月) </note>
				
				<page>43 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>of Educational Media &amp; Library Sciences, 42(3), <lb/>347-362. <lb/>McGonagle, J. (2012). Competitive intelligence versus <lb/>knowledge management. Retrieved July, 3, 2014, from <lb/>http://diy-ci.com/2012/06/22/competitive-intelligence <lb/>-versus-knowledge-management/ <lb/>Nonaka, I., &amp; Takeuchi, H. (1995). The knowledge <lb/>-creating company: How japanese companies create <lb/>the dynamics of innovation. NY: Oxford University <lb/>Press. <lb/>Porter, M. (1980). Competitive strategy: Techniques <lb/>for analyzing industries and competitors. New York: <lb/>Free Press. <lb/>Rehman, S., &amp; Chaudhry, A. S. (2005). KM education <lb/>in LIS programs. Education for 23(4), <lb/>245-258. <lb/>Rehman, S., &amp; Sumait, H. (2010). KM modules: An <lb/>analysis of coursework. Journal of Information &amp; <lb/>Knowledge Management, 9(4), 377-385. <lb/>Roknuzzaman, M., &amp; Umemoto, K. (2009). How <lb/>library practitioners view knowledge management in <lb/>libraries: A qualitative study. Library Management <lb/>30(8/9), 643-656. <lb/>Ruth, S., Theobald, J., &amp; Frizzell, V. (1999). A <lb/>university-based approach to the diffusion of knowledge <lb/>management concepts and practice. In proceedings <lb/>of the 1999 ACM SIGCPR Conference, 283-290. <lb/>Retrieved March 3, 2014 from http://www.asis.org/ <lb/>SIG/sigkm/ruthandtheobald.pdf. <lb/>Shelfer, K. &amp; Goodrum, A. (2000). Competitive <lb/>intelligence as an extension of library education. <lb/>Journal of Education for Library and Information <lb/>Science, 41(4), 353-361. <lb/>Townley, C. T. (2001). Knowledge management and <lb/>academic libraries. College &amp; Research Libraries, <lb/>62(1), 44-55. <lb/>Wiig, K. M. (1997). Knowledge management: Where <lb/>did it come from and where will it go? Expert Systems <lb/>with Applications, 13(1), 1-14. <lb/>王心裁、呂元智(2003) 。知識管理課程體系設置與 <lb/>知識管理教育芻議。圖書館學研究，1，11-13。 <lb/>【 Wang, Xin-Cai, &amp; Lu, Yuan-Zhi (2003). Zhishi <lb/>guanli kecheng tixi shezhi yu zhishi guanli jiaoyu <lb/>chuyi. Journal of Library and Information Science <lb/>1, 11-13.】 <lb/>王瑤(2005) 。美國大學競爭情報教育類課程實例研 <lb/>究。情報科學，23(8)，1249-1255。 <lb/>【Wang, Yao (2005). Meiguo daxue jingzheng qingbao <lb/>jiaoyulei kecheng shili yanjiu. QingBao KeXue, 23 <lb/>(8), 1249-1255.】 <lb/>王翠波、張玉峰、吳金紅、艾丹祥(2007) 。世界重 <lb/>點高校&quot;知識管理&quot;課程建設實證調查研究(I)：調 <lb/>查物件、方法及結果。情報學報，26(6)，896-901。 <lb/>【Wang, Cui-Po, Zhang, Yu-Feng, Wu, Jin-Hong, &amp; Ai, <lb/>Dan-Xiang (2007). Shijie zhongdian gaoxiao &quot;zhishi <lb/>guanli&quot;kecheng jianshe shizheng diaocha yanjiu (I): <lb/>Diaocha wujian, fangfa ji jieguo. QingBao XueBao, <lb/>26(6), 896-901.】 <lb/>包昌火、李艷、包琰(2012) 。論競爭情報學科的構 <lb/>建。情報理論與實踐，35(1)，1-9。 <lb/>【Bao, Chang-Huo, Yan, &amp; Bao, Yan (2012). Lun <lb/>jingzheng qingbao xueke de goujian. Information <lb/>Studies: Theory &amp; Application, 35(1), 1-9.】 <lb/>林珊如(2002) 。知識管理研究議題：一個圖書資訊 <lb/>學的角度。資訊傳播與圖書館學，8(4)，1-12。 <lb/>【Lin, Shan-Ru (2002). Zhishi guanli yanjiu yiti: Yige <lb/>tushu zixunxue de jiaodu. Journal of Information, <lb/>Communication, and Library Science, 8(4), 1-12.】 <lb/>邱子恒(2006) 。知識管理與知識組織。台北市： <lb/>文華。 <lb/>【Chiu, Tzu-Heng (2006). Zhishi guanli yu zhishi <lb/>zuzhi. Taipei city: WenHua.】 <lb/>邱均平、段宇峰(2000) 。論知識管理與競爭情報。 <lb/>圖書情報工作，44(4)，11-14。 <lb/>【Qiu, Jun-Ping, &amp; Duan, Yu-Feng (2000). Lun zhishi <lb/>guanli yu jingzheng qingbao. Library and Information <lb/>Service. 44(4), 11-14. 】 <lb/>胡笑梅、李文玉(2012) 。2009～2010 年國內競爭 <lb/>情報研究熱點分析。情報探索，174，54-57。 <lb/>【Hu, Xiao-Mei, &amp; Li, Wen-Yu (2012). 2009-2010 <lb/>nian guonei jingzheng qingbao yanjiu redian fenxi. <lb/>Information Research, 174, 54-57.】 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>44 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Library and Information Science 40(2) ：23 -46(October, 2014) <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>孫曉甯、儲節旺(2013) 。我國知識管理研究生教育 <lb/>的統計分析與啟示。圖書情報工作，57(9)，27-36。 <lb/>【Sun, Xiao-Ning, &amp; Chu, Jie-Wang (2013). Woguo <lb/>zhishi guanli yanjiusheng jiaoyu de tongji fenxi yu <lb/>qishi. Library and Information Service, 57(9), 27-36.】 <lb/>秦振飛(2014) 。近 5 年我國競爭情報研究統計分 <lb/>析。河北企業，1，49。 <lb/>【Qin, Zhen-Fei (2014). Jin 5 nian woguo jingzheng <lb/>qingbao yanjiu tongji fenxi. HEBEI QIYE, 1, 49.】 <lb/>張玉峰、王翠波、吳金紅、艾丹祥(2008) ，世界重 <lb/>點高校&quot;知識管理&quot;課程建設實證調查研究(Ⅱ)：分 <lb/>析與討論。情報學報，27(1)，110-115。 <lb/>【Zhang, Yu-Feng, Wang, Cui-Po, Wu, Jin-Hong, &amp; Ai, <lb/>Dan-Xiang (2008). Shijie zhongdian gaoxiao &quot;zhishi <lb/>guanli&quot; kecheng jianshe shizheng diaocha yanjiu (Ⅱ): <lb/>Fenxi yu taolun. QingBao XueBao, 27(1),110-115.】 <lb/>張旭、孫雪蓮、張修文(2013) 。知識管理視域下情 <lb/>報學發展路徑探析。圖書館學刊，11，3-6。 <lb/>【 Zhang, Xu, Sun, Xue-Lian, &amp; Zhang, Xiu-Wen <lb/>(2013). Zhishi guanli shiyuxia qingbaoxue fazhan <lb/>lujing tanxi. Journal of Library Science, 11, 3-6.】 <lb/>張翠英、亢臨生(1997) 。關于高校信息管理系增設 <lb/>競爭情報課程的思考。圖書情報工作，12，49-51。 <lb/>【 Zhang, Cui-Ying, &amp; Kang, Lin-Sheng (1997). <lb/>Guanyu gaoxiao xinxi guanlixi zengshe jingzheng <lb/>qingbao kecheng de sikao. Library and Information <lb/>Service, 12, 49-51.】 <lb/>張翠英、姚志廣(2008) 。我國競爭情報教育課程設 <lb/>置初探。情報探索，124，86-88。 <lb/>【Zhang, Cui-Ying, &amp; Yao, Zhi-Guang (2008). Woguo <lb/>jingzheng qingbao jiaoyu kecheng shezhi chutan. <lb/>Information Research, 124, 86-88.】 <lb/>張慧杰(2011) 。知識管理與競爭情報研究文獻計量 <lb/>【Zhang, Hui-Jie (2011). Zhishi guanli yu jingzheng <lb/>qingbao yanjiu wenxian jiliang fenxi. Modern <lb/>Enterprise Education, 24, 144-145.】 <lb/>張璐、趙輝(2012) 。國內競爭情報研究的文獻計量 <lb/>分析。科技情報發展與經濟，22(4)，79-81 <lb/>【Zhang, Lu, &amp; Zhao, Hui (2012). Guonei jingzheng <lb/>qingbao yanjiu de wenxian jiliang fenxi. Sci-Tech <lb/>Information Development &amp; Economy, 22(4), <lb/>79-81.】 <lb/>盛小平、劉泳潔(2009) 。美國知識管理專業研究生 <lb/>教 育 的 實 證 分 析 及 啟 示 。 情 報 理 論 與 實 踐 ， <lb/>32(11)，116-119。 <lb/>【Cheng, Xiao-Ping, &amp; Liu, Yong-Jie (2009). Meiguo <lb/>zhishi guanli zhuanye yanjiusheng jiaoyu de <lb/>shizheng fenxi ji qishi. Information Studies: Theory <lb/>&amp; Application, 32(11), 116-119.】 <lb/>盛小平(2010) 。知識管理課程內容的需求調查分 <lb/>析。圖書館論壇，30(6)，254-267。 <lb/>【Cheng, Xiao-Ping (2010). Zhishi guanli kecheng <lb/>neirong de xuqiu diaocha fenxi. Library Tribune, 30 <lb/>(6), 254-267.】 <lb/>陳雪華、邱子恆、范中威(2000) 。知識經濟時代中 <lb/>知識管理人才培育之探討。圖書資訊學刊，15， <lb/>1-10。 <lb/>【Chen, Hsueh-Hua, Chiu, Tzu-Heng, &amp; Fan, Jung-Wei <lb/>(2000). Educating knowledge management professionals <lb/>in the era of knowledge economy. Journal of Library <lb/>and Information Studies, 15, 1-10.】 <lb/>劉欣蓓、楊美華(2003) 。台灣高科技產業圖書館員 <lb/>參與知識管理團隊之研究。中國圖書館學會會 <lb/>報，71，79-91。 <lb/>【Liu, Hsin-Pei, &amp; Yang, Mei-Hwa (2003). A study of <lb/>corporate librarian participating in knowledge <lb/>management team in Taiwan high-tech industry. <lb/>Bulletin of the Library Association of China, 71, <lb/>79-91.】 <lb/>蔣貴凰、李艷、宋維翔(2006) 。競爭情報專業培養 <lb/>方案與課程設置初探。北京城市學院學報，3， <lb/>26-31。 <lb/>【Jiang, Gui-Huang, Li, Yan, &amp; Song, Wei-Xiang <lb/>(2006). Jingzheng qingbao zhuanye peiyang fangan <lb/>yu kecheng shezhi chutan. Journal of Beijing City <lb/>University, 3, 26-31.】 <lb/>儲節旺、郭春俠、朱永(2008) 。國內外知識管理教 <lb/>育發展研究。中國圖書館學報，6，90-97。 <lb/>【Chu, Jie-Wang, Guo, Chun-Xia, &amp; Zhu, Yong (2008). <lb/>Guoneiwai zhishi guanli jiaoyu fazhan yanjiu. <lb/>Journal of Library Science in China, 6, 90-97.】 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">圖書館學與資訊科學 40(2) ：23 -46(民一○三年十月) </note>
				
				<page>45 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">The Comparative Curriculum Content Analysis <lb/>for Knowledge Management and Competitive <lb/>Intelligence: an Investigation of ALA-accredited <lb/>Master&apos;s Programs in Library and Information <lb/>Studies <lb/>Yuan-Ho Huang <lb/>Associate Professor, Department of Library and Information Science, <lb/>Fu Jen Catholic University, Taiwan (R.O.C) <lb/>E-mail: yuanho@lins.fju.edu.tw <lb/>Keywords: Curriculum Design; Knowledge Management; Competitive Intelligence; Education <lb/>for Librarianship <lb/>【Abstract】 <lb/>Knowledge management (KM) has developed for decades. Business schools begin to incorporate <lb/>KM into their curriculum design, then Library and Information Science (LIS) schools also follow the <lb/>trend to integrate with KM into curriculums. Many prior literatures related to the integration of KM <lb/>with the LIS curriculum. The number of schools providing KM related course has grown from 3 to <lb/>20 since 2006 till now from the ALA-accredited master&apos;s programs in library and information <lb/>studies. We provide a comparative curriculum analysis for knowledge management and competitive <lb/>intelligence, including course name, positioning in LIS schools, number of credits, purposes and <lb/>contents, course design, and exploring the relationship among two courses. Applying content <lb/>analysis to review the objective and syllabus of KM courses from 15 schools, this study synthesize <lb/>9 dimensions as followings: theory, scope, organizational culture and human resources, processes, <lb/>knowledge sharing and network, evaluation, information technology and systems, practice and <lb/>case studies, competitive intelligence and knowledge services. The abovementioned dimensions <lb/>are similar with those prior studies. Though the development of competitive intelligence (CI) is <lb/>earlier than knowledge management, there are few studies in Taiwan. This study also review the <lb/>objective and syllabus of CI courses from 7 schools and synthesize 13 dimensions as followings: <lb/>strategic theory, the role played by intelligence, the intelligence cycle and delivering timely, the <lb/>co-opetition relationship among stakeholders, legal and ethical aspects, value of information services <lb/>and needs identification, new technologies, evaluation, problem solving and decision-making, <lb/>system security, national security, crises and threats, epistemology and the limitations of human <lb/>judgment. CI mainly focuses on external environment with use of internal and external sources for <lb/>strategic planning, whereas KM focus on internal improvement for organizational growth. CI and <lb/></div>

			<page>46 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Library and Information Science 40(2) ：23 -46(October, 2014) <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">KM has its unique characteristics, we suggest LIS schools could provide both courses in different <lb/>semesters for their complementary resources. Furthermore, both courses emphasize practice and <lb/>case studies, we suggest providing the teaching workshop of Harvard Business School case <lb/>method for teachers in LIS schools in order to improve the teaching skill. </div>


	</text>
</tei>
