<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<page>45 <lb/></page>

			<front>圖書資訊學刊 第15卷第1期 (2017.6) 頁45-76 <lb/></front>
			
			<front>doi: 10.6182/jlis.2017.15(1).045 <lb/></front>

			<front>文殿閣書莊 <lb/>Wen Tien Ke <lb/>雷 強 1 <lb/>Qiang Lei 1 <lb/>摘 要 <lb/>文殿閣書莊並非傳統意義上北京舊書肆的翹楚，但它理應為二十世紀中國出版史所銘 <lb/>記，且在漢學發展史中佔有一席之地。在二十餘年的時間裡，文殿閣書莊從事古籍善本流 <lb/>通買賣、「國學文庫」叢書的策劃出版、翻印西文經典漢學著作數十種，為中、日、歐美 <lb/>學界提供專業的服務。本文透過日記、回憶錄、新聞報紙、已公開檔案、書刊實體等一手 <lb/>資料間的比對和分析，明確文殿閣書莊的成立時間、釐清其與日本學界的往來淵源、再現 <lb/>其翻印事業的全貌，將其從事各項業務的全貌展現給今人。 <lb/>關鍵字： 文殿閣書莊、國學文庫、翻印、漢學 <lb/></front>

			<front>Abstract <lb/>Based on enormous first-hand data as diaries, memoirs, newspapers, archival materials, books, <lb/>and journals, this article tries to clarify some important aspects concerning Wen Tien Ke(Ko) (文殿閣) <lb/>such as when it established, how its inner structure worked and what its major businesses covered. By <lb/>doing so, the author tells the story of the Wen Tien Ke: how it had witnessed the vicissitudes of its time <lb/>and its own, how it had contributed to the cultural exchange and communication between China and <lb/>the West through its daily business activities such as rare book retails, and reprint of books on various <lb/>aspects of China in English and other languages written by distinguished western sinologists. In all, <lb/>this article makes efforts to explore the publishing history of Wen Tien Ke from 1934 to 1950s. <lb/>Keywords: Wen Tien Ke; Sinological Archive; Reprint; Sinology <lb/>1 中國國家圖書館(北京) <lb/>National Library of China, Beijing, China <lb/>E-mail: rhapsodymaster@gmail.com <lb/></front>

			<page>46 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Library and Information Studies 15:1 (June 2017) <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">Extended Abstract <lb/>Conventionally, Wen Tien Ke Bookstore <lb/>(文殿閣書莊) was not the most distinguished <lb/>among the old bookstores in Beijing. The traces of <lb/>this bookstore are barely found in contemporary <lb/>writings and discourses. Nevertheless, since its <lb/>establishment in the 1930s, Wen Tien Ke not <lb/>only played a crucial role in circulating ancient <lb/>and rare books, but also pursued an alternative <lb/>path of typesetting and publishing the Sinological <lb/>A r c h i v e (國學文庫) a s w e l l a s p r o d u c i n g <lb/>anastatic editions (影印本) of Western sinology <lb/>classics, providing comprehensive services for <lb/>both Chinese and international academia. By <lb/>comparing and analyzing first-hand data such as <lb/>diaries, memoirs, newspapers, archival materials, <lb/>books, and journals, this study aims to determine <lb/>Wen Tien Ke&apos;s date of establishment, trace the <lb/>history of its relations with Japanese academia, <lb/>reconstruct a full picture of its reprint enterprise, <lb/>and present a panoramic view of its businesses to <lb/>contemporary readers. <lb/>1. Introduction <lb/>Wen Tien Ke Bookstore was operated by the <lb/>Wang Dien-Xin (王殿馨) and Wang Dien-Sheng <lb/>(王殿升) brothers. Both had more than ten years <lb/>of apprenticeship at established bookstores such as <lb/>Wen Kue Tang (文奎堂) and Nanyang Shanfang <lb/>(南陽山房) before they started their own business <lb/>in 1934. The store was located near Longfu <lb/></div>
			
			<note place="footnote">Note. To cite this article in APA format: Lei, Q. (2017). Wen Tien Ke. Journal of Library and Informa-<lb/>tion Studies, 15(1), 45-76. doi: 10.6182/jlis.2017.15(1).045 [Text in Chinese]. <lb/>To cite this article in Chicago format: Qiang Lei. &quot;Wen Tien Ke.&quot; Journal of Library and Informa-<lb/>tion Studies 15, no. 1 (2017): 45-76. doi: 10.6182/jlis.2017.15(1).045 [Text in Chinese]. <lb/></note>
			
			<div type="annex">Temple (隆福寺), one of the famous bookstore <lb/>districts in Beijing. According to anecdotes, the <lb/>brothers took Su Feng-Ming (蘇鳳鳴) and Ge <lb/>Hong-Nian (葛鴻年) as apprentices in Wen Tien <lb/>Ke, who then transferred to China Bookstore <lb/>approximately in the mid-1950s. <lb/>2. Sinological Archive <lb/>The Sinological Archive, organized by <lb/>a renowned scholar Qian Daosun (錢稻孫) <lb/>and a Japanese in Beijing Matsumura Taro <lb/>(松村太郎), focuses on the borderland histories <lb/>and geographies of China and the historical <lb/>documents about Sino-foreign relations in modern <lb/>times. Since the publication of the first volume <lb/>Notes on the non-Chinese of the Four Quarters <lb/>of the Ming Imperium (皇明四夷考) in June of <lb/>1933, Qian and Matsumura had utilized their <lb/>resources in both Chinese and Japanese academia, <lb/>as well as selected and published a total of 49 rare <lb/>and crucial books. Wen Tien Ke had become the <lb/>series publisher since the 21 st volume Account of <lb/>the Canton Customs (粵海關志), and remained <lb/>so until it was forced to terminate the project in <lb/>the outbreak of the Marco Polo Bridge Incident. <lb/>Although the series consists of reprinted <lb/>(typeset) publications, it has been valued <lb/>and acclaimed by Chinese and international <lb/>academia and the cultural community as the <lb/>model of serial publications undertaken by old <lb/></div>

			<page>47 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Extended Abstract <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">bookstores. Moreover, Hellmut Wilhelm listed <lb/>the series in the first and second editions of &quot;A <lb/>Selected List of Sinological books Published <lb/>in China Since 1938 (1938年以來在華出版漢 <lb/>學書目選).&quot; After Monumenta Serica: Journal <lb/>of Oriental Studies (華裔學志) was known to <lb/>the Western academia, the Sinological Archive <lb/>became valuable historical materials that <lb/>Chinese, Japanese, European, and American <lb/>scholars have relied upon. <lb/>3. Selling and Buying of <lb/>Ancient Books <lb/>In October 1935, Wen Tien Ke printed the <lb/>first issue of New Bibliography of Old Books <lb/>(新舊書目), and sent complimentary copies to <lb/>scholars and public sectors. The bibliography can <lb/>be regarded as an indicator of the bookstore&apos;s <lb/>scale management. The bibliography offered <lb/>the directions for placing mail orders, and <lb/>specifically noted the policies for book delivery <lb/>to Japan, which indicated its close relations with <lb/>clients in Japan. Wen Tien Ke was not confined <lb/>to Beijing as the enterprise grew gradually. <lb/>Instead, the bookstore frequently searched <lb/>for books in Jiangnan (Southern China), and <lb/>purchased ancient and refined editions, usually <lb/>with huge amounts of money, by dint of the <lb/>political situation. <lb/>Particularly, although Wen Tien Ke had long-<lb/>term contact with Japan, it maintained a close <lb/>relationship with the Documents Preservation <lb/>Federation, frequently assisting Zheng Zhenduo <lb/>(鄭振鐸) to purchase rare books. Zheng not only <lb/>recognized the expertise of Wang Dien-Xin but <lb/>also valued him. <lb/>4. Anastatic Editions of <lb/>Western Books <lb/>The major contribution of the current study <lb/>is using historical materials in China and Japan <lb/>to reconstruct the process of how Wen Tien Ke <lb/>produced anastatic editions of Western books. <lb/>By citing and comparing first-hand data from <lb/>The Evolution of Chinese Geography Semi-<lb/>monthly Magazine (禹貢), Bibliography (書誌 <lb/>學), and Shigaku-Zasshi (史學雜誌), this study <lb/>not only confirmed Wen Tien Ke&apos;s specific date of <lb/>establishment, but also ascertained the vital figure <lb/>in the bookstore&apos;s close connection with Japan-<lb/>Matsumura Taro. <lb/>In addition, the author compiled the general <lb/>bibliography of the Western books reprinted <lb/>by Wen Tien Ke according to the bookstore&apos;s <lb/>bibliographies and the catalogues of college <lb/>and university libraries in China and Japan. <lb/>Furthermore, the author compared the lists <lb/>with the physical books at hand to identify <lb/>and correct mistakes, and finally compiled a <lb/>reliable bibliography. <lb/>5. Implications <lb/>Either the Sinological Archive or the reprinting <lb/>of Western sinology classics, Wen Tien Ke <lb/>had consistently emphasized the selection and <lb/>compilation of first-hand data about both Chinese <lb/>and Western transportation history, borderland <lb/>history and geography, and ethnic languages. This <lb/>reflects the organizer&apos;s penetrating insight into <lb/>that Beijing, as the center of traditional Chinese <lb/>culture and academia, is the best place not only <lb/>for Sino-Western academic exchanges but also for <lb/>training students. Both undertakings required the <lb/>circulation and nourishment of classics. Through <lb/></div>>

			<page>48 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">圖書資訊學刊 第15卷 第1期 (2017.6) <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">commercial dealings, Wen Tien Ke greatly <lb/>facilitated the development of sinology both in <lb/>China and other countries, and become a crucial <lb/>part in the circulation of Western sinology classics. <lb/>For example, Bibliotheca Sinica: Dictionnaire <lb/>Bibliographique des Ouvrages Relatifs à L&apos;Empire <lb/>Chinois (西人論中國書目) recently published by <lb/>Zhonghua Bookstore is based on the edition of <lb/>Wen Tien Ke, serving for generations of scholars. <lb/></div>
			
			<body>壹、 引言 <lb/>1940年4月25日，困守北京的畢樹棠在其 <lb/>日記中寫下： <lb/>繼至文殿閣，有翻印之英法文所著 <lb/>之漢學書數種，如Henri Cordier之 <lb/>Bibliotheca Sinica，A. Wylie之Chinese <lb/>Researches等，原板現已稀見，有之 <lb/>亦價奇昂，而此等舊籍又今日西人治 <lb/>漢學所不可缺少之參考，遂為狡賈 <lb/>所伺，趁機印而牟利。聞T&apos;oung Pao <lb/>(《通報》)與Chinese Repository等 <lb/>近亦有人翻印，轉售於歐美各地， <lb/>獲利無算，而在中國書肆中反不易 <lb/>見，此亦美金高漲使然也(畢樹棠， <lb/>2014，頁53)。 <lb/>此段記述雖然只百餘字，但資訊量頗大， <lb/>值得人留心考察。首先抗戰軍興已近三年，歐 <lb/>戰業已爆發半年，北京的書肆卻在此大環境下 <lb/>翻印西文漢學經典，超乎常人想像；其次，從 <lb/>事翻印事業絕非個別店家，文中提到的「文殿 <lb/>閣」在畢樹棠看來可算作代表；最後，印好的 <lb/>書刊不在國內經銷，幾乎全部售予歐美機構， <lb/>毫不避諱「翻印」的不良感觀。然而，無論是 <lb/>當事人還是旁觀者，都很難知悉這一行為的意 <lb/>義。事實上，以文殿閣為代表的北京舊書肆興 <lb/>起了民國以來首次集中翻印西文漢學經典的浪 <lb/>潮，其規模與影響至今仍難以超越。 <lb/>貳、 文殿閣書莊概述 <lb/>畢樹棠提到的文殿閣(書莊)，並非北 <lb/>京書肆中的資深店家，與文奎堂、富晉書社、 <lb/>來薰閣、松筠閣、修經堂、文祿堂、通學齋、 <lb/>藻玉堂等店相比，可謂少有聲望，相關史料留 <lb/>存不多。孫殿起在〈琉璃廠書肆三記〉中僅有 <lb/>數十字的介紹：「文殿閣：王殿馨，字浡馥， <lb/>束鹿縣人，於民國二十三年開設」；有「弟子 <lb/>蘇鳳鳴、葛鴻年」；曾刊行「國學文庫三十八 <lb/>種」(孫殿起，2001，頁134、240、181)。 <lb/>束鹿縣，今河北省石家莊以東辛集市，晚清民 <lb/>國時期北京書肆老闆多出自此地，如王福田 <lb/>(福潤堂)、王雲慶(帶經堂)、王雲瑞(文 <lb/>奎堂)，王殿馨相對於這幾位前輩，只能算是 <lb/>「王」姓一族中的晚進。此外，雷夢水《書林 <lb/>瑣記》有以下補充史料：「(王殿馨)與其 <lb/>弟殿升字平齋合營此肆。浡馥受業於文奎堂 <lb/>王輯五先生。平齋則受業於南陽山房張敬亭 <lb/>先生。」(雷夢水，1 988，頁61)王輯五即 <lb/>上文所提王雲瑞，文奎堂的老掌櫃，光緒年間 <lb/>創店，1927年間其子王金昌繼承父業，王殿馨 <lb/>與之同輩；張敬亭，原名張淩貴，1918年設南 <lb/>陽山房，二十年代末歇業(雷夢水，1988，頁 <lb/>122)。 <lb/></body>

			<page>49 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">文殿閣書莊 <lb/></note>

			<body>楊聯陞在其文章〈憶錢稻孫先生--兼 <lb/>憶賈德納〉中也提到了文殿閣和國學文庫， <lb/>頗具參考價值，原文如下： <lb/>我第一次到受璧胡同錢府，大約 <lb/>是在大二或大三的時候，好像是去 <lb/>借書，也許是為了商談標點《國學 <lb/>文庫》的事。那時北平有一家舊書 <lb/>鋪文殿閣，重新排印若干種關於邊 <lb/>防與非漢族的史籍雜著，名之曰《 <lb/>國學文庫》。起初沒有標點，後來 <lb/>錢稻孫介紹我在課餘之暇給他們句 <lb/>讀過十一二種，報酬是送了我一套 <lb/>《文庫》，約有三四十冊(楊聯陞， <lb/>2013，頁47-48)。 <lb/>據楊聯陞自傳可知其1933年進入國立 <lb/>清華大學，這與國學文庫第1編--《皇明 <lb/>四夷考》的刊印時間大致吻合，可以相互 <lb/>佐證。日本學者長澤規矩也極為留意北京 <lb/>書林，對隆福寺書肆十分稔熟，但無論是其 <lb/>寫於1931年2月3日的〈中華民國書林一瞥〉 <lb/>還是在同年夏秋之際完成的〈中華民國書林 <lb/>一瞥補正〉都沒有提到文殿閣(內藤湖南、 <lb/>長澤規矩也，2006)。基於以上種種史料， <lb/>筆者亦認同孫殿起的記述--文殿閣在1934 <lb/>年 成 立 。 然 而 ， 該 店 店 址 並 非 隆 福 寺 街 <lb/>四百七十號(孫殿起，2001，頁181)，而 <lb/>是隆福寺街路南一四七號。 <lb/>至於文殿閣書莊的存續時間，筆者並 <lb/>未見及準確記錄。但可以判定，它在1949年 <lb/>後仍然存續了一段時間，學徒葛鴻年1950年 <lb/>另立門戶--鴻文閣，店址最初在別處，後 <lb/>因文殿閣遷至同處隆福寺地區的鹽店大院， <lb/>將其店搬至隆福寺街路南一四七號老店舊址 <lb/>(雷夢水，1 9 8 8，頁6 1)。楊殿珣撰寫的 <lb/>〈書林掇英--魏隱儒古籍版本知見錄序〉 <lb/>曾提到： <lb/>在 1 9 6 1 年 ， 隆 福 寺 文 殿 閣 主 人 <lb/>王平齋家散出《周易說略》(清 <lb/>張爾岐撰)一書，係康熙五十八 <lb/>年泰山徐志定真合齋磁版印本， <lb/>封面上題有「泰山磁版」四字( <lb/>楊殿珣，2010，頁25)。 <lb/>倘若以此推斷上世紀六十年代文殿閣仍 <lb/>然存在，則是值得商榷的。一方面，1949年 <lb/>後大陸的工商業面臨巨大的變革壓力，1956 <lb/>年公私合營的浪潮席捲了北京的舊書店，兩 <lb/>年後幾乎全部歸於「中國書店」名下，筆者 <lb/>在鄧之誠日記中找到相應史料，他對明清兩 <lb/>代筆記、文集極為關注，多方囑託琉璃廠、 <lb/>隆福寺書店代為尋找順康兩朝的集部文獻， <lb/>亦從旁記錄了北京舊書業的變革，1958年後 <lb/>其曾兩次提到：隆福寺(十餘家書店)只存 <lb/>修綆、文奎二家(鄧之誠，2012，頁1107、 <lb/>1174)；另一方面，筆者認為楊殿珣的回憶 <lb/>只是強調了《周易說略》由文殿閣主人家中 <lb/>散出，並非表示此時仍有文殿閣書莊。 <lb/>參、 國學文庫 <lb/>《皇明四夷考》的刊印時間是1 9 3 3年 <lb/>6月，這明顯與孫殿起記述的「民國二十三 <lb/>年」相矛盾。倘若據此將文殿閣成立提前 <lb/>至1 9 3 3年甚至更早，則是輕信了孫殿起另 <lb/></body>

			<page>50 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">圖書資訊學刊 第15卷 第1期 (2017.6) <lb/></note>

			<body>外 一個說法--(文殿閣)刊行「國學文 <lb/>庫三十八種」。事實上，《皇明四夷考》 <lb/>(圖一)首次印行時並沒有標明出版方，只有 <lb/>「國學文庫第壹編」字樣。 <lb/>最早對國學文庫報導的是北京本地的學 <lb/>術刊物--《國立北平圖書館館刊》，1933 <lb/>年底第7卷第6號的「新書介紹」一欄提及： <lb/>又近日北平坊間有一種國學文庫 <lb/>……第六種為滿清入關前與高麗交 <lb/>涉史料(歷史博物館藏)，已為研 <lb/>究四裔史之要籍，以知者尚少，因 <lb/>並為識於篇末(明，1933，頁114-<lb/>116)。 <lb/>以上隻言片語附在〈遼居雜著乙稿、渤 <lb/>海國志長編要刪、清初史料四種〉三書介紹 <lb/>末尾處，該文作者應為向達(字覺明)。其 <lb/>中，值得注意的是第六種《滿清入關前與高麗 <lb/>交涉史料》據國立北平歷史博物館所藏鈔本重 <lb/>印，可見籌劃該叢書的人與北京學界關係不 <lb/>淺。以向達先生的見識(註一)，應知悉此套 <lb/>叢書的始作俑者，但其只作客觀介紹，認為坊 <lb/>間新刊的六種國學文庫是治四裔史的必備書。 <lb/>圖一 1937年2月，《皇明四夷考》再版，封面處增加了「總發售處北平隆福寺街文殿閣書莊」字樣。 <lb/></body>

			<page>51 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">文殿閣書莊 <lb/></note>

			<body>1936年4月13日，天津《大公報．圖書 <lb/>副刊》第128期，刊登了署名為「無忌」的 <lb/>文章--〈翻印舊書之風〉，撰者認為相對 <lb/>於隨意翻印文學書籍牟利，國學文庫的翻印 <lb/>是非常值得鼓勵並提倡的(無忌，1936)。 <lb/>該文前半部分專談國學文庫，較之前面數 <lb/>篇介紹都更為詳盡，提供了更多的資訊，其 <lb/>中部分正確，部分值得商榷(註二)。可信 <lb/>者，如稱「亦不知其出版處及編者姓名或 <lb/>其他重印緣起……有外國人從中擘劃」， <lb/>「……欽定蒙古源流據文津閣四庫全書本， <lb/>站赤據東洋文庫影印永樂大典本，選擇頗 <lb/>為審慎」；偏頗之處則是「入民國二十五 <lb/>年，書面便有北平隆福寺街文殿閣重印字 <lb/>樣了」。事實上，書面首次出現「文殿閣 <lb/>書莊」是《粵海關志》第7冊(貢舶市舶行 <lb/>商)，該書為國學文庫第21編，1935年10月 <lb/>印，而此前1編《萬曆武功錄．東三邊》印 <lb/>於該年7月。換言之，1935年夏秋之際，文 <lb/>殿閣書莊開始負責國學文庫叢書的出版工 <lb/>作。《大公報．圖書副刊》由國立北平圖書 <lb/>館負責組稿、編輯，〈翻印舊書之風〉刊發 <lb/>於此，大抵可以窺見北方學界對此部翻印叢 <lb/>書頗為積極的態度(註三)；另一方面，能 <lb/>夠排印文津閣四庫本和東洋文庫永樂大典 <lb/>本，亦彰顯了幕後籌劃者在中日學界廣博的 <lb/>人脈。文殿閣作為一家新晉的私人書肆，無 <lb/>論是王殿馨還是兄弟王殿升，都難有連結中 <lb/>日學術界、利用各家公藏的能力。 <lb/>在此之後，對國學文庫少有報導，筆 <lb/>者只見到幾處：一為1936年《禹貢》第5卷 <lb/>第3、4期合刊中，對《皇明四夷考》、《 <lb/>四夷考》(1 3，該數字為國學文庫序號， <lb/>下同)作簡要介紹(禹貢學會，1 9 3 6)； <lb/>二為謝興堯曾稱讚文殿閣為書肆中編印文 <lb/>庫之表率，他認為「然書商之頭腦活潑， <lb/>資本較裕者，亦相率自印，不敢後人。最 <lb/>著者如文殿閣之國學文庫，共出三十八種， <lb/>每 種 皆 舊 書 中 極 不 易 得 或 極 貴 者 。 」 ( <lb/>蕘公，1 9 4 3，頁2 8 )然而，無論是孫殿 <lb/>起，還是謝興堯都將國學文庫記作3 8種， <lb/>這與實際情況相距甚遠。在1 9 3 6年9月修 <lb/>訂的《文殿閣新舊書目》第3 期中，該叢 <lb/>書 的 確 只 計 有 3 8 種 ， 且 最 後 1 種 --《 <lb/>萬曆武功錄》標註為「印刷中」(文殿閣 <lb/>書莊，1936，頁233)。在此之後，國學文 <lb/>庫繼續出版了：《柳邊紀略五卷》(39)、 <lb/>《大金國志》上冊(4 0)、《大金國志》 <lb/>下 冊 ( 4 1 ) 、 《 嶺 外 代 答 》 ( 4 2 ) 、 《 <lb/>元高麗紀事》(43)、《長春真人西遊記校 <lb/>注》(4 4)、《北巡私記．皇明北虜考》 <lb/>( 4 5 ) 、 《 四 朝 大 政 錄 ． 三 朝 大 議 錄 》 <lb/>(4 6)、《契丹交通史料七種》(4 7)、 <lb/>《庚申外史》(4 8)、《大元馬政記．官 <lb/>制雜記》(49)。這11種書的資訊不僅記錄 <lb/>在1938年4月《文殿閣新書目》中，也大都 <lb/>被衛德明(Hellmut Wilhelm)輯錄在〈1938 <lb/>年以來在華出版漢學書目選〉(A Selected <lb/>List of Sinological Books Published in China <lb/>Since 1938)第一、二編中(Wilhelm, 1942, <lb/>1943)(註四)。考慮到國學文庫中最晚者 <lb/>印於1937年7月，筆者認為正是由於「盧溝 <lb/></body>

			<page>52 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">圖書資訊學刊 第15卷 第1期 (2017.6) <lb/></note>

			<body>橋事變」的爆發中止了該項出版計畫。在這 <lb/>4 9編中，有幾種書以不同卷的形式重複出 <lb/>現，除了以上提到的《大金國志》，還有 <lb/>《萬曆武功錄》(20、24、34、38)、《 <lb/>粵海關志》(1 8、 2 1、 3 3)、《站赤》 <lb/>( 2 8、 3 0)、《皇明經濟文錄》(1 4、 <lb/>19)，合併以上5種，國學文庫實際包含41 <lb/>種書籍，在此雷夢水的記述可謂準確無誤 <lb/>(雷夢水，1 9 8 8，頁6 1)。另外，筆者注 <lb/>意到一個細節，早期國學文庫叢書確無句 <lb/>讀(註五)，直到1 9 3 6年4月後出版的《 <lb/>站赤》上冊(28)、《站赤》下冊(30)、 <lb/>《大金國志》上下冊、《契丹交通史料七 <lb/>種》、《庚申外史》、《大元馬政記．官制 <lb/>雜記》等書才有了標點，亦從側面印證了 <lb/>楊聯陞之回憶。 <lb/>除了中外學術界，筆者亦見到日本政界 <lb/>對國學文庫的記錄。1935年2月，日本外務 <lb/>省收到了《皇明四夷考》等7編(外務省報 <lb/>第318號；日本外務省，1935)，足鑒文庫 <lb/>編纂方針的實用性。 <lb/>肆、 古籍買賣 <lb/>民國時期，北京舊書肆為廣招顧客、行 <lb/>銷天下，常刊行自家書目，譬如《通學齋書 <lb/>目》、《文芸閣書目》、《粹雅堂書目》、 <lb/>《來薰閣書目》、《修綆堂書目》、《文奎 <lb/>堂書目》等，均可視為此中代表，而自訂 <lb/>書目亦可作為大中型店家與一般書鋪的區分 <lb/>標識。1935年10月文殿閣書莊訂《文殿閣新 <lb/>舊書目》第1期，以贈閱方式付與學者或公 <lb/>家機構，此冊可視作其規模化經營古籍善本 <lb/>書之標誌(文殿閣書莊，1935)。該書目古 <lb/>籍部分依照四庫慣例，分經、史、子、集四 <lb/>部，其中小說列入子部、劇曲入集部；為方 <lb/>便文史學者瞭解版本，每書資訊如撰者、版 <lb/>本紙張、刊刻時代、卷冊數目皆舉要注明， <lb/>其中善本名校，更是標明源流。新書部分則 <lb/>以在編的國學文庫為主，並告知該店代售北 <lb/>平圖書館、中央研究院、故宮博物館、北京 <lb/>大學、北平研究院等各大學院校機構的出版 <lb/>物。除上門購買的傳統方式，文殿閣更看重 <lb/>郵寄售書，在封面內頁註明「外埠通信購書 <lb/>辦法」，其中丙則：「國內及日本寄書郵費 <lb/>均十冊以下者二角三分，多還少補」值得今 <lb/>人留意。北京舊書肆與日本學界素有往來， <lb/>如孫殿起、王晉卿等人皆被日方看重，但倘 <lb/>若將此視作行業慣例，則也不盡然。 <lb/>或許是借助首期《文殿閣新舊書目》 <lb/>的宣傳，該店新舊書刊生意十分興隆，翌年 <lb/>9月第3期《文殿閣新舊書目》即已訂立並印 <lb/>行。至1939年4月，文殿閣已訂立《文殿閣舊 <lb/>書目》第5期，同月刊行《文殿閣方志目》， <lb/>新書部分則另闢詳目。其「附告」一欄寫道 <lb/>(文殿閣書莊，1939)： <lb/>蒙士林嘉許，茲因前四期書目內之 <lb/>書多已售出，不適用。今敝店新由 <lb/>江浙諸省藏書家收有書籍甚夥，彙 <lb/>集五期，定價從廉以付惠顧之雅 <lb/>意。倘蒙海內外圖書館及各藏書家 <lb/>惠顧，方知言不謬也…… <lb/>事實上，以上言辭的確不謬，此時店主 <lb/></body>

			<page>53 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">文殿閣書莊 <lb/></note>

			<body>王殿馨並不囿於北京一地，而是常在江南各 <lb/>處訪書，借助時局廣購古槧精刻，常常一擲 <lb/>千金。 <lb/>恰此期間，鄭振鐸與張壽鏞、何炳松、 <lb/>張元濟、張鳳舉在上海秘密發起「文獻保存 <lb/>同志會」，搶救江南著名書樓之古籍，文 <lb/>殿閣正是其重要的購書渠道之一。就筆者所 <lb/>見及，鄭振鐸在其日記中四次提到王殿馨( <lb/>王浡馥)，分別在1940年1月8日、8月2日、 <lb/>1941年1月22日、5月20日，此外在其撰寫的 <lb/>「文獻保存同志會第一、四、八、九號工作 <lb/>報告書」中亦有提及。此間記錄有三筆尤其 <lb/>值得提及，一是搶先購入《皇朝禮器圖式》 <lb/>九冊，讓鄭振鐸羡慕不已(鄭振鐸，2016， <lb/>頁392)；二是1940年與滬上書商李紫東聯 <lb/>手購入劉體智(字晦之)遠碧樓藏書中宋版 <lb/>九種，並將之轉售鄭振鐸(鄭振鐸，2016， <lb/>頁320)；三是豪取劉聲木(字十枝)藏書 <lb/>中的一千餘部方志，其中大半售與燕京大 <lb/>學，餘下精品若干則輾轉歸於「文獻保存同 <lb/>志會」(鄭振鐸，2016，頁359)。在已公 <lb/>開的日記和報告之外，筆者亦曾見過相關史 <lb/>料，如鄭振鐸經王浡馥之手為「文獻保存同 <lb/>志會」購入萬曆刊本《牛首山志》等書( <lb/>李慧，2010)。1941年6月3日，鄭振鐸在第 <lb/>九號工作報告書中寫道：「平肆各賈書款， <lb/>大致已結清；計付來薰閣六百六十八元，文 <lb/>殿閣六百元，修文堂一百元。撰寫帳中各書， <lb/>大都尚系去冬擱置至今者，價均未漲。雖頗費 <lb/>口舌，然諸賈均能深明大義，可嘉也！」( <lb/>鄭振鐸，2016，頁364)正是由於以上種種交 <lb/>往，鄭振鐸雖然偶有牢騷，認為商賈重利，有 <lb/>時難於把控，好書經其手不免失之國家，但總 <lb/>體而言，他對文殿閣做出了較為正面的評價。 <lb/>此外，文殿閣收售古籍善本事，散見 <lb/>於雷夢水、鄧之誠等人的記述。其中較為大 <lb/>宗者有：三十年代中期協助日本東洋文庫 <lb/>購買中國地方誌(巴兆祥，2008)；1941年 <lb/>與文奎堂、松筠閣、文祿堂等合資收購天 <lb/>津張氏明清善本，文殿閣得明銅活字本《 <lb/>鳳洲筆記》(雷夢水，1988，頁55-56)； <lb/>四十年代初購得鄧邦述部分藏書(沈津， <lb/>2008)；1947年與文奎堂等五家書鋪豪取 <lb/>徐樹錚藏書(鄧之誠，2012，頁436)。這 <lb/>些史料雖只能記錄文殿閣舊書售賣的點滴片 <lb/>段，卻也可以窺見其業務規模。 <lb/>伍、 翻印西書 <lb/>一、 緣起 <lb/>在國學文庫和大宗古籍售賣事業外， <lb/>文殿閣書莊最應被後人所銘記的是其翻印了 <lb/>數十種西文漢學著作，嘉惠學林。1935年， <lb/>《禹貢》第4卷第7期刊登了一則「英文諸藩 <lb/>志箋證」的廣告，全文如下： <lb/>此書係英文繙譯宋人趙汝適所著之 <lb/>諸藩志，且附有注釋箋證。其精確 <lb/>詳實，久為歐美學術界所稱讚，乃 <lb/>研究史學者必備之參考書。原本出 <lb/>版於一九一二年，因所印不多， <lb/>流傳甚少；今日更為罕覯，雖以 <lb/>五六十元之重價，亦難覓得。茲特 <lb/>取原本影印，瑞典紙十六開本，凡 <lb/></body>

			<page>54 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">圖書資訊學刊 第15卷 第1期 (2017.6) <lb/></note>

			<body>二百八十八頁，附圖一大張，平裝 <lb/>一冊。版式尺寸，紙張裝幀，悉同 <lb/>原本，冀存廬山面目。每部實價國 <lb/>幣七元。(外埠及日本另加郵費一 <lb/>角五分五厘)書印無多，購請從速 <lb/>(禹貢學會，1935，頁46)。 <lb/>這則消息中的諸多細節，頗值得考量。 <lb/>首先，《禹貢》是禹貢學會的會刊，於1934 <lb/>年3月1日創刊發行，其研究旨趣是研究中 <lb/>國沿革地理，而邊疆史地和中西交通史料均 <lb/>是重要的組成部分，無論是撰稿群還是訂閱 <lb/>者大都是相關領域的專家或者有志於此的青 <lb/>年學人，因此文殿閣在此刊登廣告有強烈的 <lb/>針對性，可謂「有的放矢」。其次，從行文 <lb/>中不難看出，影印書籍並非全由文殿閣主觀 <lb/>決斷，而是有學界的支撐，換言之市場需求 <lb/>催生了該行為；再次，文殿閣影印無論是內 <lb/>容、配(地)圖、頁數還是版式、紙張均意 <lb/>欲與原書保持一致，以存原貌，這不僅是承 <lb/>諾更是其賣點；最後，該書不僅針對國內， <lb/>日本也是其主要的行銷地區。事實上，「英 <lb/>文諸藩志箋證」是文殿閣影印的第一種西文 <lb/>漢學著作，而此後該店再未在《禹貢》刊登 <lb/>過任何類似廣告。 <lb/>圖二 《書誌學》第6卷第6期的「雜報」原文 <lb/></body>

			<page>55 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">文殿閣書莊 <lb/></note>

			<body>1936年6月5日，日本東京發行的《書誌 <lb/>學》第6卷第6期的「雜報」欄刊(圖二)登 <lb/>了一則消息，翻譯過後大意如下： <lb/>民國自數年前開始，翻版問題十分 <lb/>嚴重。就是未經許可就翻刻別的書 <lb/>肆出版的書，所謂偽版問題。在北 <lb/>平的某邦人(即日本人)也加以效 <lb/>法，未經許可複製了與支那相關的 <lb/>歐文書籍。我邦因為Plage問題導致 <lb/>許多麻煩，所以即使支那並未加入 <lb/>版權同盟，對學者而言也是便利之 <lb/>事，也希望邦人不要再參與其中， <lb/>而完全交於北平書賈(作者不詳， <lb/>1936，頁40)。 <lb/>文 中 提 到 的 「 P l a g e 問 題 」 ， 是 指 <lb/>1931年德國人Wi l h e l m P l a g e以歐洲著作 <lb/>權 管 理 團 體 的 代 理 人 身 份 ， 向 日 本 電 臺 <lb/>和 演 奏 家 索 取 高 額 著 作 權 使 用 費 ， 該 事 <lb/>件 對 日 本 文 化 界 觸 動 極 大 ， 並 直 接 催 生 <lb/>了 1 9 3 4 、 1 9 3 9 年 日 本 著 作 權 法 修 正 案 ( <lb/>註六)。這則消息沒有註明作者，但倘若 <lb/>熟 悉 《 書 誌 學 》 雜 誌 的 內 情 ， 便 可 知 悉 <lb/>「雜報」一欄多由該社編輯橘井清五郎、 <lb/>長澤規矩也、川 一馬撰述，而三人之中 <lb/>只有長澤規矩也洞悉中國(北京)書業動 <lb/>態。不僅如此，從日文表述上可以判定， <lb/>此篇「雜報」的作者是知道哪位在北京的 <lb/>日本人參與了複製歐文書籍，但囿於情面 <lb/>沒有道明。 <lb/>結合以上兩條史料，筆者認為確有日人 <lb/>在北京協助書肆影印了西文漢學著作，而且 <lb/>出於讓日本學界同樣便利使用這些學術著作 <lb/>的考慮，在翻印之初即有意針對日方市場。 <lb/>1934年《書誌學》第2卷第5期中刊登了「質 <lb/>疑應答」(圖三)，長澤規矩也就中國書籍 <lb/>購買的途徑等回答了日本學生的提問。在東 <lb/>京求文堂、京都彙文堂外，他還推薦了一 <lb/>家位於北京東城西堂子胡同內的書店，名為 <lb/>「字紙簍社」，並這樣介紹到： <lb/>經營者松村太郎氏曾為《順天時 <lb/>報》記者，久居北平，與北平書賈 <lb/>亦多相知，有什麼事情找他，都會 <lb/>很方便。經營字紙簍社之前，時常 <lb/>能在北平小書店或書攤見到他的身 <lb/>影。如想買舊雜誌、手冊，找他則 <lb/>再便利不過……字紙簍雖也經營古 <lb/>版本，但不在松村氏專業之內。不 <lb/>過他可代為聯絡北平古書肆，這一 <lb/>點也還不錯(長澤規矩也，1934， <lb/>頁60)。 <lb/>松村太郎與錢稻孫、周作人等人的交 <lb/>集、往來，今人已有梳理；錢稻孫為「字紙 <lb/>簍社」刊物《字紙簍》撰稿之事亦有學者鉤 <lb/>沉，筆者不再贅述(註七)。然而，以上種 <lb/>種史料雖層層佐證，但大都隱晦，只能讓人 <lb/>從旁推論。 <lb/>真正將松村太郎與文殿閣書莊直接聯 <lb/>繫在一起的是王殿馨本人的一封信，其文刊 <lb/>登在日本極具威望的學術期刊《史學雜誌》 <lb/>(Shigaku-Zasshi)第46編第11號(史學會， <lb/>1935)(圖四)，正文翻譯過後如下： <lb/></body>

			<page>56 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">圖書資訊學刊 第15卷 第1期 (2017.6) <lb/></note>

			<body>購買新舊漢籍者敬請惠顧北平文殿 <lb/>閣書店 <lb/>(至本年十一月三十日迄，古書類 <lb/>八折、新刊本除外) <lb/>弊 店 雖 為 去 年 剛 開 業 之 新 店 ， 然 <lb/>鄙人擁有在本地某書店從業十九年之經 <lb/>驗，略有自信，故而開店營業。 <lb/>弊店主營古書類，鑒於學界近來之 <lb/>趨勢，與本地及各省重要公私立大學、 <lb/>圖書館出版部皆有聯絡，經營其所出版 <lb/>之書籍。由本地三四有志之士企劃，博 <lb/>得學界好評之《國學文庫》，此次亦將 <lb/>其出版業務移交於弊店，故今後續刊之 <lb/>事也在計畫之中。 <lb/>至於庫存書目，本欲迅速編制，然 <lb/>因採購進貨等事而拖延，複經各位主顧 <lb/>再三催促，此次由松村太郎先生推薦， <lb/>委託字紙簍社代為編制。為日本方面各 <lb/>位之便宜計，倉促著手，終於得呈貴 <lb/>覽。只恐不能如字紙簍一般每月刊行一 <lb/>圖三 通過《書誌學》，長澤規矩也向日本學人推薦北京地區的日籍書商松村太郎(字紙簍社 <lb/>經營者)。 <lb/></body>

			<page>57 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">文殿閣書莊 <lb/></note>

			<body>次，故計畫於每年一次之總目錄編制完 <lb/>成後，每二三月刊行一次其後購入之古 <lb/>書及新刊書小目錄，贈呈貴覽。 <lb/>如上所述，茲敬望今後各位如愛顧 <lb/>字紙簍社一般愛顧弊店。 <lb/>中華民國二十四年十月 <lb/>中華民國北平隆福寺街路南 <lb/>文殿閣書店 王殿馨 敬白 <lb/>坦言之，此信解決了很多歷史疑問。 <lb/>首先，王殿馨自述了店面成立時間--1934 <lb/>年，孫殿起在此的記述可謂準確；其次，這 <lb/>封信落款的時間，恰是《粵海關志》第7冊 <lb/>刊印之時，如王殿馨所言出版方的確由企劃 <lb/>學者--錢稻孫等人交付於他，並標註了文 <lb/>殿閣書莊字樣；最後，1 9 3 5年1 0月也是《 <lb/>文殿閣新舊書目》第1期訂印之時，該書目 <lb/>實為松村太郎(字紙簍社)代為編纂。 <lb/>由此可知文殿閣格外重視日本市場的 <lb/>根由即為松村太郎，他不僅參與了國學文庫 <lb/>的籌劃、更是文殿閣書莊連結日本學術界的 <lb/>核心人物；而結合前文長澤規矩也的隱晦規 <lb/>勸及其對字紙簍社的推介，不難得出以下結 <lb/>圖四 王殿馨在日本《史學雜誌》上登載公開信，後附購書細則十條。 <lb/></body>

			<page>58 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">圖書資訊學刊 第15卷 第1期 (2017.6) <lb/></note>

			<body>論--松村太郎直接參與了文殿閣影印西文 <lb/>漢學名著的事業。自1934年始至1941年終， <lb/>文殿閣歷時七年之久的翻印西文漢學經典事 <lb/>業，是在松村太郎、錢稻孫等人的規劃下一 <lb/>步步展開的。 <lb/>二、 文殿閣翻印書目 <lb/>本書目主要依據1939年4月訂《文殿閣 <lb/>新書目》中「影印漢學西書目」、衛德明 <lb/>輯〈1 9 3 8年以來在華出版漢學書目選〉， <lb/>並與公藏單位及筆者一年來從各國購買的 <lb/>書籍實體一一比對，以求臻於完善。書目 <lb/>以時間為序，如遇某書翻印過數次，則只 <lb/>在 第 一 次 時 記 錄 ， 並 在 結 尾 處 標 註 不 同 <lb/>版次。另，如《蒙古史》(History of the <lb/>Mongols)五冊非同一年印行，則根據每一 <lb/>冊的影印時間分別輯錄。書目共收錄圖書 <lb/>3 4種，涉及英、法、德、俄語，絕大部分 <lb/>為原書影印，少數翻印學刊中某篇文章的 <lb/>抽印本。其中最為著名者有《西人論中國 <lb/>圖五 筆者所藏《西人論中國書目》之卷一 <lb/></body>

			<page>59 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">文殿閣書莊 <lb/></note>

			<body>書目》(Bibliotheca Sinica)(圖五)、《 <lb/>蒙古史》(History of the Mongols, from the 9th <lb/>to the 19th century)、《李雅各英譯七經》 <lb/>(The Chinese Classics)、法譯本《史記》 <lb/>(Les Mémoires Historiques de Se-Ma Ts&apos;ien) <lb/>等書。 <lb/>每條書目資訊通常分為三段，其一為 <lb/>英文資訊，第二段則為封面處之中文資訊( <lb/>註八)，第三段附錄其所用底本之資訊。文 <lb/>殿閣書莊所影印的西文書籍，各時期稍有不 <lb/>同，如前期《趙汝適「諸藩志」譯注》、 <lb/>《大唐西域記箋證》等常在其封面或書名頁 <lb/>加蓋「文殿閣書莊」藍色印章(圖六)，中 <lb/>期翻印書籍皆在封面處有「文殿閣書莊」 <lb/>字樣，晚期圖書如《京庭十有三年記》則 <lb/>常隱去店面訊息。以上種種差別，筆者根 <lb/>據書目資訊及書籍實體標註自行統一，不 <lb/>再逐一贅述。 <lb/>圖六 筆者所藏《大唐西域記箋證》之卷一，封面、書名頁蓋有文殿閣書莊的藍色印章。此書 <lb/>曾經日本一誠堂書店(The Isseido Booksellers)出售，後入藏於夏威夷大學哲學系。 <lb/></body>

			<page>60 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">第1期 (2017.6) <lb/></note>

			<body>1934年 <lb/>Hirth and W. W. Rockhill, Ju-kua: his <lb/>work on the Chinese and Arab trade in the <lb/>twelfth and thirteenth centuries, entitled <lb/>Chu-fan-chi, translated from the Chinese <lb/>and annotated, x, 288 pages, 1 folded map, <lb/>26.5×19.5 cm. <lb/>夏德、柔克義共著，《趙汝適「諸藩志」譯 <lb/>注》，實價國幣七元 <lb/>St. Petersburg: Printing Office of the Imperial <lb/>Academy of Sciences, 1911 <lb/>此書1939年再次翻印 <lb/>P. G. von Möllendorff, A Manchu Grammar, <lb/>with analysed texts, 52 pages, 28 cm. <lb/>穆聯德爾夫著，《滿語文法》，定價國幣一 <lb/>元五角(特價國幣一元二角) <lb/>Shanghai: Printed at the American Presbyterian <lb/>Mission Press, 1892 <lb/>1935年 <lb/>A. Neville J. Whymant, A Mongolian Grammar, <lb/>outlining the Khalkha Mongolian with <lb/>notes on the Buriat, Kalmuck, and Ordoss <lb/>Mogolian, 74 pages, 20 cm. <lb/>懷滿德著，《蒙語文法》，定價國幣一元二 <lb/>角(特價國幣一元) <lb/>London: Kegan Paul, Trench, Trubner, 1926 <lb/>1936年 <lb/>Thomas Watters, On Yuan Chwang&apos;s Travels in <lb/>India 629-645 A. D., edited after his death, <lb/>by T. W. Rhys Davids and S. W. Bushell, <lb/>2 Vols, with two maps and an itinerary by <lb/>Vincent A. Smith, xiii, 401, 357 pages, 2 <lb/>folded maps, 23.4×16 cm. <lb/>瓦達斯著，《大唐西域記箋證》，中華民國 <lb/>二十五年在北平影印，實價國幣八元五角 <lb/>London: Royal Asiatic Society, 1904-1905 <lb/>Henry H. Howorth, of the Mongols, <lb/>from the 9 th to the 19 th century, part I. The <lb/>Mongols proper and the Kalmaks, xxviii, <lb/>743 pages, 2 folded maps, 23.5×16.5 cm. <lb/>霍渥斯著，《蒙古史》第一冊，中華民國貳 <lb/>拾五年影印，實價國幣拾五圓 <lb/>London: Longmans, Green, 1876 <lb/>Wilhelm Grube, Die Sprache und Schrift der <lb/>Jučen, xi, 147 pages, 26.5×19 cm. <lb/>葛魯貝著，《女真語言文字考》，中華民國 <lb/>貳拾五年影印，總發售處文殿閣書莊， <lb/>北平隆福寺街，實價國幣四元 <lb/>L e i p z i g: K o m m i s s i o n s -Ve r l a g v o n O. <lb/>1896 <lb/>Alexander Wylie, Chinese Researches, 4, 3, <lb/>150, 101, 271 pages, 24×16 cm. <lb/></body>

			<page>61 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">文殿閣書莊 <lb/></note>

			<body>衛禮著，《中國研究錄》，中華民國貳拾五 <lb/>年影印，總發售處文殿閣書莊，北平隆 <lb/>福寺街，實價國幣拾元 <lb/>Shanghai, 1897 <lb/>Gaston Cahen, Some Early Russo-Chinese <lb/>Relations, translated and edited by W. <lb/>Ridge, 128 pages, 22.6×15.6 cm. <lb/>嘎 恩 原 著 、 利 治 翻 英 ， 《 早 期 之 中 俄 關 <lb/>係》，中華民國貳拾五年影印，總發售 <lb/>處文殿閣書莊，實價國幣一元三角 <lb/>Shanghai: &quot;The National Review&quot; Office, 1914 <lb/>此書1939、1940年兩次翻印，但尺寸與1936 <lb/>年本皆不盡相同。 <lb/>1937年 <lb/>I. J. Schmidt, Grammatik der Mongolischen <lb/>xii, 179 pages, 27.7×19.7 cm. <lb/>史密德著，《蒙古語文法》，民國貳拾六年 <lb/>影印，總發售處文殿閣書莊，北京隆福 <lb/>寺街，實價三元六角 <lb/>St. Petersburg: Gedruckt in der Buchdruckerei <lb/>d e r K a i s e r l i c h e n A k a d e m i e d e r <lb/>Wissenschaften, 1831 <lb/>此書1939年再次翻印 <lb/>Berthold Laufer, Christian Art in China, 19 <lb/>pages, ill., plates, 26×19 cm. <lb/>勞弗爾著，《中國耶教藝術》，中華民國貳 <lb/>拾六年影印，總發售處文殿閣書莊，北 <lb/>平隆福寺街 <lb/>Mitteilungen des Seminars fur Orientalische <lb/>Sprache, Yahrgang XIII. Erste Abteilung. <lb/>Ostasistische Studien, 1910 <lb/>此書1939年再次翻印 <lb/>E. Bretschneider, Mediaeval Researches, <lb/>from eastern Asiatic sources, 2 vol., <lb/>maps, 24 cm. <lb/>布勒士柰得著，《元明人西域史地論考》， <lb/>實價八元 <lb/>London: K. Paul, 1910 <lb/>W. W. Rockhill, The Journey of William of <lb/>Rubruck to the Eastern Parts of World, <lb/>1253-55, lvi, 304 pages, 1 folded map, <lb/>23.2×16.5 cm. <lb/>洛克希爾譯註，《「魯勃洛克」東遊記》，中 <lb/>華民國貳拾六年影印，總發售處文殿閣書 <lb/>莊，北平隆福寺街，實價國幣六元五角 <lb/>London: Printed for the Hakluyt Society, 1900 <lb/>Jacob Schmidt, Geschichte der Ost-<lb/>Mongolen und ihres Fürstenhauses, xxiv, <lb/>509 pages, 27×19 cm. <lb/>(蒙古)薩 徹辰編纂、(俄國)史密 <lb/>註，《東部蒙古史：蒙 合璧蒙古源 <lb/>流》，實價拾六元 <lb/>St. Peterburg: Gedruckt bei N. Gretsch; Leipzig: <lb/>bei Carl Cnobloch, 1829 <lb/></body>

			<page>62 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">圖書資訊學刊 第15卷 第1期 (2017.6) <lb/></note>

			<body>1938年 <lb/>M P e t i d s d e l a C r o i x , T h e H i s t o r y o f <lb/>Genghizcan the Great, first emperor of the <lb/>Moguls and Tartars, in four books, <lb/>ix, 448 pages, 20 cm. <lb/>(法國)克羅亞著，《成吉斯汗傳》1，民 <lb/>國貳拾七年影印，總發售處文殿閣書 <lb/>莊，北京隆福寺街，實價六元 <lb/>London: J. Darby, 1722 <lb/>Henry H. Howorth, History of the Mongols, <lb/>from the 9 th to the 19 th century, part Ⅱ, the <lb/>so-called tartars of Russia and central Asia, <lb/>division Ⅰ. 6, xxxiv, 626 pages, 23.5×16.5 cm. <lb/>霍渥斯著，《蒙古史》第二冊，民國貳拾七 <lb/>年影印，總發售處文殿閣書莊，北京隆 <lb/>福寺街，實價銀拾三元 <lb/>London: Longmans, Green, and Co., 1880 <lb/>Henry H. Howorth, History of the Mongols, <lb/>from the 9 th to the 19 th century, part Ⅱ, the <lb/>so-called tartars of Russia and central Asia, <lb/>Ⅱ. 4, 461 pages, 23.5×16.5 cm. <lb/>霍渥斯著，《蒙古史》第三冊，民國貳拾七 <lb/>年影印，總發售處文殿閣書莊，北京隆 <lb/>福寺街，實價銀九元五角 <lb/>London: Longmans, Green, and Co., 1880 <lb/>Henry Yule, Cathay and the Way Thither: being <lb/>a collection of medieval notices of China, <lb/>vol. 1, Preliminary essay on the intercourse <lb/>between China and the Western nations previous <lb/>to the discovery of the Cape route, xxiii, 318, <lb/>pages, 3 plates (2 folded), maps, 23 cm. <lb/>裕爾編譯、考狄補訂，《東域記程錄叢》第 <lb/>一冊，民國貳拾七年，總發售處文殿閣 <lb/>書莊，北京隆福寺街，實價七元五角 <lb/>Cambridge: Printed for the Hakluyt Society, <lb/>1915. (Works issued by the Hakluyt <lb/>Society; 2nd ser, no. 38) <lb/>Henry Yule, Cathay and the Way Thither: being <lb/>a collection of medieval notices of China, <lb/>vol. 2, Odoric of Pordenone, xii, 367 <lb/>pages, 1 folded map, 24 cm. <lb/>裕爾編譯、考狄補訂，《東域記程錄叢》第 <lb/>二冊，民國貳拾七年，總發售處文殿閣 <lb/>書莊，北京隆福寺街，實價九元 <lb/>London: Printed for the Society, 1913. <lb/>(Works issued by the Hakluyt Society; 2nd <lb/>ser, no. 33) <lb/>Henry Yule, Cathay and the Way Thither: being a <lb/>collection of medieval notices of China, vol. <lb/>3, Missionary Friars, Rashíduddín, Pegolotti, <lb/>xv, 269 pages, 1 map, 23.5×16.5 cm. <lb/>裕爾編譯、考狄補訂，《東域記程錄叢》第 <lb/>三冊，民國貳拾七年，總發售處文殿閣 <lb/>書莊，北京隆福寺街，實價銀五圓五角 <lb/>London: Printed for the Hakluyt Society, 1914. <lb/>(Works issued by the Hakluyt Society; 2nd <lb/>ser, no. 37) <lb/></body>

			<page>63 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">文殿閣書莊 <lb/></note>

			<body>Isaac Mason, Notes on Chinese Mohammedan <lb/>Literature, 44 pages, 4 plates, 24 cm. <lb/>玫遜編，《中國回教書目》，民國貳拾七年 <lb/>影印，總發售處文殿閣書莊，北京隆福 <lb/>寺街，實價八角 <lb/>Reprinted from Journal of the North-China <lb/>of the Royal Asiatic Society Vol. <lb/>56, 1925 <lb/>Henri Cordier, Bibliotheca Sinica: dictionnaire <lb/>bibliographque des ouvrages relatifs a <lb/>l&apos;empire Chinois, 5 vols., xvii, 4439 pages, <lb/>27×18.9 cm. <lb/>法國考狄編，《西人論中國書目》，民國貳 <lb/>拾七年影印，總發售處文殿閣書莊，北 <lb/>京隆福寺街，實價銀八拾四元 <lb/>Paris: Libraire Orientale &amp; Américaine, 1904-1924 <lb/>1939年 <lb/>Henry Yule, Cathay and the Way being <lb/>a collection of notices of China, <lb/>vol. 4, Ibn Batuta, Benedict Goës, index, <lb/>xii, 359 pages, 1 folded map, 24 cm. <lb/>裕爾編譯、考狄補訂，《東域記程錄叢》第 <lb/>四冊，民國貳拾八年，總發售處文殿閣 <lb/>書莊，北京隆福寺街，實價九元 <lb/>London: Printed for the Hakluyt Society, 1916. <lb/>(Works issued by the Hakluyt Society; 2nd <lb/>ser, no. 41) <lb/>Henry H. Howorth, History of the Mongols, <lb/>from the 9 to the 19 th century, part Ⅲ, <lb/>the Mongols of Persia, x, 776 pages, <lb/>23.5×16.5 cm. <lb/>霍渥斯著，《蒙古史》第四冊，民國貳拾八 <lb/>年影印，總發售處文殿閣書莊，北京隆 <lb/>福寺街 <lb/>London: Longmans, Green, and Co. and New <lb/>York: 15 east 16 th street, 1888 <lb/>Henry H. Howorth, of the Mongols, <lb/>from the 9 th to the 19 th century, part IV, <lb/>supplement and indices, iv, 378 pages, <lb/>23.5×16.5 cm. <lb/>霍渥斯著，《蒙古史》第五冊，民國貳拾九 <lb/>年，北京影印 <lb/>London: Longmans, Green, and Co., New York: <lb/>Bombay, and Calcutta, 1927 <lb/>Alexander Csoma de Kőrös, A Grammar <lb/>of the Tibetan Language, in English: <lb/>prepared, under the patronage of the <lb/>government and the auspices of the <lb/>Asiatic Society of Bengal, xii, 204, 40 <lb/>pages, 27.6×20 cm. <lb/>(匈國)綽瑪著，《藏語文法》(道光十四 <lb/>年版)，民國貳拾八年影印，總發售處 <lb/>文殿閣書莊，北京隆福寺街，實價銀價 <lb/>八元 <lb/>Calcutta: Printed at the Mission Press, Circular <lb/>Road, 1834 <lb/></body>

			<page>64 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">第1期 (2017.6) <lb/></note>
			
			<body>Edouard Chavannes, Les Mémoires Historiques <lb/>de Se-Ma Ts&apos;ien. <lb/>沙畹譯注，《史記》，共六冊，reprinted in <lb/>China, 實價九拾五元 <lb/>Paris: Ernest Leroux éditeur, 1895-1905 <lb/>Isaal Jacob Schmidt, Mongolisch-Deutsch-<lb/>Russisches Wörterbuch, nebst einem <lb/>D e u t s c h e n u n d e i e m R u s i s c h e n <lb/>Wörtregister, viii, 613 pages, 28×20 cm. <lb/>史密 編，《合璧蒙 俄語辭典》，民國 <lb/>北京隆福寺街 <lb/>Санктпетербургъ: Изд. Императорскою <lb/>академію наукъ, 1835 <lb/>Fredrich Hirth, China and the Roman Orient, <lb/>re s e a rc h e s i n t o t h e i r a n c i e n t a n d <lb/>mediaeval relations as represented in old <lb/>Chinese records, xvi, 329 pages, 5 folded <lb/>plates, 23 cm. <lb/>(德國)夏德編，《大秦國全錄》，中華民 <lb/>國二十八年影印，實價拾六元 <lb/>Leipzig, 1885 <lb/>Paul Pelliot, Les Mongols la Papauté, 3 vols., <lb/>27 cm. <lb/>( 法 國 ) 伯 希 和 ， 《 蒙 古 與 羅 馬 教 廷 通 <lb/>函》，共三冊，實價六元五角 <lb/>Paris: Extrait de la Revue de l&apos;Orient Chrétien. <lb/>3e série, t. III (XXIII), nos. 1 et 2 (1922-<lb/>23), pp. 3-30; t. IV (XXIV), nos. 3 et 4 <lb/>(1924), pp. 225-335; t. VIII (XXVIII), no. <lb/>1 et 2 (1931-32), pp. 3-84. <lb/>Matteo Ripa, Memoirs of Father Ripa, during <lb/>thirteen years&apos; residence at the court of <lb/>Peking in the service of the Emperor of <lb/>China, selected and translated from the <lb/>Italian, by Fortunato Prandi, viii, 160 <lb/>pages, 18.5×12.5 cm. <lb/>馬國賢撰，《京庭十有三年記》，中華民國 <lb/>二十八年影印 <lb/>London: John Murray, Albemarle Street, 1855 <lb/>W. Woodville Rockhill, Tibet: a geographical, <lb/>historical sketch, <lb/>derived from Chinese sources, 291 pages, <lb/>6 folded maps, 24 cm. <lb/>《吐蕃考：據唐代中國史料》，Wên tien ko <lb/>shuchuang, 1939 <lb/>London: Royal Asiatic Society of Great Britain <lb/>and Ireland, 1891 <lb/>E r n e s t J. E i t e l, H a n d -B o o k o f C h i n e s e <lb/>Buddhism: being a Sanskrit-Chinese <lb/>dictionary, with vocabularies of Buddhist <lb/>in Pali, Singhalese, Siamese, <lb/>B u r m e s e, Ti b e t a n, M o n g o l i a n a n d <lb/>Japanese, 324 pages, 22.3×15.2 cm. <lb/>《中國佛教梵漢字典》，中華民國二十八年 <lb/>影印，Peking: Wen Tien Ko <lb/>Tokyo: Sanshusha, 1904 <lb/></body>

			<page>65 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">文殿閣書莊 <lb/></note>

			<body>History of the Two Tartar Conquerors of China: <lb/>including the two journeys into Tartary of <lb/>Father Ferdinand Verbiest, in the suite of <lb/>the Emperor Kang-Hi: from the French of <lb/>Père Pierre Joseph d&apos;Orléans, to which is <lb/>added Father Pereira&apos;s journey into Tartary <lb/>in the suite of the same emperor, from P. <lb/>Joseph d&apos;Orlèans and Nicolaas Witsen, 4, <lb/>153 pages, 23.2×15.7 cm. <lb/>南懷仁，《韃靼扈從記》(據法荷兩文史 <lb/>料)，民國貳拾八年影印，總發售處文 <lb/>殿閣書莊，北京隆福寺，實價六元五角 <lb/>London: Printed for the Hakluyt Society, 1854 <lb/>Kenneth Scott Latourette, The History of Early <lb/>Relations between The United States and <lb/>China 1784-1844, 209 pages, 23×13.5 cm. <lb/>賴德烈著，《中美初期關係史》，1939 <lb/>New Haven: Yale University Press, 1917 <lb/>1940年 <lb/>James Legge, The Chinese Classics: with a <lb/>translation, critical and exegetical notes, <lb/>prolegomena, and copious indexes, Anastic <lb/>Edition, Wen Tien Ko, Peking, China <lb/>26.2×18.5 cm. <lb/>李雅各譯，《李雅各英譯七經》，中華民 <lb/>國二十九年影印(註十)，A n a s t i c <lb/>Edition, Wen Tien Ko, Peking, China <lb/>Vol. I, Confucian Analects; the great learning; and, <lb/>the doctrine of the mean, xv, 503 pages, <lb/>第一冊《論語》 <lb/>Oxford, at the Clarendon Press, 1893 <lb/>Vol. II, The Works of Mencius, viii, 587 pages, <lb/>第二冊《孟子》 <lb/>Oxford, at the Clarendon Press, 1895 <lb/>Vol. III Part I, The first part of the Shoo King, <lb/>or the books of T&apos;ang, the book of <lb/>the book of Hea, the book of Shang, and <lb/>the prolegomena, xii, 208, 279 pages, 1 <lb/>folded map, <lb/>第三冊《尚書》上 <lb/>London: Henry Frowde, Oxford University <lb/>Press Warehouse Amen Corner E.C. <lb/>Vol. Part II, The fifth part of the Shoo King, <lb/>or the books of Chow, and the indexes, <lb/>455 pages, <lb/>第四冊《尚書》下 <lb/>Hong Kong: at the Author&apos;s, London: Trubner <lb/>&amp; Co., 60, Paternoster Row, 1865 <lb/>Vol. IV Part I, The first part of the <lb/>or the lessons from the states; and the <lb/>prolegomena, xii, 182, 243 pages, 1 <lb/>folded map, <lb/>第五冊《詩經》上 <lb/>London: Henry Frowde, Oxford University <lb/>Press Warehouse Amen Corner E.C. <lb/>Vol. IV Part II, The second, third, and fourth <lb/>parts of the She-King, or the minor odes <lb/>of the kingdom, the greater odes of the <lb/>kingdom, the sacrificial odes and praise-<lb/>and the indexes, 541 pages, <lb/></body>

			<page>66 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">圖書資訊學刊 第15卷 第1期 (2017.6) <lb/></note>

			<body>第六冊《詩經》下 <lb/>London: Frowde, Oxford University <lb/>Press Warehouse Amen Corner E.C. <lb/>Vol. V Part I, Dukes Yin, Hwan, Chwang, <lb/>Min, He, Wan, Seuen and Ch&apos;ing, and <lb/>the prolegomena, x, 147, 410 pages, 2 <lb/>maps, <lb/>第七冊《春秋左傳》上 <lb/>Hong Kong: Lane, Crawford &amp; Co., London: <lb/>Trübner &amp; Co., 60, Parternoster Row, 1872. <lb/>Vol. V Part II, Dukes Seang, Ch&apos;aou, Ting, and <lb/>Gae, with Tso&apos;s appendix, and the indexes, <lb/>pages, <lb/>第八冊《春秋左傳》下 <lb/>London: Henry Frowde, Oxford University <lb/>Press Warehouse Amen Corner E.C. <lb/>Edouard Biot, Le Tcheou-Li ou Rites des <lb/>Tcheou, 3 vols., 23 cm. <lb/>《周禮》，中華民國二十九年影印，We n <lb/>Tien Ko, Peking, China <lb/>Paris: L&apos;Imprimerie Nationale, 1851 <lb/>William Frederick Mayers, The Chinese <lb/>R e a d e r &apos;s M a n u a l : a h a n d b o o k o f <lb/>biographical, historical, <lb/>general literary reference, 444 pages, <lb/>23.2×14.9 cm. <lb/>梅輝立著，《中國辭彙》，中華民國二十九 <lb/>年影印，Wen Tien Ke, Peking, China. <lb/>Presbyterian Mission Press, 1924 <lb/>Frank Herring Chalfant, Early Chinese Writing, <lb/>35 L plates, 33×25.2 cm. <lb/>沙方福著，《中國古文字》，民國二十九年 <lb/>影印 <lb/>New York: Memoires of the Carnegie <lb/>Vol. 4, No. 1, Sept. 1906 <lb/>Documents sur les Tou-<lb/>kiue (Turcs) Occidentaux, vi, 378 pages, 1 <lb/>folded map, 26.2×19.3 cm. <lb/>沙畹著，《西面突厥誌》，民國二十九年 <lb/>影印，總發行處文殿閣書莊，北京隆 <lb/>福寺街 <lb/>S t. -P é t e r s b u rg: C o m m i s s i o n n a i r e s d e <lb/>Impériale de sciences, 1903 <lb/>John Dudgeon, Historical Sketch of the <lb/>Ecclesiastical, political, and commercial <lb/>relations of Russia with China, drawn <lb/>chiefly from original sources, iii, 8, 53, 23 <lb/>pages, 23 cm. <lb/>德 貞 著 ， 《 中 俄 政 教 誌 略 》 ， 中 華 民 國 <lb/>二十九年影印，Anastic Edition, Wen <lb/>Ko <lb/>Peking, 1872 <lb/>1941年 <lb/>Gaston Cahen, Histoire des Relations de la <lb/>Russie avec la Chine, sous Pierre le <lb/>Grand (1689-1730), 274, ccxvii pages, <lb/>24×16.3 cm. <lb/></body>

			<page>67 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">文殿閣書莊 <lb/></note>

			<body>嘎恩著，《清初中俄交涉史》，中華民國 <lb/>三十年影印，Anastic Edition <lb/>Paris: Librairie Félix Alcan, 1912 <lb/>疑似部分： <lb/>該部分只以筆者親見書籍實體為依據 <lb/>編寫，其樣式、用紙皆與文殿閣書莊影印本 <lb/>相近似，但因為缺少關鍵資訊，又無法在各 <lb/>期《文殿閣書目》中找到資訊完全一致的對 <lb/>象，故只列作疑似。 <lb/>W. W. Rockhill, The Journey of William of <lb/>Rubruck to the Eastern Parts of the World, <lb/>1253-55, lvi, 304, 20 pages, 1 folded map, <lb/>23×15.5 cm. <lb/>美 國 柔 克 義 譯 註 ， 《 「 魯 勃 洛 克 」 東 遊 <lb/>記》，民國三拾年，北京影印 <lb/>London: Printed for the Hakluyt Society, 1900 <lb/>Henry Yule, Cathay and the way thither: <lb/>being a collection of medieval notices <lb/>China, vol. I, Preliminary essay on <lb/>the intercourse between China and the <lb/>Western nations previous to the discovery <lb/>of the Cape route, xxiii, 318 pages, 2 <lb/>plates, 23×15.8 cm. <lb/>裕爾編譯、考狄補訂，《東域記程錄叢》第 <lb/>壹冊，民國三十壹年北京影印 <lb/>London: Printed for the Hakluyt Society, 1915 <lb/>Thomas Watters, On Yuan Chwang&apos;s Travels in <lb/>India 629-645 A. D., edited after his death, <lb/>by T. W. Rhys Davids and S. W. Bushell, <lb/>2 Vols, with two maps and an itinerary by <lb/>Vincent A. Smith <lb/>《大唐西域記注釋》，reprinted in Peking, <lb/>1941 <lb/>London: Royal Asiatic Society, 1904-1905 <lb/>與Licoph Service的甄別 <lb/>筆者在整理以上書目的過程中，發現 <lb/>在美國各大學圖書館館藏資訊中標註了一批 <lb/>Service字樣的影印西文書，譬 <lb/>如普林斯頓大學圖書館中有Die Sprache und <lb/>Schrift der Jučen(《女真文字考》)、Les <lb/>Mongols et la Papauté(《蒙古與羅馬教廷 <lb/>通函》)、Geschichte der Ost-Mongolen und <lb/>ihres Fürstenhauses(《東部蒙古史》)， <lb/>史丹佛大學圖書館藏有Christian Art in China <lb/>(《中國耶教藝術》)、Notes on the Malay <lb/>Archipelago and Malacca(《南洋群島文獻 <lb/>錄》)，國會圖書館則藏有An Enumeration <lb/>of all the Plants Known from China Proper <lb/>(《英文中國植物學索引》)，澳大利亞 <lb/>國立圖書館亦有Christian Art in China(《 <lb/>中國耶教藝術》)，這些書大半在文殿閣 <lb/>影印西書之列。此外，筆者親眼見到一冊 <lb/>《史記序》法譯本(Introduction d&apos;Édouard <lb/>Chavannes, A Sa Traduction des Mémoires <lb/>Historiques de Se-Ma Ts&apos;ien)，在其書名頁 <lb/>印刷了Licoph Service(圖七)。 <lb/>1 9 4 6 年 3 月 2 1 日 ， 職 哈 佛 燕 漢 <lb/>和 圖 書 館 多 年 的 裘 開 明 去 信 蘇 聯 學 院 <lb/></body>

			<page>68 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">第1期 (2017.6) <lb/></note>

			<body>Basil Alexéiev教授，談到從北京購買的影 <lb/>印書籍： <lb/>由於1941年爆發了太平洋戰爭，我 <lb/>們無法直接與北平Licoph Service通 <lb/>信，在此之前，我們曾購買過他們 <lb/>的全部出版物。我聽說北平Licoph <lb/>Service現在已經被清算，因為在日 <lb/>本人短期統治北平期間，該公司的 <lb/>一位奠基人曾與日本人合作。可 <lb/>是，在北平可能還存有他們出版的 <lb/>複本(程煥文，2008，頁328)。 <lb/>考慮到松村太郎與王殿馨的關係，此信 <lb/>曾讓筆者懷疑Licoph Service即文殿閣書莊， <lb/>只不過是其對外的一個稱謂。但隨著研究的 <lb/>深入，筆者否定了這一觀點。 <lb/>首先，據裘開明所稱，Licoph Service <lb/>在二戰結束後，因與日人合作已被清算，這 <lb/>的確與松村太郎協助文殿閣印書事相仿。但 <lb/>圖七 沙畹《史記序》法譯本 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">文殿閣書莊 <lb/></note>

			<body>鄧之誠在1947年9月1日的日記中寫道：「文 <lb/>殿閣來，言文殿、文奎等五家書鋪以二億買 <lb/>連其他總數二千餘種，廉哉！以幣值計之， <lb/>不及承平時二千金也。」(鄧之誠，2012， <lb/>頁436)由此可見，戰後文殿閣書莊的生意 <lb/>並未過於受時局影響。 <lb/>其次，筆者仔細查閱標有Licoph Service <lb/>的書籍，除《史記序》法譯本外，該所字 <lb/>樣通常出現在封底內頁的左上角處，且明 <lb/>顯非印製，而是採用了貼附標籤的形式。由 <lb/>圖八可知Licoph Service應位於Chengfu Postal <lb/>District，筆者查閱了相關的郵政區域圖，發 <lb/>現Chengfu即「成府」，位於清華園東側， <lb/>這與文殿閣店址相差甚遠。 <lb/>最後，由畢樹棠的日記可知，此時北 <lb/>京有許多書肆影印西文書籍，兜售與外國各 <lb/>大學、圖書館，以掙取美元，Licoph Service <lb/>極有可能是其中之一。而文殿閣有其自定的 <lb/>英文名稱：Wen Tien Ke(Ko)，並偶爾會 <lb/>印於其西文圖書上(圖九)，日本各大學圖 <lb/>書館因保存了原書的封面，編目時亦遵照此 <lb/>名稱。 <lb/>圖八 《英文中國植物學索引》之封底內頁，該本為哈佛大學漢和圖書館收藏。 <lb/></body>

			<page>70 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">第1期 (2017.6) <lb/></note>

			<body>基於以上三方面的比對，筆者認為這 <lb/>是兩家完全無關的機構，雖然同時從事了翻 <lb/>印西書的事業。英美某些大學圖書館在編目 <lb/>時，把二者混為一談。 <lb/>影響與意義 <lb/>無論是國學文庫還是西文漢學著作翻 <lb/>印，文殿閣書莊編選的思路均注重中西交通 <lb/>史、邊疆史地、民族語言的一手資料、這 <lb/>反映出謀劃者敏銳的洞察力，意識到北京作 <lb/>為中國傳統的文化、學術中心，中西方學 <lb/>界不僅在此砥礪切磋，更是培養年輕學生 <lb/>的最佳場所，這兩方 面 都 需 要 經 典 著 作 的 <lb/>傳 播 與 滋 養 。 而 能 夠 連 結 中 日 方 的 各 類 <lb/>資 源 ， 形 成 系 列 的 出 版 物 ， 這 也 說 明 了 <lb/>錢 稻 孫 松 村 太 郎 、 王 馨 、 王 殿 升 兄 <lb/>弟細緻籌謀，絕非一時興起。 <lb/>在故都北京這一文化中心翻印如此多 <lb/>的西文著述，其意義十分重大。北京地區大 <lb/>學、研究所、圖書館、博物院林立，學術 <lb/>資源最為豐富，與國外學界的交往也最為密 <lb/>切。上世紀二三十年代陳垣等人發願通過自 <lb/>己的努力趕上法國、日本的漢學研究，「奪 <lb/>取漢學中心」(汪潤，2009，頁25)。在此 <lb/>圖九 Wen Tien Ke(Ko) <lb/></body>

			<page>71 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">文殿閣書莊 <lb/></note>

			<body>背景下，北京大學、清華大學、輔仁大學、 <lb/>燕京大學、中研院(史語所)、北平研究院 <lb/>的機構培養了一大批有志青年，他們投身於 <lb/>歷史、地理、語言等領域的漢學研究中，這 <lb/>也從客觀上催生了翻印事業的現實需求。 <lb/>雖然「翻印」一詞總含有不良的觀感， <lb/>但從其初衷上講，確有推動學術研究的考 <lb/>慮，絕非完全逐利。《文殿閣新舊書目》第 <lb/>3期介紹《(英文)中國研究錄》的廣告語 <lb/>這樣寫道：「原書，一八九七年刊於上海， <lb/>國學界咸無不知。此亦絕版既久，市價百元 <lb/>以上，而非必得，茲亦影印，並抑其價，以 <lb/>貢學界。」而影印本的價格只有十元，這與 <lb/>大之詞，但巨大的價格差距可知此本必獲讀 <lb/>書人的青睞。同樣，正因為此，文殿閣書莊 <lb/>的中西文翻印事業並未受到指責，在大多數 <lb/>場合下中國學人均給予正面的評價。 <lb/>1934年至1941年間，恰是私立輔仁大 <lb/>學、燕京大學快速發展的階段，而此兩者與 <lb/>國外學術界皆有極其密切的聯繫；與此同時 <lb/>中法漢學研究所、中德學會等中外合辦機構 <lb/>活躍在北京，文殿閣書莊印行的國學文庫、 <lb/>西文漢學著作大都通過它們的介紹或代購流 <lb/>傳到歐美學界。無論是歐美大學還是同樣具 <lb/>有知識版權意識的日本學術機構，對翻印之 <lb/>事幾乎無惡語相加，涉及文章全為學術引用 <lb/>(Shadick, 1963)。這一方面可以理解為學 <lb/>術界對此次翻印行為的默認，另一方面則表 <lb/>明在原本稀見的客觀情況下，文殿閣影印本 <lb/>的確成為中外學者可以依賴的原始材料。 <lb/>隨著太平洋戰爭的爆發，北京與歐美學 <lb/>界之間的溝通趨於中斷，影印事業因為銷路 <lb/>無多，成為了蝕本買賣難以為繼。而這數十 <lb/>種影印圖書卻成為西方經典漢學著作流傳中 <lb/>的重要一環，譬如北京中華書局日前影印出 <lb/>版的《西人論中國書目》即以文殿閣書莊本 <lb/>作為底本，為一代代學人服務。有鑑於此， <lb/>其背後的人與事亦值得世人知曉。 <lb/>註釋 <lb/>註一： 1930年向達即已在國立北平圖書館任 <lb/>職，而參與策劃國學文庫的錢稻孫 <lb/>自中華圖書館協會1925年成立時即為 <lb/>會員，兩者以北京文化學術界、國立 <lb/>北平圖書館為紐帶，應有較為密切的 <lb/>交往，因此筆者認為向達很有可能知 <lb/>悉該套叢書的內情。此外，北京大 <lb/>同書店作為國立北平圖書館的隸屬 <lb/>機構，亦曾刊登廣告介紹文殿閣影印 <lb/>的西文漢學名著四種，參見《中華圖 <lb/>書館協會會報》第11卷第6期，頁50 <lb/>(中華圖書館協會執行委員會編輯， <lb/>1936)。 <lb/>註二： 除對錯之外，該文還有一些說法尚無 <lb/>法證實。撰者曾寫道：「聽說從前在 <lb/>東三省印行過」。首先此話不知是特 <lb/>指某一種書，還是指國學文庫中的數 <lb/>種或大部，其次筆者曾就此嘗試一一 <lb/>比對，除《滿洲實錄》(9)外，並 <lb/>未見到有哪些選本在東三省印行過。 <lb/></body>

			<page>72 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">第1期 (2017.6) <lb/></note>

			<body>註三： 上世紀二三十年代，北京一地小書店 <lb/>翻印成風，引發讀者、學界極大憤慨， <lb/>政府初無動於衷，後由於輿論壓力，嚴 <lb/>厲打擊，遂有收斂之勢。參見〈北平翻 <lb/>印書之惡運〉(作者不詳，1932)。 <lb/>註四： 國學文庫全部49編皆在1937年「盧 <lb/>溝橋事變」前印行，衛德明在編寫 <lb/>〈1938年以來在華出版漢學書目選〉 <lb/>時將《大金國志》等諸冊列入該目。 <lb/>雖然時間上並不符合1938年後之說，但 <lb/>事實如此，非筆者錯錄，特此說明。 <lb/>註五： 國學文庫中有的選本曾重印過，如 <lb/>第1編《皇明四夷考》首版時沒有句 <lb/>讀，而1937年2月再版時標記了標點。 <lb/>註六： 就Wilhelm Plage與日本文化界的交涉 <lb/>及日本修改知識財產權法律條文事， <lb/>可參見Goldstein與Straus(2009, pp. <lb/>135-136)。 <lb/>註七： 松村太郎與錢稻孫、周作人等人的交 <lb/>集可參見〈1930年代，在日本如何購 <lb/>讀中國書報？〉(蘇枕書，2016)。 <lb/>而錢稻孫與松村太郎(字紙簍社) <lb/>的交往則見高山杉(2016)。這兩篇 <lb/>學術散文功力深厚，皆可視為各自 <lb/>領域的代表之作，筆者不再贅述。 <lb/>而有關松村太郎自身的史料，筆者只 <lb/>見到他人的一篇回憶文章--〈松筠 <lb/>閣與松村太郎〉(魏廣洲，1994)， <lb/>作者魏廣洲(1912-2006)，14歲時 <lb/>經族人介紹到北京琉璃廠松筠閣學習 <lb/>古舊書版本知識，25歲自立門戶，作 <lb/>為親歷者其回憶頗為可信。文中談到 <lb/>因與松筠閣店主劉際唐立場不合，「 <lb/>松村太郎就給隆福寺文殿閣介紹生意 <lb/>去了」，並提到1937年盧溝橋事變 <lb/>後，松村太郎回國。 <lb/>註八： 《文殿閣新書目》中「影印漢學西書 <lb/>目」偶有西文拼寫錯誤，筆者自行 <lb/>訂正，並非簡單抄錄。價格資訊只會 <lb/>在封底處出現，但並非每本書都有， <lb/>且有時會出現小幅調整，譬如在《 <lb/>文殿閣新書目》前後數編的價格與書 <lb/>籍實體封底標識不同，筆者認為這是 <lb/>一種隨行就市的策略，在此筆者優先 <lb/>記錄封底價格。在《文殿閣新書目》 <lb/>的宣傳介紹中，《滿語文法》、《 <lb/>史記》、《蒙古與羅馬教廷通函》三 <lb/>種書宣稱有精裝本，在查找比對的過 <lb/>程中筆者發現了《史記》的平裝本， <lb/>而《滿語文法》在國內外公藏機構只 <lb/>有平裝的記錄，此時期北京地區的西 <lb/>文書精裝本封面很難印製各類資訊， <lb/>只為整潔的布面硬裝，這意味著全書 <lb/>幾乎無任何地方可以判定是新的翻印 <lb/>本，故此筆者只記錄可以查證的平裝 <lb/>本。另外，筆者從歐美各處購入的書 <lb/>籍，相當數量者已遭重新裝訂，原軟 <lb/>皮或被去除或被加裝硬殼，價格項如 <lb/>並未抄寫，則是付諸闕如。 <lb/>註九： 此書所有日本大學的館藏資訊皆標為 <lb/>1937年影印，而筆者在美國大學資料 <lb/>庫(HathiTrust)獲得的書影電子檔 <lb/></body>

			<page>73 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">文殿閣書莊 <lb/></note>

			<body>顯示為中華民國27年，且1939年4月 <lb/>訂《文殿閣新書目》中該書一項並未 <lb/>標注有再版字樣，故筆者將此書只歸 <lb/>於1938年，特此說明。 <lb/>註十： 《李雅各英譯七經》第五冊、第六冊 <lb/>的封面都標記為Vol. V，而實際上都 <lb/>應為第四卷，筆者自行訂正；該書各 <lb/>卷所依據的底本並不一致，經過仔細 <lb/>確無誤的，可參見〈理雅各《中國經 <lb/>典》主要版本考辨及其他〉(姜哲， <lb/>2015，頁40)。該套叢書(八冊)和 <lb/>《中國辭彙》、《周禮》(三冊)在 <lb/>其書名頁背面標注為中華民國二十八 <lb/>年影印，筆者編目時皆依照封面資訊 <lb/>列入中華民國二十九年。 <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">致謝 <lb/>本研究自2015年末開始構思，彙集各史 <lb/>料文獻中的記述。最終完成得益於在美好友 <lb/>王躍長久以來不辭辛勞將筆者從歐美各國所 <lb/>購書籍寄送至北京。中國國家圖書館古籍館 <lb/>的彭福英女士、中國社會科學院文學研究所 <lb/>的鄭海娟女士協助查驗了數種書刊。另，南 <lb/>京師範大學的劉婉明女士協助筆者譯校了日 <lb/>文資料，在此一併感謝！ <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>參考文獻 References <lb/>中華圖書館協會執行委員會編輯(1936)。 <lb/>北平大同書店新書報告。中華圖書館協 <lb/>會會報，11(6)，50。【Chinese Library <lb/>Association. (1936). [Bei Ping Da Tong <lb/>Dian xin shu bao gao]. Bulletin of the <lb/>Library Association of China, 11(6), 50. (in <lb/>Chinese)】。 <lb/>日本外務省(1935)。圖書受入。外務省 <lb/>報，318，35-44。【Ministry of Foreign <lb/>Affairs of Japan. (1935). Tosho ukeire. <lb/>Gaimushoho, 318, 35-44. (in Japanese)】 <lb/>巴 兆 祥 ( 2 0 0 8) 。 論 中 國 方 志 流 布 日 本 <lb/>的 特 點 。上 海 大 學 學 報 ( 社 會 科 學 <lb/>版)，15(2)，107-114。【Ba, Zhao-<lb/>Xiang (2008). On characteristics of the <lb/>spread of Chinese local chronicles to <lb/>Japan. Journal of Shanghai University <lb/>(Social Sciences Edition), 15(2), 107-<lb/>114. (in Chinese)】 <lb/>文殿閣書莊(1935)。文殿閣新舊書目第 1 <lb/>期。北京市：文殿閣書莊。【Wen Tien <lb/>Ke. (1935). Wen Tien Ke new bibliography <lb/>of old books Vol, 1. Peking: Wen Tien Ke. <lb/>文殿閣書莊(1936)。文殿閣新舊書目第 3 <lb/>期。北京市：文殿閣書莊。【Wen Tien <lb/>Ke. (1936). Wen Tien Ke new bibliography <lb/>of old books Vol, 3. Peking: Wen Tien Ke. <lb/>(in Chinese)】 <lb/>文 殿 閣 書 莊 ( 1 9 3 9) 。文 殿 閣 方 志 目 。 <lb/>北京市：文殿閣書莊。【We n T i e n <lb/>(1939). Wen Tien Ke [fang zhi mu]. <lb/>Wen Tien Ke. (in Chinese)】 <lb/>內藤湖南、長澤規矩也(2 0 0 6)。日本學 <lb/>人中國訪書記 (錢婉約、宋炎譯)。 <lb/>北京市：中華書局。【Naito Konan, &amp; <lb/>Nagasawa Kikuya (2006). [Ri Ben xue ren <lb/>Zhong Guo fang shu ji]. ([Wan-Yue Qian] <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>74 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">圖書資訊學刊 第15卷 第1期 (2017.6) <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>&amp; [Yan Song], Trans.). Beijing: <lb/>Book. (in Chinese)】 <lb/>史學會(1935)。《史學雜誌》 (Shigaku-<lb/>【[Shi Xue Hui]. (1935). Shigaku-Zasshi <lb/>[di 46 bian di 11 hao]. Tokyo: [Shi Xue <lb/>Hui]. (in Japanese)】 <lb/>作 者 不 詳 ( 1 9 3 2 年 5 月 3 1 日 ) 。 北 平 翻 <lb/>印 書 之 惡 運 。中 央 日 報 ， 第 2 版 。 <lb/>【Anonymous. (1932, May 31). [Bei <lb/>Ping fan yin shu zhi e yun]. Central Daily <lb/>News, p. 2. (in Chinese)】 <lb/>作者不詳(1936)。雜報。書誌學，6(6)， <lb/>248。【Anonymous. (1936). [Za bao]. <lb/>[Shu Zhi Xue], 6(6), 248. (in Japanese)】 <lb/>李慧(2 0 1 0)。文獻保存同志會第一號工 <lb/>作報告(1 9 4 0年4月2日)考釋。在國 <lb/>家圖書館善本特藏部(編)，文津學 <lb/>志第 3輯 (頁3 6 -4 3)。北京市：國家 <lb/>圖書館。【[Li, Hui] (2010). [Wen xian <lb/>bao cun tong zhi hui di yi hao gong zuo <lb/>bao gao (1940nian 4yue 2ri) kao shi]. In <lb/>National Library of China, [Shan Ben Te <lb/>Cang Bu] (Ed.), Wen jin xue zhi [di 3 ji] <lb/>(pp. 36-43). Beijing: National Library of <lb/>China. (in Chinese)】 <lb/>汪潤(2009)。『奪取漢學中心』的理念與 <lb/>實踐--以《輔仁學志》為中心(未出 <lb/>學院，北京市。【[Wang, Run] (2009). <lb/>[&quot;Duo qu han xue zhong xin&quot; de li nian yu <lb/>shi jian-Yi &quot;Fu Ren Xue Zhi&quot; wei zhong <lb/>(Unpublished doctoral dissertation). <lb/>School of History, Beijing Normal <lb/>University, Beijing. (in Chinese)】 <lb/>沈津(2008)。傅斯年圖書館的鎮庫之寶： <lb/>群玉集、碧雲集。收藏家，8，65-68。 <lb/>【Shen, Jin (2008). Group Jade Collection <lb/>and Jasper Collection of Fu Si Nian Library. <lb/>Collectors, 8, 65-68. (in Chinese)】 <lb/>明(1933)。新書介紹：遼居雜著乙稿、渤 <lb/>海國志長編要刪、清初史料四種。國 <lb/>立北平圖書館館刊， 7(6)，114-116。 <lb/>【[Ming] (1933). Notice of new books: <lb/>[Liao Ju Za Zhe Yi Gao, Bo Hai Guo Zhi <lb/>Bian Yao Shan, Qing Chu Shi Liao <lb/>Si Zhong]. Bulletin of the National Library <lb/>of Peiping, 7(6), 114-116. (in Chinese)】 <lb/>長澤規矩也(1934)。質疑應答。書誌學， <lb/>2(5)，340-341。【Nagasawa Kikuya <lb/>(1934). [Zhi yi ying da]. [Shu Zhi Xue], <lb/>2(5), 340-341. (in Japanese)】 <lb/>姜哲(2015)。理雅各《中國經典》主要版 <lb/>本考辨及其他。國際漢學，2，34-41。 <lb/>【Jiang, Zhe (2015). The vicissitudinous <lb/>history of the main versions of James <lb/>The Chinese Classics. International <lb/>Sinology, 2, 34-41. (in Chinese)】 <lb/>禹貢學會(1 9 3 5)。《禹貢》第 4卷第 7 <lb/>期 。北京市：禹貢學會。【[Yu Gong <lb/>Xue Hui]. (1935). [&quot;Yu Gong&quot; di 4 juan <lb/>di 7 qi]. Peking: [Yu Gong Xue Hui]. (in <lb/>Chinese)】 <lb/>禹貢學會(1 9 3 6)。《禹貢》第 5卷第 3、 <lb/>4期。北京市：禹貢學會。【[Yu Gong <lb/>Xue Hui]. (1936). [&quot;Yu Gong&quot; di 5 juan <lb/>di 3, 4 qi]. Peking: [Yu Gong Xue Hui]. (in <lb/>Chinese)】 <lb/>孫殿起(編)(2001)。琉璃廠小志。北京 <lb/>市：北京古籍。【[Sun, Dian-Qi] (Ed.). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>75 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>文殿閣書莊 <lb/>(2001). [Liu Li Chang xiao zhi]. Beijing: <lb/>[Bei Jing Gu Ji]. (in Chinese)】 <lb/>高山杉(2016年10月16日)。《字紙簍》 <lb/>中的《學舌》。南方都市報 ．閱讀週 <lb/>刊，第8版。【[Gao, Shan-Shan] (2016, <lb/>October 16). [&quot;Zi Zhi Lou&quot; zhong de &quot;Xue <lb/>She&quot;]. [Nan Fang Dou Shi Bao, Yue <lb/>Zhou p. 8. (in Chinese)】 <lb/>畢樹棠(2 0 1 4)。螺君日記 。北京市：海 <lb/>豚。【[Bi, Shu-Tang] (2014). [Luo jun ri <lb/>ji]. Beijing: Dolphin Books. (in Chinese)】 <lb/>無忌(1936年4月30日)。翻印舊書之風。 <lb/>大公報 ．圖書副刊 ，第11版。【[ Wu <lb/>Ji] (1936, April 30). [Fan yin jiu shu zhi <lb/>feng]. [Da Bao, Tu Shu Fu Kan], p. <lb/>11. (in Chinese)】 <lb/>程煥文(編)(2008)。裘開明年譜。桂林 <lb/>市：廣西師範大學。【[Cheng, Huan-<lb/>Wen] (Ed.). (2008). A chronicle of Alfred <lb/>K&apos;aiming Ch&apos;iu&apos;s life. Kweilin: Guangxi <lb/>Normal University Press. (in Chinese)】 <lb/>楊 殿 珣 ( 2 0 1 0 ) 。 書 林 掇 英 --魏 隱 儒 <lb/>古 籍 版 本 知 見 錄 序 。收 藏 家 ， 1 0 ， <lb/>23-30。【Yang, Dianxun (2010). Wei <lb/>Yinru&apos;s record of ancient books edition. <lb/>Collectors, 10, 23-30. (in Chinese)】 <lb/>楊聯陞(2 0 1 3)。哈佛遺墨 。北京市：商 <lb/>務印書館。【Yang, Lien-Sheng (2013). <lb/>[Ha Fo yi mo]. Beijing: The Commercial <lb/>Press. (in Chinese)】 <lb/>雷夢水(1988)。書林瑣記。北京市：人民日 <lb/>報。【[Lei, Meng-Shui] (1988). lin suo <lb/>ji]. Beijing: People&apos;s Daily Press. (in Chinese)】 <lb/>鄧之誠(2 0 1 2)。鄧之誠文史劄記 。南京 <lb/>市：鳳凰。【[Deng, Zhi-Cheng] (2012). <lb/>[Deng Zhi Cheng wen shi zha ji]. Nanjing: <lb/>Phoenix. (in Chinese)】 <lb/>鄭振鐸(2016)。為國家保存文化：鄭振鐸 <lb/>搶救珍稀文獻書信日記輯錄。北京市： <lb/>中華書局。【Zheng, Zhendao (2016). <lb/>[Wei guo jia bao cun wen hua: Zheng <lb/>Zhendao qiang jiu zhen xi wen xian shu <lb/>xin ri ji ji lu]. Beijing: Zhonghua Book. (in <lb/>Chinese)】 <lb/>蕘公(1 9 4 3)。古書之翻印與舊書業的進 <lb/>步--書林逸話(下)。古今，14，27-<lb/>32。【[Rao Gong] (1943). [Gu shu zhi fan <lb/>yin yu jiu shu ye de jin bu: Shu Lin Yi Hua <lb/>(xia)]. [Gu Jin], 14, 27-32. (in Chinese)】 <lb/>魏 廣 洲 ( 1 9 9 4 年 1 0 月 1 日 ) 。 松 筠 閣 與 <lb/>松村太郎。文匯讀書週報 ，第7 版。 <lb/>【[Wei, Guang-Zhou] (1994, October 1). <lb/>[Song Yun Ge yu Matsumura Taro]. [Wen <lb/>Du Shu Zhou Bao], p. 7. (in Chinese)】 <lb/>蘇枕書(2016年8月28日)。1930年代，在 <lb/>日本如何購讀中國書報？南方都市報． <lb/>閱讀週刊 ，第7版。【[Su, Zhen-Shu] <lb/>(2016, August 28). [1930 nian dai, zai Ri <lb/>Ben ru he gou du Zhong Guo shu bao]? <lb/>[Nan Fang Dou Shi Bao, Yue Du Zhou <lb/>Kan], p. 7. (in Chinese)】 <lb/>Goldstein, P., &amp; Straus, J. (Eds.). (2009). <lb/>Intellectual property in Asia: Law, <lb/>history and politics. Berlin, <lb/>Springer-Verlag. <lb/>H. (1963). Review of the book The <lb/>Chinese Classics, by J. Legge. The <lb/>Journal of Asian Studies, 22(2), 202-204. <lb/>doi: 10.2307/2050015 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>76 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">圖書資訊學刊 第15卷 第1期 (2017.6) <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>2017/2/17 接受日期Accepted: 2017/4/25) <lb/>Wilhelm, H . 1 9 4 2 ) . A s e l e c t e d l i s t o f <lb/>Sinological books published in China <lb/>since 1938. Monumenta Serica, 7(1/2), <lb/>92-174. <lb/>Wilhelm, H. (1943). list of Sinological <lb/>books published in China since 1938. <lb/>Monumenta Serica, 8, 336-393. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
