<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="711-1460-1-PB" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			<idno>DOI: 10.6245/JLIS.2017.432/711</idno>
			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>開放取用教科書現況發展分析 </titlePart>
			</docTitle>
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>陳亞寧</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			<byline>
				<affiliation>淡江大學資訊與圖書館學系</affiliation>
			</byline>
			副教授
			<lb />
			E-mail:
			<email>arthur9861@gmail.com</email>
			關鍵詞：
			<keyword>開放取用；開放取用型教科書；開放型教科書；教科書 </keyword>
			【摘要】
			<div type="abstract">
				隨著開放教育資源的應用發展，減緩了電子教育資源因價格昂貴而無法取得的問題，類似的
				<lb />
				議題亦發生在教育界的教科書方面。近年來，導入開放取用(Open Access, OA)模式至教科書
				<lb />
				已隱然成為一項研究議題。本文採取系統性評閱(Systematic Review, SR)為研究方法，選取
				<lb />
				23 個個案及其相關灰色文獻為研究對象，試從內容提供者、聯合目錄平臺、授權方式、使用方式、
				<lb />
				提供模式、檔案格式、品質審查、營運模式，探討開放取用教科書 (Open Access Textbook, OAT)
				<lb />
				相關議題(如聯合目錄平臺、內容客製化、永續經營與數位保存)，希冀對圖書資訊界的電子資 源資訊服務有所助益。
				<lb />
			</div>
			Open Access Textbooks
			<lb />
			Ya-Ning Chen
			<lb />
			Associate Professor,
	
	Department of Information and Library Science,
			<lb />
			Tamkang University,
	

	Taiwan

	(R.O.C.)
			<lb />
			E-mail:
	arthur9861@gmail.com
			<lb />
			Keywords:
	Open Access; Open Access Textbooks; Open Textbooks; Textbooks 【Abstract】
			<lb />
			With the application and development of open educational resources, the skyrocketing price of
			<lb />
			educational resources that hinders the users to easily access educational materials has been alleviated.
			<lb />
			Student textbooks face similar challenges, and educators and teachers have taken the open access
			<lb />
			approach to provide open access textbooks (OAT). This study aimed to provide an overview analysis of
			<lb />
			the current development of open access textbooks. Twenty-three use cases of open access textbooks
			<lb />
			were selected for systematic review. The investigated items regarding the issues about OAT include:
			<lb />
			source of provision, bibliographic identification, use license, mode of use, mode of provision, file
			<lb />
			format, quality review, and business model. Implications for libraries as a collection policy are
			<lb />
			discussed.
			<lb />
			【Long Abstract】
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>