<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<page>67 <lb/></page>

			<front>圖書資訊學研究 9：2 (June 2015)：67-109 <lb/></front>

			<front>投稿日期：2015 年 5 月 日；接受日期：2015 年 6 月 15 日 <lb/>Email: 林菁 lingin@mail.ncyu.edu.tw；陳耀輝 ychen@mail.ncyu.edu.tw <lb/>Ꮠ͜‫ن‬ᙄኬΣʘઞӺόኪ୦‫‬ <lb/>༟ৃ९ቮሙj <lb/>ቮʃʞϋॴኪ͛ᙄሞঐɢ <lb/>Argument-Driven Inquiry in Fifth-Grade Information <lb/>Literacy Instruction: A Way to Cultivate Students&apos; <lb/>Argument Skills <lb/>林菁 <lb/>Lin-Ching Chen <lb/>ͭྗ່ɽኪᅰЗኪ୦ணࠇၾ၍ଣӻબ <lb/>Professor <lb/>Department of E-learning Design &amp; Management <lb/>National Chiayi University <lb/>陳耀輝 <lb/>Yaw-Huei Chen <lb/>ͭྗ່ɽኪ༟ৃʈӻਓબ <lb/>Associate Professor <lb/>Department of Computer Science &amp; Information Engineering <lb/>National Chiayi University <lb/>ࠅ Abstract <lb/>本研究旨在應用爭議導向探究於資訊素養課程中，以檢視 <lb/>國小五年級學生議論能力的表現。研究現場是一個國小五年級班 <lb/>級，共 30 位學生。探究主題是古今中外的爭議性人物，由資訊 <lb/></front>

			<page>68 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">圖書資訊學研究 9：2 (June 2015) <lb/></note>

			<front>素養老師和班級級任老師協同教學。研究時間為 17 週，主要利 <lb/>用每週一節的資訊素養課程，再輔以十節國語課程。本研究以參 <lb/>與觀察、訪談、測驗和資料分析的方法來蒐集質化和量化資料。 <lb/>研究結果顯示在國小五年級資訊素養課程中應用爭議性人物主題 <lb/>探究，來培養學生議論能力是一可行的方案。學生整體議論能力 <lb/>有顯著進步，他們瞭解議論文的目的和基本元素。半數學生在議 <lb/>論文實際寫作表現優異，能撰寫具有觀點的爭議性人物議論文 <lb/>章。在口頭發表方面，十組學生中有五組可邏輯性的報告小組觀 <lb/>點，三組清楚說出小組論點，但論證較不足，另二組則論點和論 <lb/>證均弱。最後二位老師建議在資訊素養課程中設計循序漸進爭議 <lb/>導向的探究學習任務，以有系統的提升學生議論能力。 <lb/>The purpose of this study was to investigate the effects of <lb/>argument-driven inquiry information literacy instruction on fifth-<lb/>graders&apos; argumentative learning. It was conducted in an elementary <lb/>school and lasted for seventeen weeks. The research site was a fifth-<lb/>grade classroom and the information literacy instruction was taught <lb/>a period of time per week by a teacher librarian, who collaborated <lb/>with a classroom teacher. The classroom teacher taught the basics of <lb/>argumentive texts in Chinese course. They designed an inquiry project, <lb/>titled &quot;Controversial Persons Inquiry&quot; in the information literacy <lb/>and the Chinese course to cultivate students&apos; argument reasoning. <lb/>Research data collected included interviews, participant observations, <lb/>tests, and document analysis. The results showed that using argument-<lb/>driven inquiry in fifth-grade information literacy curriculum was an <lb/>effective project for cultivating students&apos; argument skills. Their overall <lb/>argument performance was improved significantly. They understood <lb/>the purposes and basics of argument writings. Half of students <lb/>performed well in argument writings with insightful claims about the <lb/>controversial figures inquired. In the aspect of speaking, among ten <lb/>groups, five groups presented their findings logically; three groups <lb/>proposed their perspectives clearly, but reasoning was weak. The last <lb/>two groups performed poor in providing claims and warrants. Finally <lb/>teachers suggested that we should systematically design argument-<lb/>driven inquiry projects in information literacy curriculum, so that <lb/>students&apos; argumentative skills can be improved progressively. <lb/></front>

			<page>69 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">林菁、陳耀輝：應用爭議導向之探究式學習於資訊素養課程： <lb/>培養國小五年級學生議論能力 <lb/></note>

			<front>ᗫᒟο Keywords <lb/>議論能力；爭議導向；資訊素養 <lb/>Argumentative skills; Argument-driven; Information literacy </front>
			
			<body>ఠeၫሞ <lb/>書本、期刊、報紙，和政府及機構的網站等，歷來都是我們獲取 <lb/>資訊的主要來源。然而，隨著社群概念和數位科技的蓬勃發展，無論 <lb/>Facebook、Youtube、Line，甚或智慧型手機和穿戴式行動載具等軟硬體， <lb/>逐漸取而代之，成為我們現今取得資訊的另類管道。然而，這些似是 <lb/>而非的資訊常讓我們墜入五里霧中，無法判斷其真偽；尤其當這些資 <lb/>訊牽涉爭議性議題時，大家更可能陷入各執一辭，或人云亦云的窘境， <lb/>既提不出清楚的論點和論證，也無法做出適當的決定。因此，如何培 <lb/>養學生具備理性批判、合理論證和明智抉擇的能力，成為現今教育領 <lb/>域的重要課題之一(National Research Council, 2012; Manson &amp; Scirica, <lb/>2006; Newell, Beach, Smith, &amp; VanDerHeide, 2011)。 <lb/>許多學者指岀這種說理的能力是生活在民主社會中，每位公民都 <lb/>須具備的素養，因為每天的生活中，我們都會遭遇許多爭議性議題， <lb/>需要學生使用合理論證的能力，表達自己的主張(Flower, 2008; Larson <lb/>&amp; Keiper, 2011; Newell et al., 2011)。Hillocks(2011)更強調這種以理 <lb/>服人和批判思考的能力不是吵架，也不是如商業廣告只想推銷產品， <lb/>而是無論升學和就業都須具備的關鍵能力。因此，學者專家建議學校 <lb/>應及早開始教導學生這種思辨力，並最好能建構一個爭議性議題的探 <lb/>究學習情境，來培養學生的議論能力(Hillocks, 2011; Kuhn, 2008)。 <lb/>然而，我國學校的教學現場卻鮮少實踐此種教學策略，尤其是在 <lb/>國小階段，不僅教科書中議論文體的篇幅偏少，課堂上正式的論證教 <lb/>學更是付之闕如(李琬蓉，2009；張緯文、林樹聲，2014)。鑑此， <lb/>本研究旨在探討於國小五年級資訊素養課程中，應用爭議性人物主題 <lb/>探究，來培養學生議論能力的可行性。統整而言，本研究的目的包括 <lb/>以下三項： <lb/>( 一 ) 探討在此資訊素養課程中學生整體議論能力的表現。 <lb/>( 二 ) 探討在此資訊素養課程中學生在爭議性議題寫作的表現。 <lb/>( 三 ) 探討在此資訊素養課程中學生在爭議性議題口頭發表的表現。 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">圖書資訊學研究 9：2 (June 2015) <lb/></note>

			<body>൩e˖ᘠઞী <lb/>ɓe‫ن‬ᙄ‫‬ᙄᕚኪ୦ٙࠠࠅ <lb/>民主社會是一個透過人民相互尊重、溝通和包容，以形成共識和 <lb/>決策的理性社會。但近來爭議性議題所衍生的激烈抗爭活動，卻在世 <lb/>界各民主國家層出不窮。例如臺灣的國道收費員抗爭事件、美國的白 <lb/>人警察槍殺黑人事件、希臘的反緊縮政策等，在在說明了理性溝通之 <lb/>不易，但如此激進的抗爭活動終究不是民主社會解決爭端的良策。事 <lb/>實上，學者指出面對生活中有關社會、經濟、政治等爭議性議題最佳 <lb/>的策略是先釐清自己的觀念，再靈活掌握論點、論據和論證，有條理 <lb/>的論述自己的主張，說服對方，同時也適度考量對方的觀點，以達到 <lb/>相互溝通的目的(Hillocks, 2010, 2011; Larson &amp; Keiper, 2011)。 <lb/>爭議性議題的論述就是議論文(argumentative texts)，它主要包 <lb/>含三個基本元素(李琬蓉，2009；Gunning, 2012; Hillocks, 2010, 2011; <lb/>Mason &amp; Scirica, 2006; State of Delaware, 2013)： <lb/>( 一 ) 論點(claim)：作者對於議題所提出的主要觀點和主張，能讓人 <lb/>信服的論點需要立場清楚且有見地。 <lb/>( 二 ) 論據(evidence)：作者對於支持的論點所提出的證據，可分為事 <lb/>實證據和意見證據，前者指已客觀存在的資料，如數據、圖表、 <lb/>研究結果等；後者則是相關的人或團體所發表的主觀看法，如名 <lb/>言、諺語、專家的意見等。無論是何種證據，它都要與議題相關， <lb/>且是充分、正確和信實的。 <lb/>( 三 ) 論證(warrant, reasons)：將論據做進一步合理且正確的推論，以 <lb/>支持作者的論點。論證的方法有歸納、演繹、因果關係、類比、 <lb/>引用權威等。 <lb/>因此，相較於故事和記敘文文體，議論文的結構較複雜多變且是 <lb/>非線性，再加上我國遲至國小高年級才開始正式接觸它，故學生對於 <lb/>議論文的閱讀和寫作方式均感陌生。楊裕貿(2013)觀察國語日報 <lb/>2012 年 8 月至 2013 年 7 月的投稿寫作體材，發現多是記敘文，偶爾 <lb/>才有以議論文為寫作形式的文章(國語日報 2013/10/30，第 9 版)。 <lb/>然而，研究指出無論是在人文、社會科學和自然科學等領域的學習 <lb/>上，學生經常面對爭議性議題，需要思考有效捍衛自己立場的方法； <lb/>因此，學者多以為學校課程有導入爭議性議題的必要性(Larson &amp; <lb/>Keiper, 2011; Means &amp; Voss, 1996; Sandoval &amp; Millwood, 2005)。此外， <lb/></body>

			<page>71 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">林菁、陳耀輝：應用爭議導向之探究式學習於資訊素養課程： <lb/>培養國小五年級學生議論能力 <lb/></note>

			<body>研究也證實，無論是在國中小或大學階段引進爭議性議題的學習方法， <lb/>讓學生進行分組議題討論，不但可培養其邏輯性，還可提升學生學科 <lb/>知識和概念學習的成效，並強化其學習動機和參與度(引自 Mason &amp; <lb/>Scirica, 2006)。鑑此，美國在 2010 年修訂全國共同核心州課程標準 <lb/>時(Common Core State Standards)，就將爭議性文章讀和寫的能力逐 <lb/>步規劃於幼稚園至 12 年級的英語課程中，並認為這些能力無論對於 <lb/>歷史、社會、科學和技術等學習領域，均是重要的能力指標，可確保 <lb/>學生做好升學和就業的準備(Council of Chief State School &amp; National <lb/>Governors Association, 2010; Llewellyn, 2013; Newell et al., 2011)。 <lb/>另一方面，許多研究卻發現現今的學生不但缺乏說理的能力，甚 <lb/>至連分辨資訊可信度的批判閱讀(critical reading)能力亦不足。例如， <lb/>由美國 Harrison Group(2010)針對全國 1,045 對中小學學生和家長進 <lb/>行的全國大調查，結果發現有 39% 的 9 至 17 歲學生以為網路上的資 <lb/>訊都不會有錯誤。另一類似的研究也發現只有 4% 的中學生會檢查自 <lb/>己閱讀網路資訊的正確性(New Literacies Research Team, 2006)。因此， <lb/>Gunning(2012)建議要鼓勵學生進行批判閱讀，老師應該建構一個爭 <lb/>議性議題的探究學習情境，教導學生批判的能力，以幫助他們考慮多 <lb/>元的論點，不會非理性的驟下判斷。Gunning 更列出多項學生須具備 <lb/>的批判閱讀能力，包括分辨事實和意見的不同、查證事實的真偽、找 <lb/>出文章中的偏見、歸納合理的結論、判斷資訊的來源等，以為如此才 <lb/>是具備議論文讀寫的基本能力，可以成為民主社會的公民。 <lb/>Sandoval 與 Millwood(2005)指出許多高中生雖然知道要舉出證 <lb/>據來支持自己的論點，但他們常只引註一方的論據，甚至未覺察這些 <lb/>證據與自己的觀點有所牴觸。Hillocks(2010)也發現美國國中和高中 <lb/>教科書，約 1,000 頁中只有 45 頁是說服性文章，議論性文章也只佔 1.5 <lb/>頁。這些教科書不但未強調事實和意見論述的不同，也未教導學生面 <lb/>對爭議性和弱結構問題時，應如何做出邏輯性的推論。我國教科書的 <lb/>情況亦類似，根據梁崇輝(2004)對於國小高年級國語教科書版本議 <lb/>論文數量的調查，結果發現議論文只占全部課文的 9%，平均五和六年 <lb/>級每學期都只有一至兩篇議論文。因此，不分中外，學者專家均呼籲 <lb/>教育界應更重視爭議性議題的教學，因為它是批判思考的核心，更是 <lb/>學生進入高等教育念書和職場工作的關鍵能力所在(張緯文、林樹聲， <lb/>2014；Hillocks, 2010)。 <lb/></body>

			<page>72 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">圖書資訊學研究 9：2 (June 2015) <lb/></note>

			<body>ɚe‫ن‬ᙄ‫‬ᙄᕚٙኪ <lb/>研究指出教導爭議性議題的瓶頸主要有二項(Hillocks, 2011; Kuhn, <lb/>2005; Mason &amp; Scirica, 2006; Newell et al., 2011)。首先是師生對於爭議 <lb/>性文章缺少完整的概念。就如上述，由於語文教科書中屬於議論文的 <lb/>文章較少，使得大部份學生不熟悉此種文體，甚至老師也無法有效的 <lb/>拿捏議論文的教學技巧，常主導教室裡的討論，未給予學生充分討論 <lb/>和建構議論內容的機會。教導爭議性議題遭遇的第二個瓶頸是縱使學 <lb/>生在課程中有練習議論技巧的寫作作業，但寫作對象(audience)多是 <lb/>老師本身，而非真實事件中需要被說服的人物。學生因此意興闌珊， <lb/>草草完成作業，未努力表達出自己的觀點。 <lb/>有鑑於以上的教學瓶頸，學者專家從不同層面提出許多教學策 <lb/>略，以提升學生的議論技巧。從認知過程層面來說，學者發現提供學 <lb/>生更明確的學習目的和寫作對象，可激勵四年級至八年級學生考慮不 <lb/>同意見者的論點，以寫出高品質的議論性文章，也更願意修正議論作 <lb/>品 中 有 瑕 疵 處(Ferretti, MacArthur, &amp; Dowdy, 2000; Midgette, Haria, &amp; <lb/>MacArthur, 2008)。另外，研究證實議論性文章的寫作教學要搭配閱 <lb/>讀教學才較有成效，教學內容可包括分析議論文章的正面和反面觀 <lb/>點，以及論點和論證間連結的合理性等。如此的讀寫整合，不但可建 <lb/>立學生的議論文基模(schema)，提高議論文的寫作品質，更可改變 <lb/>他們既有的偏見，願意客觀引用不同觀點的證據(Kuhn &amp; Udell, 2004; <lb/>Wolfe, Britt, &amp; Butler, 2009)。此外，鼓勵學生分組理性討論、老師提 <lb/>供回饋、以文章大綱作鷹架，以及在議論過程善用資訊工具等策略， <lb/>均是在認知過程層面可採行的議論文教學策略(Newell et al., 2011)。 <lb/>許佩琦(2001)的研究則發現學生對爭議性議題瞭解的高低，會影響 <lb/>其對於此議題相關文章內容的理解；因此建議老師最好能標示清楚文 <lb/>章內容的正反立場，才能提升低先備知識學生的理解能力。另外，李 <lb/>琬蓉(2009)根據 Piaget 的認知發展理論，建議國小高年級學生因剛 <lb/>進入形式運思期，可先從二元邏輯的思索方向教導他們論證能力，之 <lb/>後再擴充為多元面向。 <lb/>除了認知層面的教學策略外，Newell 等人(2011)還建議採用社 <lb/>會行動觀點的教學策略，以達到學生在真實情境中活用議論技巧的目 <lb/>的。這些教學策略包括：(一)設計有溝通對象的學習情境(如國際 <lb/>友伴、同儕、家人等)，這樣不但可提高學生使用議論技巧的動機， <lb/>願意主動練習和參與討論，更可培養他們的公民素養，成為負責任的 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">林菁、陳耀輝：應用爭議導向之探究式學習於資訊素養課程： <lb/>培養國小五年級學生議論能力 <lb/></note>

			<body>好公民(Crisco, 2009; Flower, 2008; Ward, 2009)；(二)鼓勵學生從對 <lb/>方的立場來思考，多進行雙方開放性的溝通和對話，以找出理性解決 <lb/>爭端的方法(Felton &amp; Herko, 2004)；(三)使用照片、影片、聲音 <lb/>等多媒體資源，來增加議論的多元性和說服性(Bruce, 2009)。此外， <lb/>Kuhn(2008)和 Llewellyn(2013)更建議可建構一個爭議性議題的探 <lb/>究學習情境，以統整上述的教學策略於一個有意義的環境中，培養有 <lb/>思考力的學習者。 <lb/>ɧe‫ن‬ᙄኬΣʘઞӺόኪ୦ <lb/>爭議性議題和探究式學習是現今教育趨勢一體的兩面，二者均強 <lb/>調學生要具備主動學習、批判思考、問題解決、邏輯推理及明智判斷 <lb/>等能力。因此，Kuhn(2008)以為單純的知識追求不是教育的最終 <lb/>目的，惟有同時具備探究和議論的高層次思考能力才是化解爭端和解 <lb/>決問題的不二法門；而且此二者最好能以統整的方式跨越橫向學科領 <lb/>域，及縱向年齡層來教學。Hillocks(2010)也強調議論與探究式學習 <lb/>的過程類似，均是從定義問題和檢視資料開始，再藉由多元的證據支 <lb/>持，以形成論點並解決問題。美國國家研究委員會(National Research <lb/>Council)也建議在科學實驗中設計爭議導向的探究學習活動，如此不 <lb/>但可發展學生科學思考的習慣和興趣，也可提升他們閱讀、寫作和口 <lb/>說的能力(Sampson, Grooms, &amp; Walker, 2009)。 <lb/>除 了 科 學 領 域 的 課 程 外， 資 訊 素 養 課 程(information literacy <lb/>curriculum)也著重提問、搜尋資訊、批判思考、問題解決和明智判斷 <lb/>等能力的培養，近來它更成為世界各國在不同學習階段積極推動的課 <lb/>程 之 一(Fulton, 2010; Hepworth &amp; Walton, 2009; Kurbanoglu, Grassian, <lb/>Mizrachi, Catts, &amp; Spiranec, 2013)。學者指出資訊素養一詞的本質不只 <lb/>是資訊科技的使用能力，還包含批判思考、問題解決和社會文化影響 <lb/>等相關議題(AASL, 2009; Bruce, 2008)。因此，若從資訊素養的過程 <lb/>(process)層面來考量，資訊素養就是探究式學習，指一個人能有效 <lb/>的尋找、取得、組織、評估、利用和創造各種資訊的能力和態度(林菁、 <lb/>謝欣穎、謝文峰，2014；AASL, 2009)。在此探究的過程中，學生提 <lb/>出自己有興趣探究的主題或問題，再取得相關資訊，並分析統整它們， <lb/>以獲得最終的解答。 <lb/>學者指出資訊素養不能另成一個單獨領域教學，應要藉由探究 <lb/>式 學 習 的 架 構， 適 時 融 入 不 同 學 習 領 域 中， 才 較 有 成 效( 林 菁， <lb/>2011；Chu, Tse, 2011; Kuhlthau, Maniotes, &amp; Caspari, 2007)。Eisenberg <lb/></body>

			<page>74 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">圖書資訊學研究 9：2 (June 2015) <lb/></note>

			<body>與 Robinson(2007) 以 及 Eisenberg 與 Berkowitz(1999) 即 建 議 可 以 <lb/>Super3 和 Big6 模式，將資訊素養融入不同學習領域中。許多研究也發 <lb/>現此探究式學習架構不但淺顯易懂，且已廣為全世界的幼稚園至高中， <lb/>甚至大學生使用，成效不錯(林菁、顏仁德、黃財尉，2014；Chu, Tse, <lb/>Loh, &amp; Chow, 2011; Santana Arroyo, 2013)。然而，雖然這些融入課程 <lb/>琳瑯滿目，包括自然、社會、健康等領域，但均較少涉及爭議性議題。 <lb/>因此，將爭議導向之探究式學習藉由資訊素養課程和 Big6 模式來教學， <lb/>以培養學生的議論能力，是一值得研究的方向。 <lb/>ਞeӺ˙‫ج‬ <lb/>ɓeӺணࠇ <lb/>本 研 究 採 個 案 研 究 法( 林 佩 璇，2000；Merriam, 1998; Springer, <lb/>2010)，以一群在資訊素養課程中應用爭議導向探究學習的師生為研 <lb/>究對象，檢視學生在「爭議性人物」主題探究的議論能力表現。個案 <lb/>研究法旨在探討與分析一個個案在特定情境脈絡下的活動情形，以深 <lb/>入瞭解其獨特性。 <lb/>ɚeӺତఙၾΥЪϼࢪ <lb/>本研究現場是嘉義地區小小國小(化名)的五年甲班，全班有 30 <lb/>位學生(男女生各 15 人)。研究者自 2005 年起即與這所國小合作， <lb/>共同設計資訊素養課程綱要；自 2009 年起更與該校資訊素養團隊合作， <lb/>自一年級開始，逐年研發資訊素養相關教材。研究對象自 98 學年度以 <lb/>一年級身份進入該校後，每週均有一至兩節的資訊素養課程 ，學習資 <lb/>訊素養涵蓋的各項概念和技巧，並活用這些技巧於每學期的學習任務 <lb/>中；「爭議性人物」是研究對象學習的第八個學習任務，之前的任務 <lb/>包括一下的校園生物大搜索、二上的社區巡禮、三上的樹朋友、四上 <lb/>的班級水族箱等，均採用 Super3 和 Big6 模式來進行探究(限於篇幅， <lb/>細節請參見林菁等人，2014)。因此，學生均熟悉 Super3 和 Big6 模式 <lb/>1 資訊素養課程在低年級為每週一節；中年級加入電腦課程，由一位資訊素養 <lb/>老師教導，故為每週兩節；高年級資訊素養課程由資訊素養老師教學，但電 <lb/>腦課程由資訊組長教學，他另有自己的進度和教學內容，故資訊素養課程每 <lb/>週為一節。 <lb/></body>

			<page>75 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">林菁、陳耀輝：應用爭議導向之探究式學習於資訊素養課程： <lb/>培養國小五年級學生議論能力 <lb/></note>

			<body>的探究過程和技巧，如使用概念圖定義問題、利用書碼找尋書籍、關 <lb/>鍵字查詢網路等。但協同教學的級任林老師指出學生對於議論文較不 <lb/>熟悉：「ʞϋॴٙኪ͛࿁‫ޟ‬ჿ݊ᙄሞ˖Չྼ݊ϺdΪ <lb/>‫̬މ‬ϋॴഐҼʘ‫ۃ‬d˼ࡁ‫ה‬༾ཀٙ˖͉˖ே݊াા˖e Ꮠ͜˖ <lb/>ձˇᅰٙႭ‫˖‬d‫˸ה‬࿁ᙄሞ˖݊ࠤ͛ٙ」(級任林師省文)。 <lb/>教導資訊素養的張老師投入資訊素養課程教學多年，重視學生活 <lb/>用資訊素養來解決生活上問題的能力，並樂意與其他相關授課老師溝 <lb/>通和協同，以為協同合作可以彼此互補，讓大家的優勢均得以發揮(張 <lb/>師訪 20130909)。在本研究中，張老師主要負責「爭議性人物」主題 <lb/>探究課程整體的規劃與教學。五年甲班的級任林老師是張老師的協同 <lb/>教學老師，負責教導議論文的讀和寫，並批改學生最後撰寫的議論文 <lb/>作品。他就讀於課程與教學研究所，研究方向是閱讀理解策略。他經 <lb/>常在國語課程中教導學生預測、比較、六何、摘要、提問、文章結構、 <lb/>理解監控等閱讀策略(林師訪 20130905)。研究過程中，兩位老師每 <lb/>週利用一節空堂討論教學進度和學生表現，以及時修正接下來的教學 <lb/>內容。 <lb/>ɧeኪʫணࠇ <lb/>本研究以「爭議性人物」為資訊素養課程的探索主題，統整國小 <lb/>五年級議論文的閱讀與寫作。整個教學內容設計依照 Big6 模式的六個 <lb/>步驟反覆進行。全班學生自由分組，三人一組共有十組。 <lb/>由於「繞道而行」是五年級上學期國語課本(康軒版)首次導入 <lb/>的議論文，學生對其文章結構仍不瞭解，而國語課本第一課「名人記 <lb/>趣」是篇學生熟悉的記敘文，介紹三位名人的機智表現。故張老師 <lb/>和林老師在暑假期間經過多次討論後，決定藉此課文，引導學生思 <lb/>考是否每位名人都只有正面評價？是否有些名人可能具有爭議性， <lb/>例如當時極具爭議性的美國國安局包商雇員 Edward Snowden(討論 <lb/>20130807、20130815、20130819、 20130821)。 <lb/>當學生初步瞭解「爭議」一詞的意義後，課程正式進入 Big6 模式 <lb/>的「定義問題」階段，即學生要合理的將問題的焦點和範圍定義出來， <lb/>以確定解決此問題所需要資訊的方向。張老師先請各組學生討論想要 <lb/>探究的爭議性人物為誰。由於每週只有一節課，為節省時間，張老師 <lb/>事先蒐集許多爭議性人物的書面和影音資料。結果十組挑選的爭議性 <lb/>人物多來自老師的名單，如秦始皇(三組)、曹操(二組)、伽利略(二 <lb/>組)、甘地(一組)和愛因斯坦(一組)等人，只有探究王金平的組 <lb/></body>

			<page>76 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">圖書資訊學研究 9：2 (June 2015) <lb/></note>

			<body>別是自己挑選人選。決定探究的人物後，學生繪製概念圖，以決定要 <lb/>探索的方向。由於五年級學生已熟悉 Big6 模式的「尋找策略」和「取 <lb/>得資訊」之技巧，張老師乃將主要心力投入在 Big6 模式的「使用資訊」 <lb/>階段，即學生要根據獲得資訊的類型，有效能的從中萃取出重要的資 <lb/>訊。因此，張老師不斷引導學生有目的摘錄重點，包括爭議性人物生 <lb/>平、事件、正反面觀點等，以及重新檢視概念圖的合理性。林老師也 <lb/>適時利用七節國語課時間，協同教導議論文的結構、基本三元素，以 <lb/>及閱讀理解策略。他更特別加強學生提出推論性和評論性問題的能力， <lb/>因為如此他們才會整理文章的內容和腦中的思緒(討論 20131108)。 <lb/>林老師要求學生預習每課國語課文後，提出三個問題，問題性質最好 <lb/>是要經過思考和推理才能找到答案的「推論性問題」，以及以自己的 <lb/>知識、想法和評論回答的「評論性問題」。例如預習完「繞道而行」 <lb/>那篇議論文課文，S16 提出事實性的問題「課文中作者提到的昆蟲是 <lb/>甚麼？」就遭到林老師提醒「請提升問題的層次」；而 S23 提出推論 <lb/>性問題「為什麼文中的蜻蜓一直無法從房間裡飛出去？」，S26 提出 <lb/>評論性問題「『百折不撓』和『隨機應變』哪個比較好？」就獲得老 <lb/>師的讚許(S16、S23、S26 作業簿)。 <lb/>學生摘錄完不同資料的重點後，進入 Big6 模式的「統整」階段， <lb/>即要整合各類資訊，以達到資訊的需求，並選用適當的媒體將統整的 <lb/>資訊發表出來。各組學生利用概念圖統整爭議性人物的資料和自己的 <lb/>意見，再以 PowerPoint 軟體進行口頭報告；報告完，同儕即時提問並 <lb/>相互評論；之後，每位學生利用二節國語課程撰寫一篇爭議性人物探 <lb/>究的議論文。最後每位學生填寫「我的回顧與省思」學習單，挑選出 <lb/>整個學習過程中最有趣和最困難的事情，並寫下原因；這是 Big6 模式 <lb/>的「評估」階段，即學生能判斷整個研究結果是否已有效的解決了探 <lb/>究的問題，並且自我反省整個過程所花費的時間和精力是否有效率， <lb/>以及是否擁有成就感。在此兩個階段中，兩位老師共同引導學生思考 <lb/>如何做出最佳的口頭報告和議論文寫作，如張老師教導學生規劃簡報 <lb/>內容的 666 原則(每張 PPT 不超過六個項目編號、每個編號不超過六 <lb/>個字、不連續六張 PPT 都有六個項目)，以及議論文的四段內容(第 <lb/>一段生平、第二段事件、第三段正負面評價、第四段自己的看法)； <lb/>林老師教導議論文寫作規範(包含論點、論據和論證、用詞客觀、合 <lb/>乎邏輯、適合的標題等)，並提供學生爭議性文章寫作規準，鼓勵學 <lb/>生寫出高品質的議論文作品；撰寫完後，林老師還利用一節課請學生 <lb/>根據寫作規準，給予彼此有建設性的意見。 <lb/></body>

			<page>77 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">林菁、陳耀輝：應用爭議導向之探究式學習於資訊素養課程： <lb/>培養國小五年級學生議論能力 <lb/></note>

			<body>限於篇幅，完整的爭議性人物教學設計請參見研究者建置的「資 <lb/>訊素養教學資源平臺」中教學資源檔案庫的五年級(http://ilr.etech. <lb/>ncyu.edu.tw)。 <lb/>̬eӺʈՈ <lb/>(一)語文大考驗 <lb/>此測驗主在檢驗學生整體的議論能力，包括議論文的基本元素及 <lb/>閱讀和寫作等。由研究者與資訊素養老師參考語文學習領域能力指標 <lb/>共同編撰測驗題目，再經由兩位五年級級任老師審查內容。此測驗總 <lb/>共有 13 題，包括七題選擇題和六題開放式問題。選擇題每題一分， <lb/>開放式問題則每題 0 至 5 分，根據規準來評量。整份試題最高總分是 <lb/>29 分，內部一致性 α 係數考驗得出 Cronbach α=0.71，難度為 0.57 <lb/>(區間是 0.19~0.87)，鑑別度為 0.44(0.30~0.69)，評分者信度是 <lb/>0.72。 <lb/>( 二 ) 爭議性文章寫作規準 <lb/>由於議論文寫作無對錯之別，只有好壞程度之分，故以規準作為 <lb/>評量的方法。研究者提供許多相關規準與兩位老師討論多次(討論 <lb/>20131101、20131104)，之後共同研擬出爭議性文章寫作規準。它包 <lb/>括六個向度(論據、論據、論證、組織、句型和用語)，及其下的三 <lb/>個等級(1 加油、3 不錯、5 很棒)。議論文基本分數為 70 分，若六 <lb/>個向度均獲得五分，可達滿分 100 分。 <lb/>ʞe༟ࣘႎණ <lb/>本研究蒐集資料的方法包括以下四種： <lb/>(一)參與觀察 <lb/>研究者參與觀察每週課程，觀察師生的教與學活動(例如老師引 <lb/>導學生認識爭議性人物的過程、學生對於爭議一詞瞭解的表現等)， <lb/>也會協助老師蒐集相關教材、設計規準等。每週觀察時，研究者於札 <lb/>記中記錄經驗的事物和問題，以於課後與老師深入討論，並利用攝影 <lb/>機和照相機拍下教學現場的實況，以作為日後資料分析之用。 <lb/>(二)訪談 <lb/>研究者於課後常與老師和學生就教學內容，進行開放式的非正式 <lb/></body>

			<page>78 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">圖書資訊學研究 9：2 (June 2015) <lb/></note>

			<body>訪談。於期末，研究者擬定特定問題與學生和兩位老師進行一次正式 <lb/>訪談；正式訪談的學生由兩位老師挑選，包含低、中和高學業程度及 <lb/>男女性別各一名，共六位。師生正式訪談的題目見附錄一。 <lb/>(三)測驗 <lb/>本研究採用的測驗是「語文大考驗」，作為檢驗學生整體議論能 <lb/>力之用。 <lb/>(四)文件分析 <lb/>本研究蒐集的相關文件包括老師撰寫的反思文章、學校國語定期 <lb/>評量考卷、學生議論文作文等。 <lb/>ʬe༟ࣘஈଣ <lb/>在質化資料方面，研究者將所有訪談錄音謄錄成文稿，再將其它 <lb/>蒐集的資料依資料類型分類(見表 1)。之後研究者反覆閱讀它們，作 <lb/>交叉比對，以減少研究者的偏見，真正瞭解所有參與者的真實感受和 <lb/>學習表現；再將概念性質類似的資料彙整，形成主題和類別，並比較 <lb/>和驗證資料的可用性，以獲得合理的解釋。量化的測驗資料則以 SPSS <lb/>軟體進行相依樣本 t 檢定統計分析。 <lb/>‫ڌ‬ 1 <lb/>ࡡ༟ࣘʱᗳ‫ڌ‬ <lb/>༟ࣘʱᗳ <lb/>˾‫ٙڌ‬จ່ <lb/>級任林師省文 <lb/>級任林老師於課程結束後撰寫的反省文章 <lb/>林師訪 20130905 <lb/>級任林老師於 2013 年 9 月 5 日接受訪談 <lb/>S16 作業簿 <lb/>編號 16 號學生作業簿資料 <lb/>期末 S10 <lb/>編號 10 號學生回答學校期末國語科測驗的內容 <lb/>語大 S2 <lb/>編號 2 號學生回答語文大考驗的內容 <lb/>S3 訪 20140114 <lb/>編號 3 號學生於 2014 年 1 月 14 日接受訪談 <lb/>S20 反省文 <lb/>編號 20 號學生撰寫的議論文寫作反省短文 <lb/>研札 20131113 <lb/>研究者於 2013 年 11 月 13 日撰寫的觀察札記 <lb/>S23 議論文 <lb/>編號 23 號學生撰寫的議論文 <lb/>G9 簡報 20131213 <lb/>第九組於 2013 年 12 月 13 日口頭報告的轉譯內容 <lb/>S17 問 <lb/>編號 17 號學生於同儕報告時提出的問題 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">林菁、陳耀輝：應用爭議導向之探究式學習於資訊素養課程： <lb/>培養國小五年級學生議論能力 <lb/></note>

			<body>資素＆級任老師訪 <lb/>20140122 <lb/>資訊素養張老師和級任林老師於 2014 年 1 月 22 日接 <lb/>受訪談 <lb/>S13 課本 <lb/>編號 13 號學生課本資料 <lb/>討論 20130913 <lb/>張老師、林老師與研究者於 2013 年 月 13 日討論課 <lb/>程的教學設計 <lb/>ໍeӺഐ؈ၾীሞ <lb/>ɓeኪ͛ᙄሞঐɢٙ‫ڌ‬ତ <lb/>在研究的第一週，張老師以當時頗具爭議話題的美國國安局包商 <lb/>雇員 Edward Snowden 事件為例，教導學生爭議的概念。他請學生分別 <lb/>就美國人和臺灣人兩個立場，來評價 Snowden 是英雄還是罪犯(研札 <lb/>及錄影資料 20130906)。根據學生自由舉手投票情形，結果無分軒輊， <lb/>他們都覺得 Snowden 是英雄(分別是 11 票和 12 票)，只有少數人覺 <lb/>得他是罪犯(分別是 4 票和 1 票)。張老師在課後訪談中表示，他原 <lb/>先以為扮演美國人的學生多數會投票給「罪犯」，扮演臺灣人的學生 <lb/>則不一定；但結果雙方沒有很大差異，表示學生對於以不同立場來審 <lb/>視一件事情仍不甚瞭解(研札 20130906)。例如 S13 在爭議性人物介 <lb/>紹學習單的「你覺得 Snowden 是英雄還是罪犯？為什麼？對你來說， <lb/>『爭議』是甚麼意思？」問題上，以臺灣人的立場寫出：「Ϊ‫ߠ˼މ‬ <lb/>Іʉٙd݊౧।٫d݊ࡈගፒf‫ن‬ᙄ݊ϞՇԫઋৎəላ߉d <lb/>ϞɛႭவࡈdϞɛႭԟࡈdϞλϞᕸf」(S13 課本)。由此可知， <lb/>學生於研究初期，尚未掌握爭議性議題具多元面向的概念。 <lb/>本研究採用「語文大考驗」來檢驗學生整體議論能力的表現，包 <lb/>括議論文的基本元素和閱讀及寫作等。由於本研究是個案研究，並無 <lb/>控制組的設計，無意將研究結果作過度推論，但根據「語文大考驗」 <lb/>相依樣本 t 檢定結果，測驗的前測與後測達到顯著差異(t=5.855, p= <lb/>.000&lt;0.05)(見表 2)，表示爭議導向探究之資訊素養課程可提升學 <lb/>生整體議論的能力。 <lb/></body>

			<page>80 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">圖書資訊學研究 9：2 (June 2015) <lb/></note>

			<body>‫ڌ‬ 2 <lb/>Ⴇ˖ɽϽԱᅵ͉ t Ꮸ֛ <lb/>Number <lb/>Pretest <lb/>Posttest <lb/>t <lb/>p <lb/>M <lb/>SD <lb/>M <lb/>SD <lb/>30 <lb/>11.77 <lb/>5.097 <lb/>15.77 <lb/>4.360 <lb/>5.855 <lb/>.000 <lb/>α= .05 <lb/>除了整體量化的統計資料外，以下再就「語文大考驗」中個別測 <lb/>驗題目及其他相關質化資料，細部分析學生議論的能力。由於本學期 <lb/>是研究對象首次正式接觸議論文，故將「瞭解議論文的定義和目的」 <lb/>設為重要的學習目標。在「語文大考驗」前測選擇題「撰寫議論文的 <lb/>目的為何？」中，30 位學生中只有 6 人答對；但經過 17 週資訊素養 <lb/>課程後接受後測，有 27 位學生知道議論文撰寫的目的是「提出自己的 <lb/>主張，陳述辯駁意見，以說服別人」。他們大部份已瞭解議論文與其 <lb/>它文體不同之處。 <lb/>此外，論點、論據和論證三個元素也是認識議論文文體特色時， <lb/>學生要學習的新概念。在學校期末國語學習領域的定期評量中有一大題 <lb/>是閱讀測驗，請學生閱讀一篇文章「不裝懂 不怕問」(約 490 字)， <lb/>再判斷它的文體及寫下判斷的理由。結果 30 位學生中，有 20 位正確判 <lb/>斷文體，並寫出合理的理由，如因為有論點、論據、論證(期末 S4、 <lb/>5、22、26、29 等)。其中有四位學生更清楚寫出這篇文章論點、論據 <lb/>和論證各在何處，如 S10 寫道：「ୋɓeɚ‫݊ݬ‬ሞᓃdɧe̬eʞ‫݊ݬ‬ <lb/>ሞኽdʬeɖ‫݊ݬ‬ሞᗇ」(期末 S10)；S23 寫道：「ᙄሞ˖ࠅ̍ўሞ <lb/>ᓃeሞኽeሞᗇfሞᓃjࠅʔࢴɨਪfሞᗇjٝᗆԸІೌٝfሞኽjЪ <lb/>٫ٙፋԒዝf」(期末 S23)。此外，此份定期評量的閱讀測驗另一 <lb/>題是請學生從文章中舉出兩個理由，來支持作者「不恥下問」的論點。 <lb/>結果有 26 位學生能找出兩個理由，如 S29 表示：「1. Ъ٫Ϊ‫މ‬ʔᏑᅰ <lb/>ኪdϾɦӚϞ೯ਪd‫˸ה‬Ͻ༊ఱӚϽλf2. ˬᒱਪəਪᕚdШ˼ٙ <lb/>ਪᕚᜫ˼ϓ‫މ‬ਃɽٙ߅ኪf(期末 S29)；S5 寫到：「1. Ъ٫Ⴍj <lb/>ɓࡈʔ೯ਪٙɛ͑Ⴣ݊ࡈɿf‫ࠅͪڌ‬ε೯ਪf2. Ъ٫Ⴍjʔ <lb/>ࠅ‫‬ਪɓԬਪᕚf‫ͪڌ‬ʔࠅ‫ࢴ‬Ͼʔ೯ਪf」(期末 S5)。 <lb/>然而，學生活用議論文三元素的能力在「語文大考驗」中則表現 <lb/>得不甚理想。測驗第八題請學生活用自己對於論點、論據和論證的瞭 <lb/>解，「寫出一則簡短的正面事例，說明『合作』的重要」。結果學生 <lb/>無論在前測和後測中均只有半數能舉出正面例證，如螞蟻儲存食物、 <lb/>打籃球、搬重物、做海報、做作品等(語大 S2、3、15、16、8、9 等)， <lb/></body>

			<page>81 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">林菁、陳耀輝：應用爭議導向之探究式學習於資訊素養課程： <lb/>培養國小五年級學生議論能力 <lb/></note>

			<body>更只有五位學生清楚說明合作的重要，如「ʃଡ଼ীሞࣛdν؈ঐʱʈ <lb/>ΥЪd‫ึܓ‬һҞdഐ؈ɰึһλd̙ԈΥЪ݊‫ڢ‬੬ࠠࠅٙ」(語大 <lb/>S23)、「ɽඟટɢცኑၳΣːɢdΥЪೌගdʑঐྮԳᐶ」(語大 <lb/>S27)。答題不理想學生的問題是列舉負面事例，如 S12 說：「ν؈͂ <lb/>ᘫଢʔΥЪdІʉ͂Іʉdவࡈྠඟ͑Ⴣʔึ௷л」(語大 S12)；「ν <lb/>؈ӚϞΥЪd‫ܘ‬εԫఱӚ፬‫༺ج‬ϓdˢνΒ୵dν؈ӚϞӊࡈɛɓৎ <lb/>ΥЪd୵ఱʔึਗd‫˸ה‬ΥЪ݊‫ٙࠅࠠܘ‬ԫ」(語大 S29)。因此， <lb/>學生似乎還不瞭解正面和負面事證的區別。 <lb/>除了要舉證適當的論據外，邏輯推理(reasoning)也是議論文學習 <lb/>的重點，意即提出合理的論證過程。「語文大考驗」第六題請學生重 <lb/>組四個句子成為合乎邏輯的一個段落，結果學生答對率從前測的 43% <lb/>(13 人)進步到後測的 73%(22 人)，表示經過資訊素養課程，學生 <lb/>可以將複雜的句子按照轉折語氣，重新排列成為合乎邏輯的段落。「語 <lb/>文大考驗」第十三題請學生閱讀愚公移山和明鑼移山兩篇文章後(約 <lb/>2,180 字)，寫成一篇議論文，包含兩種移山的方法和自己的看法。根 <lb/>據評量規準，滿分為五分(提出論點得一分，列出兩個論據得兩分， <lb/>論證完整且合理得兩分)，學生平均分數為 3.23 分(5 人得 5 分，12 <lb/>人得 4 分，3 人得 3 分，7 人得 2 分，1 人得 1 分，2 人得 0 分)，表 <lb/>現不錯，但仍有近 1/3 學生無法提出論證。得五分者列出愚公與明鑼 <lb/>移山的不同處，並提出自己支持的方法及理由，如： <lb/>遇到困難時，我們應該學會換個方法，因為我們不可能像愚公一 <lb/>樣想剷平一座山，必須繞道而行。我們可以學學明鑼，如果山移不走， <lb/>那我們就移走自己。如果遇到困難，那我們就換個方法解決，雖然愚公 <lb/>百折不撓的精神很可佩，但必須學會繞道而行，才能離成功和目標更進 <lb/>一步。懂得繞道而行的人，往往是第一個達到目標的人(語大 S23)。 <lb/>獲得四分和三分者多是論點和論據無問題，但論證不完整或完全 <lb/>沒有論證，如 S9 得四分：「งʮʆձ‫‬ʆdงʮܱ݊ٙ͜Ҫʆ <lb/>ܱ̻d‫‬݊͜༪ႀʆԐdҢˢ༰˕ܵ‫‬ٙ˙‫ج‬dΪ‫މ‬݊І <lb/>ʉ༪ႀ༪ՑҪʆԐdШงʮܱ݊ٙ͜dவᅵ˄ɮəd༪ႀˢ༰Ҟ」 <lb/>(語大 S9)；S11 得三分：「งʮ݊͜ҪʆԐd‫‬݊༪ʆႀd <lb/>Ң݊ࠅยԐٙdʔཀҢᙂேʔλdࠅ͜߅ኪٙ˙‫ج‬ʑึ‫ܘ‬ҞٙҪʆ <lb/>͜ʔԈ」(語大 S11)。至於獲得二分至 分的 位學生則是缺少論 <lb/>點或論據中的一項，且論證完全缺乏。 <lb/>訪談六位學生對於議論文的瞭解中，也可發現四位學生可以輕鬆 <lb/>地說出自己對於探究的爭議性人物之論點、論據和論證，如探究秦始 <lb/></body>

			<page>82 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">圖書資訊學研究 9：2 (June 2015) <lb/></note>

			<body>皇的 S28 表示：「Ңࡁٙሞᓃఱ݊˼݊ਃɽٙެnn್‫ܝ‬ሞᗇఱ݊ <lb/>ҢࡁᙂΪ‫˼މ‬ɓəʕd್‫ܝ‬ɦІ၈݊ެnn್‫ܝ‬ɰ݊ึ‫މ‬І <lb/>ʉٙdఱ݊ึซࠅʔࠅᜫйɛҸ͂ආԸdఱ݊˼ਂ‫ܘ‬εԫઋd˼ <lb/>ጘəԢ‫(」۬ڗ‬S28 訪 20140114)。但有二位程度屬低和中等程度 <lb/>的學生較無法分辨論點、論據和論證的內容，如編號 S2 學生表示(S2 <lb/>訪 20140114)： <lb/>Ӻ٫jίᄳᙄሞ˖ٙࣛࡉdЫࡁ݊ʔ݊Ϟሞᓃeሞᗇeሞኽd <lb/>Ыᐝ༆ək <lb/>S2jϞᐝ༆nnʔ݊‫ܘ‬ଉɝٙᐝ༆f <lb/>Ӻ٫jЫ̙ʔ̙˸ᑘࡈԷɿk <lb/>S2jఱ݊ሞᓃnnఱ݊ࠅԟࡈnnᑘ̈༧ԟࡈ˴ᕚϞᗫٙԷ <lb/>ɿf <lb/>Ӻ٫jෝf <lb/>S2j್‫ܝ‬nnሞኽఱ݊ࠅnఱ݊ҪԟԬҬՑٙ༟ࣘdҪ̴‫׳‬ආ <lb/>̘ᙄሞ˖༁ࠦf <lb/>Ӻ٫jঐʔঐᑘࡈԷɿdԷνЫࡁଡ଼ٙฌΪվλədሞᓃe <lb/>ሞኽeሞᗇʱй݊ʡჿk <lb/>S2jఱ݊nnҢٙሞᓃఱ݊ฌΪվ˼ٙ࿁ሞd್‫ܝ‬ճnn <lb/>˼ٙሞኽఱ݊ҢҬ̈˼ʘ‫ۃ‬ԟԬ࿁ሞdఱ݊Ϟᗫ࿁ሞٙԫઋd <lb/>್‫ܝ‬Ҫ̴ᄳආ̘ <lb/>Ӻ٫jሞᗇճk <lb/>S2jෝdሞᗇnnʔাəߚl <lb/>級任林老師在學期末撰寫的反省文章中也指出，雖然他以五年級 <lb/>國語課本中唯一的一篇議論文「繞道而行」為例，利用七節課時間講 <lb/>解和練習論點、論據和論證三元素，及提問、摘要、詰問作者等閱讀 <lb/>策略，但仍有部分學生難掌握論證的精髓，因為： <lb/>வࡈʱٙኪ୦dՉྼ࿁ኪ͛ԸႭ݊ࠅ‫ͭܔ‬ɓࡈอٙਿᅼdఱ <lb/>݊‫ה‬ፗٙᙄሞ˖ٙ‫ݖ‬dኪ̥͛ீཀટᙃɓᇐᙄሞ˖ሙ͉ <lb/>ʕٙሙ˖Չྼʔd‫͜ܘࡁ˼˸ה‬୦࿕ٙাા˖ਿᅼ <lb/>Ըίᙄሞ˖ɪࠦiϾሞᓃeሞኽձሞᗇఱ݊ɧࡈอᄣ̋ٙືᓃd <lb/>வʱٙኪ୦ʥცܵᚃආБdʔ݊ᅰੀሙఱঐͭߊԈᅂٙf <lb/>‫˖ࢪ؍ॴ‬ <lb/></body>

			<page>83 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">林菁、陳耀輝：應用爭議導向之探究式學習於資訊素養課程： <lb/>培養國小五年級學生議論能力 <lb/></note>

			<body>綜上可知，經由爭議導向探究之資訊素養課程，大部份學生瞭解 <lb/>議論文的目的和基本結構，能從一篇簡短的文章找出論據(如期末定 <lb/>期評量)，對於重組句子也能找出合理的邏輯；但對於更開放的題目 <lb/>(如說明合作的重要)，及統整兩篇較長且論點不同的文章(如愚公 <lb/>移山和明鑼移山)，約三分之一學生的表現稍弱，無法靈活應用議論 <lb/>文的三大元素，尤其在提出論證上有不夠深入之嫌。此就如 Osborne、 <lb/>Erduran、Simon 與 Monk(2001)所言，論證是高層次的認知能力，必 <lb/>須透過多次真實情境的練習才能提升學生此一能力。 <lb/>ɚeኪ͛ί‫ن‬ᙄ‫‬ᙄᕚᄳЪٙ‫ڌ‬ତ <lb/>爭議性議題寫作的關鍵在強而有力的論點、合理的論證，以及相 <lb/>關且充足的證據。由於升上高年級前，研究對象在國語課程中接觸的 <lb/>文體多是記敘文和應用文，所以他們對於議論文的結構和寫作均感陌 <lb/>生。此次學習任務的最終作品是撰寫一篇議論文，故在探究爭議性人 <lb/>物的過程中，級任林老師利用國語課講解議論文的結構和三大元素， <lb/>再請學生活用所學，撰寫一篇自己探究的爭議性人物議論文。 <lb/>根據「爭議性文章寫作規準」，全班 30 人中有 6 人是 95 分以上， <lb/>表示論點、論據、論證、組織和句型五個向度均達「很棒」等級，只 <lb/>有在用語上稍有差池；10 人獲得 90~94 分，表示至少有兩個向度是「很 <lb/>棒」等級，其他向度多在「很不錯」等級。但另有 14 人在 80~89 分間， <lb/>表示至少有一個向度是「再加油」等級，其中在論點、論據、論證、 <lb/>組織、句型和用語六個向度中，「再加油」等級的人數分別是 3、5、9、 <lb/>6、5、7 人。這些數據表示約半數的學生在議論文寫作上能活用所學， <lb/>表現優異，但仍有半數學生表現較弱，尤其在論證上未能妥善分析和 <lb/>說明論據，以支持自己的論點。 <lb/>事實上，多位學生在撰寫完議論文後的反省短文中，寫出他們覺 <lb/>得議論文寫作困難之處： <lb/>Ң˸‫ۃ‬ேӚϞᄳཀᙄሞ˖d̴ձՉ˼Ъ˖ٙࢨй݊ࠅϞሞᓃe <lb/>ሞኽձሞᗇfҢᙂ௰Ѣᗭٙή˙݊˴ᕚɛ‫ٙي‬൙ᄆცࠅҬՑԑ <lb/>ٙᗇኽ˕ܵሞᗇi௰Ⴠᕦٙή˙݊ίᄳഐሞ̙ࣛ˸ਞϽʊ <lb/>ଣλٙ༟ࣘ(S10 反省文) <lb/>ᄳவᇐЪ˖ცࠅሞᓃeሞኽeሞᗇdν؈ˇᄳɓࡈఱʔ݊ᙄሞ <lb/>˖dϾ˲ᒔࠅ‫ء‬จɛ‫̻͛ٙي‬eԫe൙ᄆdவԬ݊ձՉ˼˖ <lb/>ʔΝٙή˙(S5 反省文) <lb/></body>

			<page>84 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">圖書資訊學研究 9：2 (June 2015) <lb/></note>

			<body>ᙄሞ˖ٙഐձՉ˼˖ʔΝd̴ϞሞᓃeሞᗇeሞኽdᒔϞ <lb/>࿁‫ن‬ᙄ‫‬ɛ‫̻͛ٙي‬e͍ࠋࠦ൙ᄆ(S20 反省文) <lb/>ᙄሞ˖ձՉ˼Ъ˖‫ڢ‬੬ʔɓᅵdҢࡁʔঐ྅াા˖ɓᅵ‫׳‬ɝ˄ <lb/>εชઋdɦʔঐ྅Ꮠ͜˖ɓᅵϞ‫ܘ‬εဲਪ̩d‫˸ה‬ࣛҢʔٝ༸ <lb/>‫ܣ‬ჿᄳk‫ܝ‬ԸҢӔ֛͜ϼࢪٙɧɽʩ९Ըᄳ(S24 反省文) <lb/>வϣЪ˖ˢৎ˸‫ۃ‬௰ɽʔΝ݊ࠅ͜༟ࣘԸᄳdϾʔ݊໘೯ <lb/>ซ(S22 反省文) <lb/>ίᄳЪٙཀʕdҢίஹટࠠᓃࣛdேɓ‫ܓ‬ҬʔՑஹટ൚eᔷ <lb/>ұႧ(S21 反省文)f <lb/>由以上撰寫的反省可看出，學生已瞭解議論文的特性，及它與其 <lb/>他文體不同之處，只是因為初次接觸，在寫作的熟練度上還需加強， <lb/>尤其是活用轉折語(如然而、但是、卻……等)更是陌生，只有少數 <lb/>學生能正確使用它們。例如研究秦始皇的 S23 在議論文作文中，正確 <lb/>地使用轉折語，將找到的正面和反面資料循序的陳述出來。首先，他 <lb/>在第一段先描述秦始皇的生平，之後第二段舉證其若干正面事蹟，再 <lb/>運用轉折語「然而」連接第三段，列舉多項有關秦始皇的負面事件和 <lb/>自己的論證，最後第四段綜合上述，提出秦始皇為暴君的論點。 <lb/>ୋɓ‫ެॢݬ‬dίࣛ˾ՈЍٙෂփɛ‫ي‬dίЗٙ <lb/>ɧɤɖϋ༁dఱ‫ط‬əʕɤ̬ϋdᒱ್வ࿁˚‫ٙܝ‬ʕᅂᚤଉ <lb/>ჃdШ˼ίՉʕɰಞəεೌٙɛf <lb/>ୋɚ‫ݬ‬ɓʕ‫ܝ‬d˼ጳ‫ܔ‬ə‫۬ڗ‬d‫ת‬ҤΖ̱dɦɓə˖ <lb/>οe࿆e‫ܓ‬ඎdˮಃ̙Ⴍ݊ίॢಃ‫ܔ‬ৎədᆽྼ݊ࡈəʔৎٙ <lb/>ެf <lb/>ୋɧ‫್ݬ‬Ͼd˼ਂԫɓจ֘Бd͊ᛓ՟˼ɛٙ‫ܔ‬ᙄdɰʔ <lb/>ᗴԈІʉٙॹᓃdֵɨٙЅɿேʔΣ˼ආፏdϾ˲˼Ⴉ‫މ‬ኊ <lb/>ࣣ͛͜༁ٙԊሞҭ൙Іʉd‫މ‬əʔᜫ˼ࡁᘱᚃᅧԊሞdʔШደ <lb/>์̦ࣣdᒔ‫ݺ‬εኊ͛dɓࡈሬ‫ٙ‬ёˮdᏐ༈ࠅϞකᒪٙː <lb/>Ըટॶйɛٙ‫ܔ‬ᙄdϾʔ݊͜੶ࠗٙ˙όੁИйɛٙɹfΎ٫d <lb/>ጳ‫ࣛ۬ڗܔ‬d˼ٙ݊͜Ꮐࠗɛ͏ٙ˙‫ج‬d࿁‫ೌ˓‬ʂ᚛ٙϵ֑d <lb/>ॆٙცࠅவჿಞҜkࣣΝ˖dϞɛႩ‫މ‬வԫ݊‫ط‬ଣٙλ <lb/>‫ج‬d‫ۍ‬ӚϞɛԈɳ٫ٙే‫ۑ‬dԟԬɛᗭ༸ʔҎૐঐ‫ڭ‬वІ <lb/>ʉٙ˖οkࣛٙɛɰႩ‫੶ࡈ݊˼މ‬ᅳ‫ד‬eІ˸‫ٙ݊މ‬ɛf <lb/>ୋ̬‫ެॢݬ‬ᒱɓəʬdԨ‫ٙܝ˚މ‬ʕఢ֛ə੶ɽٙ <lb/></body>

			<page>85 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">林菁、陳耀輝：應用爭議導向之探究式學習於資訊素養課程： <lb/>培養國小五年級學生議論能力 <lb/></note>

			<body>ਿᓾdШவʕdϞεˇٙɛ‫މ‬Ϥᙼ‫ޒ‬kவԬԫઋ༁dҢႩ‫މ‬ <lb/>ॢެ݊ࡈʔʠ༸ٙᅳёd˼ٙБ‫݊މ‬уԴ˼ਂΎεഛԫeϞΎ <lb/>ɽ্ٙᘠɰೌ‫ج‬Ꮞٙf(S23 議論文) <lb/>事 實 上， 兩 位 老 師 在 課 程 中 均 曾 強 調 議 論 文 轉 折 語 運 用 的 原 <lb/>則：寫在轉折語之前的事件是自己不支持的立場，之後的事件才是 <lb/>自 己 支 持 且 要 傳 達 的 論 點， 數 量 應 較 前 者 為 多( 研 札 20131113、 <lb/>20131115)。但許多學生在使用轉折語時，並未仔細考慮自己支持論 <lb/>點之正反面性質，就貿然將資料陳述出來，違反議論文中轉折語的使 <lb/>用原則。例如研究曹操的 S5 雖然將事件和評價分開兩段來撰寫，但都 <lb/>是負面資料在前，正面在後，且數量相當；不料在第四段結論段落， <lb/>S5 卻選擇了反面評價，認為曹操是個殘忍無情的人。 <lb/>ୋɚ‫ݬ‬வЗೌɛʔٝೌɛʔወٙ૨əεϞʑঐٙɛd <lb/>νፑɻҹeग़ᔼശКձᜫૣٙˆፄf˼ᒔίࢱψ૨əɤεΤ <lb/>ೌϵ֑d֜ನʘ‫ݺ‬ɞεΤࠥжfШ݊˼ɰࠠ͜Ϟʑঐٙ <lb/>ɛdνeᕧeੵᔐձੵ፱fϤ̮d͂ཁ˂ɨɽɽʃʃٙ‫ن‬d <lb/>˷ϵϵ௷dҸೌʔдd˿ᅮɛᛓՑ˼ٙΤοேʔఫϾฒf <lb/>ୋɧ‫ݬ‬ٙԫᜫɛϞՇʷٙ൙ᄆfϞɛႩ‫˼މ‬ಞҜೌ <lb/>ઋdΪ‫˼މ‬૨ɛೌᅰe‫ࠥݺ‬жf್ϾϞɛႩ‫˼މ‬ᄱɽ‫ܓ‬dΪ <lb/>‫ࠠ͜˼މ‬εϞʑঐٙɛd‫˸ה‬ɛࡁ࿁˼Ϟ‫ܘ‬εʔΝٙ൙ᄆf <lb/>ୋ̬‫ݬ‬ҢႩ‫މ‬݊ࡈಞҜೌઋeዑБᚡ༸ٙɛdΪ‫˼މ‬૨ <lb/>əεೌٙϵ֑fఱၑ݊˼̰ٙࣛࡉd˼ɰҪப‫‬Ցɨd <lb/>ᜫεϞʑঐٙɛ‫ޒᙼ˼މ‬fҢɰ˼ٙΤԊjྐྵ̙Ңࠋ˂ɨ <lb/>ɛdɰʔঐ˂ɨɛࠋҢఱٝ༸˼݊ࡈεჿಞҜೌઋٙɛf(S5 <lb/>議論文) <lb/>此外，兩位老師也發現學生可以找出爭議性人物的爭議點，但在 <lb/>撰寫議論文時，常無法使用自己的話語將資料改寫(資素＆級任老師 <lb/>訪 20140122)： <lb/>༟९ੵࢪj˼ν؈ঐ͜Іʉٙ༑εᄳɓᓃٙ༑d˖‫ڗ‬ఱึˢ <lb/>༰‫ڗ‬dϾ˲ఱึˢ༰Ϟஹഐ‫‬f <lb/>ॴ‫ࢪ؍‬jҢν؈ίႧ˖ሙɪࠦεഗ˼ࡁɓࡈᇖ୦dఱˢνႭ <lb/>˼ࡁତίʊࠅ̈Ըəd್‫ܝ‬ҢவᗙΎᜫ˼ࡁࠠอҷᄳɓϣd <lb/></body>

			<page>86 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">圖書資訊學研究 9：2 (June 2015) <lb/></note>

			<body>̙ঐึˢ༰λf <lb/>༟९ੵࢪjவԬ‫܀‬ɿఱ݊ңၣࠫձңࣣɪd˼ࡁϞঐɢҴՑࠠ <lb/>ᓃdШࠠᓃ݊ң̈Ըٙ <lb/>ॴ‫ࢪ؍‬j࿁d˼ࡁቡᛘɓԬ༟ࣘٙଣ༆ɢʔd‫˼˸ה‬Ҫ̴ <lb/>ᔷ౬ϓ˖οٙࣛࡉdᄳЪٙࣛࡉɽʱ݊ԟᗙңཀԸd˼ʔ݊ <lb/>͜Іʉٙ༑ࠠᄳࠑd˼̙ঐᄳٙ‫ܘ‬ε؇Г݊˼Ցٙ‫ݔ‬ɓ‫ݬ‬d <lb/>˼ᙂவɓ‫ݬ‬ୌΥ˴ᕚd˼ఱҪ˼ңɨԸf <lb/>༟९ੵࢪj‫˸ה‬ԟࡈʱdΌफਂ௰λٙఱ݊ S29d̥Ϟ S29 <lb/>ɓࡈɛே͜Іʉٙ༑fՉ˼‫܀‬ɿ˷ே݊ҪɓԬ˼ᙂʔცࠅٙ <lb/>мદd್‫ܝ‬ԟࡈ̩ɿң̈Ըd್‫ܝ‬ʔΝ̩ɿஹίɓৎd̙݊ S29 <lb/>͜Іʉٙ༑ᄳਧl <lb/>事實上，S29、S24、S28 三人一起探討秦始皇，共享取得的資料， <lb/>合作繪製概念圖，但各自撰寫議論文。二位老師發現 S29 寫的文句雖 <lb/>然未稱優美，但用自己的話改寫取得的資料。例如： <lb/>ϞɛႩ‫݊ެॢމ‬ᅳёdΪ‫ਂ˼މ‬ə‫ܘ‬εʔλٙԫઋdॢެ <lb/>ࣣѦኊdҪ‫ܘ‬ε̦ࣣ͜˦ደəd˼ᒔຫ˟Ϟɛ༁ϞவԬࣣd <lb/>ν؈ॢެ೯ତϞɛኹϞவԬࣣd˼ึ͜‫˙ٙݺ‬όҪ˼ࡁ૨ϥi <lb/>Ϥ̮dॢެ͜ə˄εɛɢႊ‫۬ڗ‬əd‫ܘ‬εɛᙂԟᅵʔλf <lb/>(S29 議論文) <lb/>同組的 S24 雖然文句較有文采，但未消化資料，論證也較不嚴謹： <lb/>ॢެϞԬɛ൙ᄆ‫މ‬ᅳёdΪ‫˼މ‬ࣣѦኊdϾ˲ᒔίႊ‫ڗ‬ <lb/>۬ࣛਗ͜˄εٙɛɢdΪ‫މ‬வᅵॢಃɓʕ‫̥ܝ‬ዝɤ̬ϋఱу <lb/>ѓᔧɳfnnॢެ‫ͭܔ‬əʕ̦ɪୋɓࡈɓٙeε͏ૄeਖ਼ <lb/>Փ˴່ʕ̯ණᛆٙd‫މ‬ʕٙ೯ఢ֛əྼٙਿᓾf‫ה‬ፗ <lb/>Іॢ˸ԸdՉՓ͊ᜊఱ݊வࡈจ‫ܠ‬f(S24 議論文) <lb/>級任老師給予 S24 上述這段文字的評論是： <lb/>வ༁ॢಃዝࣛɤ̬ϋᔧɳٙሞᗇʔnn˼ՉྼӚϞॆٙ <lb/>ଣ༆˼ՑٙவԬ؇Гd˼̥݊ɽ฿οࠦɪμٝ༸Ⴍவࡈ͍݊ <lb/>ࠦdԟࡈ݊ˀࠦd̙݊༁ࠦʫε͏ૄeਖ਼Փ˴່eʕ̯ණᛆ <lb/></body>

			<page>87 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">林菁、陳耀輝：應用爭議導向之探究式學習於資訊素養課程： <lb/>培養國小五年級學生議論能力 <lb/></note>

			<body>ഃnnμՉྼӚϞॆٙ‫ܘ‬Ꮡd̙݊μึ̘Ҫ̴ಫ̈Ը༟ <lb/>९¯ॴϼࢪஞ 20140122f <lb/>同組的 S28 雖然與 S29 和 S24 使用同樣的資料，但論證不清楚， <lb/>也未篩檢較適用的資料： <lb/>Ϟɛᙂॢެ݊ᅳёdΪ‫މ‬ႊ‫˄ࣛ۬͜ڗ‬εɛɢdۜ˄ <lb/>εɦ˄ശdደદ̦ࣣձࣣѦኊfϤ̮d‫ܘ‬εɛሯဲॢެѐ <lb/>ʔࠨʘɿdॢ‫ݼ‬ՑႻٙ݊ॢެٙ˨ፋମɛɦΤɿูd <lb/>ମɛྼॢ݇ᑳˮʘɿdШࣛٙήЗʔ৷fS28 ᙄሞ˖݂ <lb/>ॴϼࢪ࿁ S28 ᅠᄳٙᙄሞ˖ᄳɨٙ൙Ⴇ݊jɿูɓԫၾ <lb/>ॢެٙ‫ن‬ᙄೌᗫdደદ̦ࣣၾࣣ‫ࠠۆ‬ልf <lb/>事實上，S18 在反省短文中也自省自己會不由自主的將資料直接 <lb/>抄錄下來： <lb/>ίᄳʘ‫ۃ‬ซλࠅᄳ‫ޟ‬ჿdШ‫ܝ‬Ըίᄳɦᙂʘ‫ۃ‬ซٙʔ˄ <lb/>λd௰‫ܝ‬ᄳɨԸϞԬ݊Ҫ༟ࣘңɨԸ(S18ˀ˖ )fΪϤdՇ <lb/>ЗϼࢪேႩ‫މ‬ኪ͛ึ༟ࣘʕʱؓ̈ʔΝᝈᓃdШϞࣛೌ‫ج‬ҴՑ <lb/>༟ࣘٙࣨːd݂ί‫މ‬ഐ༰ልᕏٙᙄሞ˖ࣛd˼ࡁึɢϞ͊ <lb/>ංfੵϼࢪ‫ͪڌ‬j྅வϣவᅵᄳՇᗙٙᝈᓃdҢᙂ݊ҢࡁΆ <lb/>ྡːdࣛˢ༰৷dҎૐவᅵɿਂdᜫ‫܀‬ɿ̙˸͜ɓࡈᔷұ̩d <lb/>̙݊ԫྼɪ‫܀‬ɿɰঐᄳdᄳ̈ԸɰˢӚϞவᅵٙሙԸٙλd̥ <lb/>݊Ⴍ࿁˼ࡁٙሞᗇٙʱఱ݊ˢ༰ࢮf(資素＆級任老師訪 <lb/>20140122)。 <lb/>解決之道可能是如級任林老師的建議： <lb/>ҢᙂҢίᄳЪவ෯ӚϞഹɢ‫ܘ‬εdఱ̥݊Ϟᜫ˼ࡁᄳdШ݊ <lb/>ՉྼᄳЪ‫ܘ‬ცࠅϼࢪഗٙΫ㉿d̙݊Ϊ‫ܘމ‬ώd‫˸ה‬Ңҷٙɰ‫ܘ‬ <lb/>࿔dՉྼҢᙂν؈ҢΫ㉿εɓᓃᏐ༈ึˢ༰λ༟९¯ॴ <lb/>ϼࢪஞ 20140122d˸ʿ༟ৃ९ቮੵϼࢪٙɚࡈ೯ซ(資素＆級 <lb/>任老師訪 20140122)j <lb/>其一是不要被閱讀的文本挾制： <lb/></body>

			<page>88 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">圖書資訊學研究 9：2 (June 2015) <lb/></note>

			<body>ν؈ӚϞ˖͉̙˸ਞٙࣛࡉdҢࡁ੶ࠗ˼͜˼ٙ௪ٝᗆ̘ഐ <lb/>Υd˼வࣛࡉึ੶ࠗІʉҪ˼Ցʡჿ՟̈ԸnԷνႭ‫܀‬ɿ <lb/>ίཥ໘‫ݟ܃‬༟ࣘd‫٫א‬ίྡࣣӊࡈɛٙ˓ɪேϞࣣdԟҢԚ <lb/>ٙࣛࡉdҢఱࠅᆽ֛˼ࡁίাٙࣛࡉdவࡈ˖͉݊Υഹٙd‫݊٫א‬ <lb/>ίཥ໘‫܃‬d˼ཥ໘ࠅাٙࣛࡉd˼ٙፃ࿇ࣲ݊ࠦவᅵd್‫ܝ‬ <lb/>ഃ˼Ҫ˼ซাٙাҁd˼ʑঐ͂කፃ࿇dٙࣛࡉ˼ఱʔাd <lb/>াٙࣛࡉ˼ఱ݊Ҫ˼ᜊࣲࠦn˼ʔ͜˖͉ແИٙࣛࡉd˼ఱϞ̙ <lb/>ঐ˸‫ܝ‬வᅵਂf̙݊ତίҢࡁҁΌӚϞˏኬ˼வᅵਂd˼ఱʔึซ <lb/>ՑႭdࡡԸ˼Іʉ݊Ա፠ԟԬ˖͉ٙd˼ՉྼІʉӚϞจᗆՑf <lb/>其二是只整理一個面向，不要兼顧正反雙方： <lb/>˼ࡁவϣ̀ЪՇࠦdΝࣛࠅ͍݊˙dΝࣛɰࠅ݊ˀ˙d‫˸ה‬ <lb/>Ϟࣛࡉᗭе˼ࡁఱึพʔูfШ݊ν؈Ⴍ˼ࡁࠅਂٙ݊ɓࠦd <lb/>፯ɓࡈᝈᓃႭ‫މ‬ʡჿdఱึˢ˼ࡁՇᗙேࠅᚥʿԸٙ‫‬f <lb/>另一方面，雖然學生在撰寫有關爭議性人物文章時，遭遇上述的 <lb/>困難，但有許多學生表示這次撰寫議論文是個很好的學習經驗，相信 <lb/>自己只要不斷練習和改進，將來一定會越寫越好(S19、S20、S26、 <lb/>S24 反省文)。 <lb/>總之，藉由首次撰寫爭議性人物議論文的機會，學生確實瞭解議 <lb/>論文與其它文體不同之處。但活用轉折語，以及確實消化資料，再用 <lb/>自己的話重新論述論證是學生還需再學習之處。可喜之處是學生自知 <lb/>多次練習撰寫議論文會讓自己更精進，兩位老師的建議如即時給予回 <lb/>饋、抽離閱讀文本，以及簡化議論為一個面向等，均是未來研究可再 <lb/>驗證的方向。 <lb/>ɧeኪ͛ί‫ن‬ᙄ‫‬ᙄᕚɹ᎘೯‫ڌٙڌ‬ତ <lb/>探究完爭議性人物後，張老師安排每組上臺報告探究的結果，並 <lb/>接受同儕提問。結果十組學生中有五組可以清楚且有邏輯的報告小組 <lb/>論點，三組論據豐富，但論證略顯不足，另二組則論點和論證均弱。 <lb/>在邏輯清楚的組別方面，秦始皇第 2 組先報告秦始皇的生平背景， <lb/>再以焚書坑儒和太過奢華兩個論據，來論證秦始皇的負面評價，之後 <lb/>利用轉折語帶入三點正面事蹟，包括統一文字、統一單位和蓋萬里長 <lb/>城以防止別國攻打。最後他們推論出小組自己的觀點： <lb/></body>

			<page>89 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">林菁、陳耀輝：應用爭議導向之探究式學習於資訊素養課程： <lb/>培養國小五年級學生議論能力 <lb/></note>

			<body>Ңࡁʃଡ଼Ⴉ‫݊ެॢމ‬ЗਃɽٙެdΪ‫ਂ˼މ‬ə‫ܘ‬ᗭਂٙԫ <lb/>ઋd྅ɓə˖οձఊЗdԴෂ༺ৃࢹһ˙‫ک‬nϾ˲˼ᒔႊə <lb/>Ԣ‫۬ڗ‬dԴйɛʔ‫‬Ҹ͂ආԸdɰ݊ʔ‫ٙ‬ԫઋG9 <lb/>ᔊజ 20131213f <lb/>秦始皇第 3 組雖然也是先報告秦始皇的生平，但他們是先客觀的 <lb/>說明有關秦始皇的事件(如統一六國、書同文車同軌、焚書坑儒、修 <lb/>築長城等)，再提出正面評價的理由和論證(秦始皇是位了不起的皇 <lb/>帝因為他奠定基礎、統一思想和抵禦匈奴)，及負面評價的理由和論 <lb/>證(秦始皇是位暴君因為他讓其他國家亡國、虐待人民、剛強暴戾、 <lb/>自以為是)。他們最後統整出自已組的觀點是： <lb/>ॢެ݊ЗᅳёdΪ‫˼މ‬ʔᛓ՟‫ܔ‬ᙄձʔᚥᅇйɛชաٙᅂᚤ <lb/>һᘌࠠ(G10 簡報 20130103)f <lb/>因此，他們二組雖然報告的內容類似，但因為安排的順序不同， <lb/>所以推論出不同的論點，但均屬合理的論證。 <lb/>再以論證較不足的三個組別為例，其中秦始皇第 1 組清楚報告秦 <lb/>始皇的生平和事件(包括焚書、坑儒、書同文、車同軌、兵馬俑)， <lb/>但客觀的事件與負面和正面評價的連結缺乏清楚說明。他們最後從「兵 <lb/>馬俑」和「萬里長城」成為現今觀光資源的角度來論證，認為秦始皇 <lb/>是位不錯的皇帝(見圖 1)。此論證較為牽強與唐突，也與之前的事 <lb/>件和正負面評價的解說連結不起來。 <lb/>ྡ 1 Ȳॢެୋ 1 ଡ଼ٙᔊజࠫࠦ <lb/></body>

			<page>90 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">圖書資訊學研究 9：2 (June 2015) <lb/></note>

			<body>另外，曹操第 1 組學生所提出的論證也是不足，且有牴觸之嫌。 <lb/>雖然他們繪製清楚的概念圖，包括生平背景、事蹟、評價和想法(見 <lb/>圖 2)；但對於曹操提出的評價卻相互矛盾(曹操的正面評價是重用 <lb/>了許多人，負面評價是殺有才能的人)，沒有提出進一步的論證和分 <lb/>析，即做出小組的結論是「Ңࡁᙂ݊ࡈಞҜೌઋٙɛdΪ‫˼މ‬ <lb/>‫ࠥݺ‬жdᒔ૨Ϟʑঐٙɛ」。因此，學生 S23 追問他們：「‫މ‬ <lb/>ʡჿࠅ‫ࠥݺ‬жk」S23 ਪ，張老師也提問：「ˆፄ̥Ϊ‫މ‬Ԑ፹ <lb/>ᄽ‫ژ‬Ͼ૨dШᇥٙ˨ፋٙໆʔ݊һɽd‫ۍ‬ӚϞ૨f <lb/>‫ˆ˸ה‬ፄٙঐɢ݊ˢ༰ʔλkʔ್˼‫ܣ‬ჿ૨knnӺ݊ࠠ <lb/>͜Ϟʑঐٙɛdᒔ݊૨Ϟʑঐٙɛkᒔ̤̮݊ϞࡡΪk」(G4 簡報 <lb/>20131220)。曹操第 1 組學生愣在當下，無法回答大家的提問。 <lb/>ྡ 2 Ȳୋ 1 ଡ଼ٙᔊజࠫࠦ <lb/>最後再以論點和論證均弱的二組為例，他們都瞭解各自探究的爭 <lb/>議性人物伽利略和愛因斯坦之生平，卻無法掌握這兩位人物的爭議性 <lb/>所在。以前者來說，伽利略第 2 組學生雖然查出日心說和地心說的內 <lb/>容，但無法有邏輯的論證為何伽利略會得到「妖言惑眾」和「偉大的 <lb/>科學家」之不同評價，也無法分辨「日心說」是中性的事件，不是正 <lb/>面評價；且此評價有時間的差異性，因為正面評價是後代人給予伽利 <lb/>略，嘉許他對後代科學的影響，但當時的教會仍認為他是違反教義(見 <lb/>圖 3)。再以後者愛因斯坦組別來說，他們簡單說明「相對論」在當 <lb/>時是個很奇怪的學說，但未指出愛因斯坦的爭議性主在相對論後來促 <lb/>成了原子彈的發明。他們只列出世人對於愛因斯坦的評價有「白癡」 <lb/>和「天才」之別，似乎愛因斯坦的爭議點是他智商的高低。 <lb/></body>

			<page>91 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">林菁、陳耀輝：應用爭議導向之探究式學習於資訊素養課程： <lb/>培養國小五年級學生議論能力 <lb/></note>

			<body>ྡ 3 ȲТлଫୋ 2 ଡ଼ٙᔊజࠫࠦ <lb/>在三週口頭報告的過程中，雖然張老師不斷提醒學生詢問同儕 <lb/>時，要提出與爭議性人物爭議點有關的問題(如標題與內容論點是否 <lb/>搭配、是否有評價正負面事件和影響、邏輯是否有說服力等)(研札 <lb/>20131213、20131220、20131227)，但整體而言，學生提出的問題仍 <lb/>偏重事實性。例如「ТлଫϞഐk」S17 ਪ、「ॢެϞʃ <lb/>‫܀‬k」(S21 問)、「ฌΪվ݊ᅃɛ૨ϥٙk」S1 ਪ等。 <lb/>直到第三週報告時，少數學生才開始提出涉及邏輯性的問題，如「‫މ‬ <lb/>ʡჿТлଫଡ଼ٙԫձ൙ᄆேᄳ˚ːႭd൙ᄆʔ݊Ꮠ༈ᄳԫٙ <lb/>ᅂᚤk」(S4 問)。 <lb/>因此，張老師在訪談時表示學生的思考習慣要慢慢養成，不能操 <lb/>之過急，學生能專心聆聽別組的發表就是重要的進步： <lb/>྅ S9 ঐ৵ɪ೯ତୋ 1 ଡ଼ PPT ਗ਼ٙϋᄳ፹Гʩ <lb/>155~200 ϋd͍ᆽᏐ‫މ‬ 220 ϋdԮϋʔ݊ 66 ๋dఱ‫ܘ‬ᄒəf <lb/>ᅰኪ‫ܘ‬λdɰ‫ܘ‬ਖ਼ː(張師訪 20140104)f <lb/>再就口頭報告 PPT 簡報的製作技巧來分析，由於電腦課程已教導 <lb/>學生製作 PPT 簡報的基本技巧，故張老師只利用兩節課時間指導學生 <lb/>如何規畫和製作簡報的內容，包括封面(包括標題、組員名字)、大綱、 <lb/>內容(包含生平、事件、正面和負面評價、小組評價)、資料來源等。 <lb/>為了鼓勵學生使用自己的話語重述資料的重要內容，而不是照抄長篇 <lb/>原始資料，張老師請學生遵守優秀簡報版面的基本原則，例如圖文並 <lb/>茂、文字簡潔且易讀，並特別強調 666 原則。結果各組的簡報多符合 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">圖書資訊學研究 9：2 (June 2015) <lb/></note>

			<body>這些原則，如秦始皇第 2 組報告秦始皇負面評價，不但圖文搭配適宜 <lb/>且文字精簡(見圖 4)。但是也有幾組的簡報精簡過度，反而缺少了 <lb/>細節內容(見圖 5)。 <lb/>ྡ 4 Ȳॢެୋ 2 ଡ଼ٙᔊజࠫࠦ <lb/>ྡ 5 Ȳॢެୋ 3 ଡ଼ٙᔊజࠫࠦ <lb/>簡報資料過度精簡的缺點是口頭報告的組別若未再口頭詳加闡 <lb/>述內容，仍是照唸這些簡短的文字，會讓聽講的學生掌握不到重點； <lb/>如果聽講者又沒有繼續追問，那麼學生是無法瞭解此爭議人物的來龍 <lb/>去脈。張老師就在秦始皇第 3 組簡短報告後，詢問學生：「Ыࡁேٝ <lb/>༸ԟࣛࡉ݊Դ͜ʡჿ˖οkॢެɓϓʡჿ˖οk˼ɦɓə <lb/>ʡჿఊЗkவԬே̥ϞλٙᅂᚤkЫࡁʔਪdజѓٙɛఱӚϞႭ‫‬ <lb/>ٙዚึਧnn」(G10 簡報 20140103)結果學生在老師的提醒下， <lb/>才恍然自己不完全瞭解秦始皇的事蹟，卻沒有追問。研究者之後訪問 <lb/>多位學生對於各組報告的意見時，也發現他們的困難，S3 說：「й <lb/>ଡ଼జѓࠪඎ˄ʃd‫ܘ‬ᇔٙவᅵෞᓊཀ̘n…ϞɓԬఱᛓʔᏑdᙣ <lb/>٫ˮ‫̻ږ‬ԟɓଡ଼ԟࡈԫҢఱҁΌᛓʔᏑn…ҁΌʔٝ༸ᗫႭίᑺ <lb/>‫ޟ‬ჿn…ఱၑ‫ܝ‬ԸΎሗ˼ࡁᑺɓϣdШҢᒔ݊ᛓʔᏑn…」(S3 訪 <lb/>20140114)；S10 也說：「ʝ൙‫ܘ‬ѢᗭќlΪ‫މ‬ҢேӚᛓู」(S10 <lb/>訪 20140109)。此外，從研究者訪問 S19 的談話中，也可窺見學生不 <lb/>知如何追問的端倪(S19 訪 20140107)： <lb/>Ӻ٫j‫މ‬ʡჿЫίˀఊɪʵ፯ᙂʃଡ଼ʝ൙ٙࣛࡉˢ༰Ѣ <lb/>ᗭk <lb/>S19jΪ‫މ‬ఱ݊ӚϞ‫ܘ‬ଉɝᐝ༆வଡ଼ٙɛ‫ي‬dЫ̙ঐึʔnٝ <lb/>༸˼ࡁίᑺʡჿn <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">林菁、陳耀輝：應用爭議導向之探究式學習於資訊素養課程： <lb/>培養國小五年級學生議論能力 <lb/></note>

			<body>Ӻ٫jఅd‫˸ה‬வ༁ࠦϞЫӚટᙃཀٙɛ‫ي‬k <lb/>S19j࿁d྅Тлଫf <lb/>Ӻ٫j‫˸ה‬ఱኬߧЫᛓʔᏑ˼ࡁίజѓʡჿk <lb/>S19jᛓᏑd̙݊ఱӚϞ‫ܘ‬n…ӚϞ྅ҢࡁІʉଡ଼ίᑺІʉଡ଼ <lb/>வჿᐝ༆f <lb/>Ӻ٫j‫˸ה‬Ыࡁࠅ൙˼ࡁʱᅰఱˢ༰ᗭ൙ək <lb/>S19j࿁ਧdΪ‫މ‬Ϟ̙ঐ˼ࡁਂ‫ܘ‬λd݊ҢࡁᛓʔᏑd‫݊٫א‬ <lb/>˼ࡁϞ༧Ңࡁɓᅵٙਖ਼ϞΤ൚ʘᗳٙf <lb/>Ӻ٫jЫࡁӚϞซΣ˼ࡁ̈ਪᕚk <lb/>S19jଫ፰ဲӚϞߚ ! Ϊ‫މ‬ਪٙਪᕚʔ˄λn <lb/>由以上的資料可知，較佳的爭議性人物口頭報告首先應該是在報 <lb/>告前，老師先引導學生在簡報中條列人物生平、事件和評價的關鍵語 <lb/>詞，而非寫出完整句子或整段文字；繼之，在報告時報告者要用自己 <lb/>的話語大聲且清楚地報告爭議性人物的基本資料，再闡述正面和反面 <lb/>的論據和論證，以得出小組的論點；此時，聽講者不要懼怕問題問得 <lb/>不佳，而是確實追問聽不清楚和覺得論證不合邏輯之處，以給予報告 <lb/>者再次深入說明的機會。唯有三者齊備，才能提升學生爭議性議題口 <lb/>說的能力。此就如 Kuhn(2008)和 Flint(2008)所言，爭議性議題的 <lb/>探究教學需要給予學生充裕成長的時間，讓他們能投入探究中。此外， <lb/>老師還要以促進者的角色，給予學生適當的回饋和引導，才較易激發 <lb/>起學習的動力(Newell et al., 2011)。 <lb/>ͼeഐሞၾ‫ܔ‬ᙄ <lb/>ɓeഐሞ <lb/>由以上的研究結果可知，在國小五年級資訊素養課程中應用爭議 <lb/>性人物主題探究，來培養學生議論能力是一可行的方案。藉由資訊素 <lb/>養老師和級任老師的協同教學，學生整體議論能力有顯著進步，他們 <lb/>大部分瞭解議論文與其他文體不同處，知道議論文的論點、論據和論 <lb/>證三個基本元素，也能從簡短的議論文中找出證據，並統整兩篇文章 <lb/>的觀點。在議論文實際寫作方面，半數的學生表現優異，能活用所學， <lb/>撰寫出具有觀點的爭議性人物議論文章；但仍有半數學生在撰寫議論 <lb/>文上遭遇困難，尤其在論證方面，未能妥善分析和說明論據，以支持 <lb/></body>

			<page>94 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">圖書資訊學研究 9：2 (June 2015) <lb/></note>

			<body>自己的論點。此外，許多學生未完全熟悉轉折語用法，也無法消化資 <lb/>料，再用自己的話重新論述論證。在口頭發表方面，十組學生中有五 <lb/>組可具邏輯性的報告小組觀點，三組也可清楚說出小組論點，但論證 <lb/>較不足，另二組則論點和論證均弱。雖然各組多能製作簡潔的電腦簡 <lb/>報，以輔助自己的口頭報告，但大聲且清楚報告自己組的觀點，及同 <lb/>儕彼此提問和追問的能力均仍待加強。 <lb/>事實上，爭議性人物探究是研究對象首次接觸的爭議性議題和議 <lb/>論文，他們如此的表現已屬難能可貴。就如兩位協同教學老師所言， <lb/>資訊素養課程若能設計循序漸進的議論導向學習任務，由簡入繁，逐 <lb/>步讓學生有系統的持續學習爭議性議題，相信其議論能力會有更好的 <lb/>表現。雖然小小國小導入資訊素養課程已近十年，研究對象自一年級 <lb/>下學期即開始接觸主題探究學習，但無論低年級和中年級的學習任務 <lb/>成品，均偏向記敘文和說明文的撰寫，如一年級生物大搜索的海報、 <lb/>二年級社區的 QA 單張、三年級樹朋友的身分證等(林菁，2011、 <lb/>2012；林菁、謝欣穎、謝文峰，2014)，較少涉及爭議性議題的探索， <lb/>以及議論文的閱讀和寫作。因此，Gunning(2012)之建議也許可做為 <lb/>未來修正資訊素養課程之參考，如讓低年級學生撰寫較少爭議性的議 <lb/>論文(如減少使用塑膠袋)，但不用提出論證；協助中年級學生進階 <lb/>至從文章中簡單列出支持論點的論據和理由；高年級至國中學生須提 <lb/>出有關論點的正面和反面論證；最後至國中畢業學生則不但可提出豐 <lb/>富的正面和反面觀點，且組織順暢。 <lb/>ɚe‫ܔ‬ᙄ <lb/>根據本研究的發現，研究者提出三點建議做為未來有關此領域教 <lb/>學和研究的參考： <lb/>( 一 ) 將爭議導向之探究學習藉由資訊素養課程和 Big6 模式來教學，可 <lb/>以培養國小五年級學生的議論能力，但最好能自較低年段即開始 <lb/>設計循序漸進爭議導向之學習探究任務，以有系統的逐步提升學 <lb/>生提出論點、論據和論證的能力。 <lb/>( 二 ) 無論資訊素養和級任老師最好能協同及時提供回饋，引導學生活 <lb/>用轉折語、改寫資料、加強論證邏輯思考，以及增加合理提問策 <lb/>略教學等課題。 <lb/>( 三 ) 本研究仍有若干未解決的問題，須賴未來研究釐清，如抽離閱讀 <lb/>文本以強化改寫能力、提供有溝通對象的真實情境以活用議論技 <lb/>巧等。 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">林菁、陳耀輝：應用爭議導向之探究式學習於資訊素養課程： <lb/>培養國小五年級學生議論能力 <lb/></note>

			<div type="acknowledgment">Ⴆᑽ <lb/>本 文 為 科 技 部 計 畫 的 部 分 研 究 成 果(NSC101-2511-S-415-011-<lb/>MY3)，感謝科技部對本研究之經費補助。 <lb/></div>
			
			<listBibl>ਞϽ˖ᘠ <lb/>李琬蓉(2009)。ഐΥ‫ܠ‬ᚗᇖ୦ٙᄳЪኪӺj˸ʬϋॴᙄሞ˖ <lb/>‫މ‬Է。未出版之碩士論文。國立臺中教育大學語文教育系，臺中。 <lb/>林佩璇(2000)。個案研究及其在教育研究上的應用。載於中正大學 <lb/>教育學研究所主編，ሯٙӺ˙‫462-932(ج‬ 頁)。嘉義：麗文文化。 <lb/>林菁(2011)。資訊素養融入國小一年級「校園生物大搜索」主題探究： <lb/>以 Super3 模式為例。ԃ༟ࣘၾྡࣣኪ֙̊，48(4)，539-570。 <lb/>林菁(2012)。資訊素養融入國小二年級社會學習領域「我們的社 <lb/>區」主題探究：以 Super3 模式為例。ԃ༟ࣘၾྡࣣኪ֙̊， <lb/>49(3)，447-478。 <lb/>林菁、謝欣穎、謝文峰(2014)。資訊素養融入國小三年級自然學習 <lb/>領域「樹朋友」主題探究。ྡࣣ༟ৃኪӺ，8(2)，57-99。 <lb/>林菁、顏仁德、黃財尉(2014)。探究式資訊素養融入課程成效之四 <lb/>年長期研究。ԃ༟ࣘၾྡࣣኪ֙̊，51(4)，561-595。 <lb/>許佩琦(2001)。‫ن‬ᙄ‫˖‬ٙቡᛘଣ༆Ӻ。未出版之碩士論文。 <lb/>國立中正大學心理研究所，嘉義。 <lb/>梁崇輝(2004)。ɘϋɓႧ˖ჯਹୋɚኪ୦ච‫ݬ‬Ⴇ߅ࣣႭ‫˖‬ <lb/>ၾᙄሞ˖ᇐഐʱؓӺ。未出版之碩士論文。國立臺中師範 <lb/>學院語文教育學系，臺中。 <lb/>楊裕貿(2013)。兒童寫作觀察報告。Ⴇ˚జ 2013/10/30，第 9 版。 <lb/>張緯文、林樹聲(2014)。實施議論文寫作活動提升國小學生論證與 <lb/>寫作能力。߅ኪԃ˜̊，368，2-19。 <lb/>American Association of School Librarians (2009). Standards for the 21st-<lb/>century learner in action. Chicago, IL: American Association of School <lb/>Librarians. <lb/>Bruce, C. (2008). Informed learning. Chicago: Association of College and <lb/>Research Libraries. <lb/>Bruce, D. L. (2009). Writing with visual images: Examining the video <lb/>composition processes of high school students. Research in the <lb/>Teaching of English, 43(4), 426-450. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">圖書資訊學研究 9：2 (June 2015) <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Chu, S. K., Tse, S. K., Loh, E. K., &amp; Chow, K. (2011). Collaborative inquiry <lb/>porject-based learning: Effects on reading ability and interests. Library <lb/>&amp; Information Science Research, 33(3), 236-243. <lb/>Council of Chief State School &amp; National Governors Association (2010). <lb/>Common Core State Standards for English language arts &amp; literacy in <lb/>history/social studies, science, and technical subjects. Washington, DC: <lb/>Author. Retrieved April 4, 2015 from http://www.corestandards.org/ <lb/>assets/CCSSI_ELA%20Standards.pdf <lb/>Crisco, V. (2009). Activating activist literacy: Discovering dispositions for <lb/>civic identity development. Composition Studies, 37(2), 31-51. <lb/>Eisenberg, M. B, &amp; Berkowitz, R. (1999). Teaching information &amp; <lb/>technology skills: The big6 in elementary schools. Worthington, OH: <lb/>Linworth. <lb/>Eisenberg, M. B., &amp; Robinson, L. E. (2007). The Super3: Information skills <lb/>for young learners. Worthington, OH: Linworth. <lb/>Felton, M. K., &amp; Herko, S. (2004). From dialogue to two-sided argument: <lb/>Scaffolding adolescents&apos; persuasive writing. Journal of Adolescent &amp; <lb/>Adult Literacy, 47(8), 672-683. <lb/>Ferretti, R. P., MacArthur, G. A., &amp; Dowdy, N. S. (2000). The effects of <lb/>an elaborated goal on the persuasive writing of students with learning <lb/>disabilities and their normally achieving peers. Journal of Educational <lb/>Psychology, 92(4), 694-702. <lb/>Flint, A. S. (2008). Literate lives: Teaching reading &amp; writing in elementary <lb/>classrooms. Hoboken, NJ: John Wiley &amp; Sons. <lb/>Flower, L. (2008). Community literacy and the rhetoric of public <lb/>engagement. Carbondale: Southern Illinois University Press. <lb/>Fulton, C. (2010). Information Pathways: A problem-solving approach to <lb/>information literacy. Lanham, UK: The Scarecrow. <lb/>Gunning, T. G. (2012). Creating literacy instruction for all students in <lb/>grades 4-8. Boston, MA : Pearson. <lb/>Harrison Group (2010). Kids and family reading report. New York: <lb/>Scholastic. Available online at mediaroom.scholastic.com/KFRR. <lb/>Hepworth, M., &amp; Walton, G. (2009). Teaching information literacy for <lb/>inquiry-based learning. Oxford, UK: Chandos. <lb/>Hillocks, G. (2010). Teaching argument for critical thinking and writing: An <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">林菁、陳耀輝：應用爭議導向之探究式學習於資訊素養課程： <lb/>培養國小五年級學生議論能力 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>introduction. English Journal, 99(6), 24-32. <lb/>Hillocks, G. (2011). Teaching argument writing, grades 6-12: Supporting <lb/>claims with relevant evidence and clear reasoning. Portsmouth, NH: <lb/>Heinemann. <lb/>Kuhlthau, C. C., Maniotes, L. K., &amp; Caspari, A. K. (2007). Guided inquiry: <lb/>Learning in the 21st century. Westport, CT: Libraries Unlimited. <lb/>Kuhn, D. (2008). Education for thinking. Cambridge, MA: Harvard <lb/>University Press. <lb/>Kuhn, D., &amp; Udell, W. (2003). The development of argument skills. Child <lb/>Development, 74(5), 1245-1260. <lb/>Kurbanoglu, S, Grassian, E., Mizrachi, D., Catts, R., &amp; Spiranec, S. (Eds.) <lb/>(2013). Worldwide commonalities and challenges in information <lb/>literacy research and practice. Communication in Computer and <lb/>Information Science, 397. New York: Springer. <lb/>Larson, B. E., &amp; Keiper, T. A. (2011). Instructional strategies for middle <lb/>and secondary social studies: Methods, assessment, and classroom <lb/>management. New York, NY: Routledge. <lb/>Llewellyn, D. (2013). Teaching high school science inquiry and <lb/>argumentation. Thousand Oaks, CA: Corwin. <lb/>Mason, L., &amp; Scirica, F. (2006). Prediction of students&apos; argumentation skills <lb/>about controversial topics by epistemological understanding. Learning <lb/>and Instruction, 16, 492-509. <lb/>Means, M. L., &amp; Voss, J. F. (1996). Who reason well? Two studies of <lb/>informal reasoning among children of different grade, ability, and <lb/>knowledge levels. Cognition and Instruction, 14, 139-178. <lb/>Merriam, S. B. (1998). Qualitative research and case study applications in <lb/>education. San Francisco, CA: Jossey-Bass. <lb/>Midgette, E., Haria, P., &amp; MacArthur, C. (2008). The effects of content and <lb/>audience awareness goals for revision on the persuasive essays of fifth-<lb/>and eighth-grade students. Reading and Writing, 21(1/2), 131-151. <lb/>National Research Council (2012). A framework for K-12 science education: <lb/>Practices, crosscutting concepts, and core ideas. Washington, DC: <lb/>National Academics press. <lb/>New Literacies Research Team (2006). Results summary reports 1-6 from <lb/>the survey of Internet usage and online reading. Storrs, CT: Neag <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>98 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">圖書資訊學研究 9：2 (June 2015) <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>School of Education, University of Connecticut. Available online at <lb/>http://www.newliteracies.unconn.edu/pubs.html. <lb/>Newell, G. E., Beach, R., Smith, J., &amp; VanDerHeide, J. (2011). Teaching <lb/>and learning argumentative reading and writing: A review of research. <lb/>Reading Research Quarterly, 46(3), 273-304. <lb/>Osborne, J., Erduran, S., Simon, S., &amp; Monk, M. (2001). Enhancing the <lb/>quality of argument in school science. School Science Review, 82(301), <lb/>63-69. <lb/>Sampson, V., Grooms, J., &amp; Walker, J. (2009). Argument-driven inquiry: <lb/>A way to promote learning during laboratory activities. The Science <lb/>Teacher, 76(8), 42-47. <lb/>Sandoval, W. A., &amp; Millwood, K. A. (2005). The quality of students&apos; used of <lb/>evidence in written scientific explanations. Cognition and Instruction, <lb/>23, 23-55. <lb/>Santana Arroyo, S. (2013). Information literacy for health professionals: <lb/>Teaching essential information skills with the Big6 information literacy. <lb/>Community &amp; Junior College Libraries, 19(3/4), 77-91. <lb/>Springer, K. (2010). Educational research: A contextual approach. <lb/>Hoboken, NJ: Wiley. <lb/>State of Delaware (2013). Argumentation/opinion text-based writing rubrics. <lb/>Retrieved on March 23, 2015 from http://www.doe.k12.de.us/Page/508 <lb/>Ward, M. Sr. (2009). Squaring the learning circle: Cross-classroom <lb/>collaboration and the impact of audience on student outcomes in <lb/>professional writing. Journal of Business and Technical Communication, <lb/>23(1), 61-82. <lb/>Wolfe, C, R., Britt, M. A., &amp; Butler, J. A. (2009). Argumentation schema <lb/>and the myside bias in written argumentation. Written Communication, <lb/>26(2), 183-209. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>99 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">林菁、陳耀輝：應用爭議導向之探究式學習於資訊素養課程： <lb/>培養國小五年級學生議論能力 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">‫ڝ‬ ‫ن‬ᙄ‫‬ɛ‫͛ࢪي‬ஞሔᕚͦఊ <lb/>訪問學生： <lb/>1. 你為什麼選擇這位爭議性人物？你原來對這位人物有多熟悉？ <lb/>2. 你們多是採用何種資料來源？為什麼選擇它們？ <lb/>3. 你在閱讀資料時的心得和困難是甚麼？ <lb/>4. 你現在了解事件和評價的差別嗎？論點、論據和論證的差別？請 <lb/>舉個你探究人物的例子來說明一下。 <lb/>5. 你們小組是如何形成最後的小組觀點 ( 評價 ) ？ <lb/>6. 你撰寫議論文的心得是甚麼？哪裡較容易？哪裡較困難？ <lb/>7. 你製作 PPT 和報告的心得是甚麼？哪裡較容易？哪裡較困難？為 <lb/>甚麼？ <lb/>8. 你覺得自己要怎樣做，下次撰寫議論文時可以寫得更精彩？ <lb/>9. 如果你自己再挑選別的爭議性主題，你會想選甚麼主題？為什麼？ <lb/>10. 你們小組的合作狀況如何？如何分工？喜歡和他們合作嗎？ <lb/>訪問級任老師 &amp; 資訊素養老師： <lb/>1. 你覺得學生在此探究任務過程中的資訊素養表現如何 ( 定義問題、 <lb/>尋找策略、取得資訊、使用資訊、統整、評估 ) ？哪裡有進步？哪 <lb/>裡還需要改進？ <lb/>2. 這學期你教了學生哪些閱讀策略？成效如何？你覺得學生在此探 <lb/>究任務中的閱讀和寫作表現如何？ <lb/>3. 你覺得議論文寫作適合融入爭議性人物探究任務嗎？為甚麼？有 <lb/>何需要改進之處？ <lb/>4. 你覺得這次任務與你之前的任教經驗有何不同的地方？哪裡需要 <lb/>改進？ <lb/>5. 你覺得學生在此探究任務過程中彼此幫忙的表現如何？分組方式 <lb/>需要如何改進？ <lb/>6. 你覺得學生在五年級下學期還需要加強有關資訊素養能力和語文 <lb/>能力的地方各是什麼？為什麼？ <lb/>7. 你對於將資訊素養課和語文課等統整為學習任務的看法為何？ <lb/>8. 你對於與其他老師協同合作 ( 進行學習任務或其他目的 ) 的看法為 <lb/>何？ <lb/>9. 你還有哪些其他想表達的意見？ <lb/></div>

			<page>100 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Libray and Information Science Research 9:2 (June 2015) <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">Argument-Driven Inquiry in Fifth-Grade Information <lb/>Literacy Instruction: <lb/>A Way to Cultivate Students&apos; Argument Skills <lb/>Lin-Ching Chen <lb/>Professor <lb/>Department of E-learning Design &amp; Management <lb/>National Chiayi University <lb/>Yaw-Huei Chen <lb/>Associate Professor <lb/>Department of Computer Science &amp; Information Engineering <lb/>National Chiayi University <lb/>Introduction <lb/>Many researchers allege that acquiring argumentative reading and <lb/>writing strategies and practices are important for school curricular reform, <lb/>because the ability to identify the underlying argument, and its claims, <lb/>warrants, and evidence are crucial for academic success (Hillocks, 2011; <lb/>Kuhn, 2008; Newell, Beach, Smith, &amp; VanDerHeide, 2011). In fact, the <lb/>essence of argumentation contains logical and critical thinking, which are <lb/>skills critical to empowered and meaningful participation in a democratic <lb/>society. <lb/>There are three basic elements in an argumentative text (Hillock, 2010, <lb/>2011; Mason &amp; Scirica, 2006). First, a claim is the statement and position <lb/>proposed by the author; it is persuasive if it demonstrates an insightful <lb/>understanding of topics. Secondly, evidence is the data which supports the <lb/>claim; regardless of types of evidence, they should be substantial, correct, <lb/>and related to the topic. Third, a warrant provides insightful analysis <lb/>of how evidence supports the claim. Owing to the complex structure of <lb/>argumentative texts, it is not easy to learn and teach them. <lb/></div>

			<page>101 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Argument-Driven Inquiry in Fifth-Grade Information Literacy <lb/>Instruction: A Way to Cultivate Students&apos; Argument Skills <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">Many challenges in teaching argument are mentioned in studies <lb/>(Hillock, 2010; Kuhn, 2005; Newell, Beach, Smith, &amp; VanDerHeide). For <lb/>example, both teachers and students lack clear concepts about structures <lb/>of argumentative texts because most textbooks often favor narrative and <lb/>explanatory texts over argumentative ones. In fact, compared to narrative <lb/>and expository texts, the structure of argumentative texts are nonlinear and <lb/>more complex. Hillocks (2010) asserted that teachers may not know the <lb/>instructional procedures for learning argumentative reading and writing. <lb/>Furthermore, there is agreement that teachers prefer a conflict-free zone in <lb/>classrooms during learning (Newell, et al., 2011). <lb/>How can we teach students to make a good argument? Kuhn (2008) <lb/>alleged that inquiry and argument offer the most promising paths to <lb/>resolving conflicts and solving problems. Science educators also promote <lb/>argument-driven inquiry approaches in science teaching (Sampson, Grooms, <lb/>&amp; Walker, 2006). Information literacy instruction emphasizes abilities of <lb/>inquiry, problem-solving and critical thinking. Recently it has became one of <lb/>the curricula promoted in different levels by various countries (Fulton, 2010; <lb/>Hepworth &amp; Walton, 2009). Many studies have suggested that it should be <lb/>integrated across the contexts of regular school curriculum through inquiry <lb/>learning (Chen &amp; Hsieh, 2013; Chu, Tse, Loh, &amp; Chow, 2011). Thus, there <lb/>is a need to further investigate how to design argument-driven inquiry <lb/>in information literacy instruction to cultivate students&apos; argumentative <lb/>skills. Thus, the main purposes of this study were to examine the effects of <lb/>argument-driven inquiry information literacy instruction on fifth-graders&apos; <lb/>argumentative performance. <lb/>Specific research purposes were as follows: <lb/>1.1 To examine students&apos; overall argument performance in information <lb/>literacy instruction. <lb/>1.2 To investigate students&apos; argument writing performance in information <lb/>literacy instruction. <lb/>1.3 To investigate students&apos; oral presentation performance in information <lb/>literacy instruction. <lb/></div>

			<page>102 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Libray and Information Science Research 9:2 (June 2015) <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">Methodology <lb/>This study employed a case study to investigate the effects of argument-<lb/>driven inquiry instruction on fifth graders&apos; argument skills. The main <lb/>research site was a fifth-grade classroom which had a total of 30 students <lb/>(15 boys and 15 girls). The elementary school has adopted information <lb/>literacy instruction since 2005, which was designed by the researchers <lb/>and school teachers, and integrated it into various subject matters via the <lb/>framework of inquiry-based learning, including the Super 3 and Big 6 <lb/>models. A series of inquiry projects have been implemented in information <lb/>literacy instruction in each semester since the second semester of grade one. <lb/>Therefore, all participants were familiar with inquiry-based learning, but <lb/>had little experience with argument writing. Ms. Chang, a teacher/librarian <lb/>was responsible for teaching the information literacy instruction, while Ms. <lb/>Lin, the homeroom teacher, taught writing. They both were collaborative <lb/>teachers in this study. The information literacy instruction was taught once <lb/>a week for a forty-minute period over seventeen weeks during a single <lb/>semester. <lb/>Argumentative text was introduced for the first time in the fifth-<lb/>grade Chinese language arts class this semester. Thus, Ms. Chang, Ms. <lb/>Lin and the researchers designed an inquiry project, titled &quot;Controversial <lb/>Persons Inquiry&quot; in the information literacy course to cultivate students&apos; <lb/>understanding of argumentative reasoning and writing. Students worked <lb/>in peer-mediated cooperative learning groups of three and were free to <lb/>choose any controversial persons based on their interests or select from <lb/>among the list Ms. Chang provided. Ten groups of students were asked to <lb/>collect and find more relevant information as well as perspectives on the <lb/>persons of interest from a number of resources, including books, websites, <lb/>newspaper articles, and magazine articles. After reading the materials, each <lb/>group cooperatively drew concept maps to define the framework of the <lb/>controversial person. At the same time, students recorded useful information <lb/>and perspectives in worksheets. <lb/>Based on the concept map, each student wrote an essay containing <lb/>both pro and con perspectives about the person with supporting evidence, <lb/>reasons, and his/her final position. Then each group presented their inquiry <lb/></div>

			<page>103 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Argument-Driven Inquiry in Fifth-Grade Information Literacy <lb/>Instruction: A Way to Cultivate Students&apos; Argument Skills <lb/></note>
			
			<div type="annex">project to their peer cohorts with PowerPoint, and answered questions asked <lb/>by peers. At last, students reviewed the whole inquiry process through <lb/>reflecting on whether they have done their best to complete the inquiry <lb/>projects. <lb/>The Argument Test, designed by the researchers was used for the pretest <lb/>and posttest in this study. It was composed of 13 questions which included <lb/>seven multiple-choice questions and six open-ended items for measuring <lb/>students&apos; comprehension of argumentative texts. The Cronbach&apos;s α reliability <lb/>coefficient of the test was 0.707. Open-ended questions were scored on a <lb/>0-5 Likert scale on the basis of their correctness and completeness by the <lb/>first author and an independent judge; the inter-rater reliability as indicated <lb/>by percentage agreement was 0.719. Students&apos; essays containing claims, <lb/>evidence and warrants were scored using the rubrics. The writing rubrics <lb/>included six criteria (claims, evidence, warrants, organization, sentences, <lb/>and conventions); each criterion described qualitative differences between <lb/>three levels of proficient, basic, and below basic peformance. <lb/>Data collected included interviews, participant observations, tests, and <lb/>document analyses. The documents collected included the reflective article <lb/>Ms. Lin wrote, school mid-term tests, and argumentative articles students <lb/>wrote. All of the qualitative data were organized, coded, reviewed and <lb/>analyzed multiple times. The quantitative test data were analyzed using a t <lb/>test. <lb/>Results <lb/>3.1 Students&apos; Overall Argument Performance in the Information Literacy <lb/>Instruction <lb/>According to the Argument Test results in Table 1, the paired sample <lb/>t-test was significant (t=5.855, p=.000&lt;0.05). It showed that fifth graders <lb/>acquired overall argument skills after learning argument-driven inquiry <lb/>information literacy instruction. Students understood the structural <lb/>differences between argument texts and others. Most fifth graders could <lb/>find evidence in short argumentative texts. However, some students had <lb/>problems in integrating different perspectives from longer argumentative <lb/>texts. <lb/></div>

			<page>104 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Libray and Information Science Research 9:2 (June 2015) <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">Table 1 Summary of t Test in Argument Test <lb/>Number <lb/>Pretest <lb/>Posttest <lb/>t <lb/>p <lb/>M <lb/>SD <lb/>M <lb/>SD <lb/>30 <lb/>11.77 <lb/>5.097 <lb/>15.77 <lb/>4.360 <lb/>5.855 <lb/>.000 <lb/>α= .05 <lb/>3.2 Students&apos; Argument Writing Performance in the Information Literacy <lb/>Instruction <lb/>Based on the argumentative articles students wrote, half of the students <lb/>could write an argumentative article about a controversial person with their <lb/>own prespectives. However, the other half of students had problems with <lb/>argumentative writing; especially in the warrants. They could not support <lb/>their claims with sound reasoning, though they had substantive evidence. <lb/>Furthermore, many students were not familiar with the usage of transitional <lb/>expressions, such as but, however, therefore, etc. Students also had problems <lb/>in paraphrasing the found information in their own words. <lb/>3.3 Student Oral Presentation Performance in the Information Literacy <lb/>Instruction <lb/>Of ten groups, five groups presented their findings logically and <lb/>lucidly; three groups proposed their perspectives clearly, but reasoning was <lb/>weak. The last two groups performed poor in providing claims and warrants. <lb/>Most groups did their oral presentations with concise power point slides. <lb/>However, their ability in posing questions to their peers during presention <lb/>needs to be improved. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>This was the first time fifth-graders experienced controversial issue <lb/>and argument texts. Although fifth-graders&apos; performance still needed to be <lb/>improved, what they performed was impressive. Both the teacher/librarian <lb/>and classroom teacher suggested that we should systematically design <lb/>argument-driven inquiry projects in information literacy curricula from the <lb/>lower grades in elementary level, so that students&apos; argumentative reasoning <lb/>can be progressively developed. Through such curriculum we can expect to <lb/>effectively empower an inclusive and informed future citizenry capable of <lb/>critical thinking, empowered argumentation, and meaningful participation in <lb/></div>

			<page>105 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Argument-Driven Inquiry in Fifth-Grade Information Literacy <lb/>Instruction: A Way to Cultivate Students&apos; Argument Skills <lb/></note>
			
			<div type="annex">our democratic society. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Reference <lb/>American Association of School Librarians (2009). Standards for the 21st-<lb/>century learner in action. Chicago, IL: American Association of School <lb/>Librarians. <lb/>Bruce, C. (2008). Informed learning. Chicago: Association of College and <lb/>Research Libraries. <lb/>Bruce, D. L. (2009). Writing with visual images: Examining the video <lb/>composition processes of high school students. Research in the <lb/>Teaching of English, 43(4), 426-450. <lb/>Chang, W. W., &amp; Lin, S. S. (2014). Shi shi yi lun wen xie zuo huo dong ti <lb/>sheng guo xiao xue sheng lun zheng yu xie zuo. Science Education <lb/>Monthly,368, 2-19. [Text in Chinese] <lb/>Chu, S. K., Tse, S. K., Loh, E. K., &amp; Chow, K. (2011). Collaborative inquiry <lb/>porject-based learning: Effects on reading ability and interests. Library <lb/>&amp; Information Science Research, 33(3), 236-243. <lb/>Council of Chief State School &amp; National Governors Association (2010). <lb/>Common Core State Standards for English language arts &amp; literacy in <lb/>history/social studies, science, and technical subjects. Washington, DC: <lb/>Author. Retrieved April 4, 2015 from http://www.corestandards.org/ <lb/>assets/CCSSI_ELA%20Standards.pdf <lb/>Crisco, V. (2009). Activating activist literacy: Discovering dispositions for <lb/>civic identity development. Composition Studies, 37(2), 31-51. <lb/>Eisenberg, M. B., &amp; Berkowitz, R. (1999). Teaching information &amp; <lb/>technology skills: The big6 in elementary schools. Worthington, OH: <lb/>Linworth. <lb/>Eisenberg, M. B., &amp; Robinson, L. E. (2007). The Super3: Information skills <lb/>for young learners. Worthington, OH: Linworth. <lb/>Felton, M. K., &amp; Herko, S. (2004). From dialogue to two-sided argument: <lb/>Scaffolding adolescents&apos; persuasive writing. Journal of Adolescent &amp; <lb/>Adult Literacy, 47(8), 672-683. <lb/>Ferretti, R. P., MacArthur, G. A., &amp; Dowdy, N. S. (2000). The effects of <lb/>an elaborated goal on the persuasive writing of students with learning <lb/>disabilities and their normally achieving peers. Journal of Educational <lb/></div>

			<page>106 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Libray and Information Science Research 9:2 (June 2015) <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">Psychology, 92(4), 694-702. <lb/>Flint, A. S. (2008). Literate lives: Teaching reading &amp; writing in elementary <lb/>classrooms. Hoboken, NJ: John Wiley &amp; Sons. <lb/>Flower, L. (2008). Community literacy and the rhetoric of public <lb/>engagement. Carbondale: Southern Illinois University Press. <lb/>Fulton, C. (2010). Information Pathways: A problem-solving approach to <lb/>information literacy. Lanham, UK: The Scarecrow. <lb/>Gunning, T. G. (2012). Creating literacy instruction for all students in <lb/>grades 4-8. Boston, MA : Pearson. <lb/>Harrison Group (2010). Kids and family reading report. New York: <lb/>Scholastic. Available online at mediaroom.scholastic.com/KFRR. <lb/>Hepworth, M., &amp; Walton, G. (2009). Teaching information literacy for <lb/>inquiry-based learning. Oxford, UK: Chandos. <lb/>Hillocks, G. (2010). Teaching argument for critical thinking and writing: An <lb/>introduction. English Journal, 99(6), 24-32. <lb/>Hillocks, G. (2011). Teaching argument writing, grades 6-12: Supporting <lb/>claims with relevant evidence and clear reasoning. Portsmouth, NH: <lb/>Heinemann. <lb/>Hsu, P. C. (2001). A study of controversial text comprehension. Unpublished <lb/>master&apos;s thesis, National Chung Cheng University, Chiayi, Taiwan. <lb/>[Text in Chinese] <lb/>Kuhlthau, C. C., Maniotes, L. K., &amp; Caspari, A. K. (2007). Guided inquiry: <lb/>Learning in the 21st century. Westport, CT: Libraries Unlimited. <lb/>Kuhn, D. (2008). Education for thinking. Cambridge, MA: Harvard <lb/>University Press. <lb/>Kuhn, D., &amp; Udell, W. (2003). The development of argument skills. Child <lb/>Development, 74(5), 1245-1260. <lb/>Kurbanoglu, S., Grassian, E., Mizrachi, D., Catts, R., &amp; Spiranec, S. (Eds.) <lb/>(2013). Worldwide commonalities and challenges in information <lb/>literacy research and practice. Communication in Computer and <lb/>Information Science, 397. New York: Springer. <lb/>Larson, B. E., &amp; Keiper, T. A. (2011). Instructional strategies for middle <lb/>and secondary social studies: Methods, assessment, and classroom <lb/>management. New York, NY: Routledge. <lb/>Llewellyn, D. (2013). Teaching high school science inquiry and <lb/></div>

			<page>107 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Argument-Driven Inquiry in Fifth-Grade Information Literacy <lb/>Instruction: A Way to Cultivate Students&apos; Argument Skills <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">argumentation. Thousand Oaks, CA: Corwin. <lb/>Li, W. Z. (2009). The teaching study of writing integrated speculation <lb/>planning-take six six graders&apos; to argumentative essays for example. <lb/>Unpublished master&apos;s thesis, National Taichung University, Taichung, <lb/>Taiwan. <lb/>Liang, C. H. (2004). Study on the analysis of text structure of exposition <lb/>and argumentation on Grade 1-9 Integrated Coordinated Curriculum <lb/>Second learning stage Chinese language textbook. Unpublished <lb/>master&apos;s thesis, National Taichung University, Taichung, Taiwan. [Text <lb/>in Chinese] <lb/>Lin, C. C. (2011). Integrating Information Literacy into First-Grade Inquiry <lb/>Learning: An Example of Creature Investigation on Campus Using <lb/>the Super3 Model. Journal of Educational Media &amp; Library Sciences, <lb/>48(4), 539-570. [Text in Chinese] <lb/>Lin, C. C. (2011). Integrating Information Literacy into First-Grade Inquiry <lb/>Learning: An Example of Creature Investigation on Campus Using <lb/>the Super3 Model. Journal of Educational Media &amp; Library Sciences, <lb/>48(4), 539-570. [Text in Chiese] <lb/>Lin, C. C., Hsieh H. Y., &amp; Sie, W. F. (2014). Integrating Information <lb/>Literacy into Third-Grade Science Inquiry Learning: An Example of <lb/>My Plant Friends. Journal of Library &amp; Information Science Research, <lb/>8(2), 57-99. [Text in Chiese] <lb/>Lin, C. C., &amp; Yan, R. D., &amp; Huang, T. W.(2014). The Effects of Inquiry-<lb/>Based Integrated Information Literacy Instruction: Four-Year Trends. <lb/>Journal of Educational Media &amp; Library Sciences, 51(4), 561-595. <lb/>[Text in Chinese] <lb/>Lin, P. S. (2000). Ge an yan jiu ji qi zai jiao yu yán jiu shang de ying yong. <lb/>In National Chung Cheng University Institute of Education (Eds), Zhi <lb/>De Yan Jiu Fang fa. Chiayi: Liwen [Text in Chinese] <lb/>Mason, L., &amp; Scirica, F. (2006). Prediction of students&apos; argumentation skills <lb/>about controversial topics by epistemological understanding. Learning <lb/>and Instruction, 16, 492-509. <lb/>Means, M. L., &amp; Voss, J. F. (1996). Who reason well? Two studies of <lb/>informal reasoning among children of different grade, ability, and <lb/>knowledge levels. Cognition and Instruction, 14, 139-178. <lb/></div>

			<page>108 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Journal of Libray and Information Science Research 9:2 (June 2015) <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">Merriam, S. B. (1998). Qualitative research and case study applications in <lb/>education. San Francisco, CA: Jossey-Bass. <lb/>Midgette, E., Haria, P., &amp; MacArthur, C. (2008). The effects of content and <lb/>audience awareness goals for revision on the persuasive essays of fifth-<lb/>and eighth-grade students. Reading and Writing, 21(1/2), 131-151. <lb/>National Research Council (2012). A framework for K-12 science education: <lb/>Practices, crosscutting concepts, and core ideas. Washington, DC: <lb/>National Academics press. <lb/>New Literacies Research Team (2006). Results summary reports 1-6 from <lb/>the survey of Internet usage and online reading. Storrs, CT: Neag <lb/>School of Education, University of Connecticut. Available online at <lb/>http://www.newliteracies.unconn.edu/pubs.html. <lb/>Newell, G. E., Beach, R., Smith, J., &amp; VanDerHeide, J. (2011). Teaching <lb/>and learning argumentative reading and writing: A review of research. <lb/>Reading Research Quarterly, 46(3), 273-304. <lb/>Osborne, J., Erduran, S., Simon, S., &amp; Monk, M. (2001). Enhancing the <lb/>quality of argument in school science. School Science Review, 82(301), <lb/>63-69. <lb/>Sampson, V., Grooms, J., &amp; Walker, J. (2009). Argument-driven inquiry: <lb/>A way to promote learning during laboratory activities. The Science <lb/>Teacher, 76(8), 42-47. <lb/>Sandoval, W. A., &amp; Millwood, K. A. (2005). The quality of students&apos; used of <lb/>evidence in written scientific explanations. Cognition and Instruction, <lb/>23, 23-55. <lb/>Santana Arroyo, S. (2013). Information literacy for health professionals: <lb/>Teaching essential information skills with the Big6 information literacy. <lb/>Community &amp; Junior College Libraries, 19(3/4), 77-91. <lb/>Springer, K. (2010). Educational research: A contextual approach. Hoboken, <lb/>NJ: Wiley. <lb/>State of Delaware (2013). Argumentation/opinion text-based writing rubrics. <lb/>Retrieved on March 23, 2015 from http://www.doe.k12.de.us/Page/508 <lb/>Ward, M. Sr. (2009). Squaring the learning circle: Cross-classroom <lb/>collaboration and the impact of audience on student outcomes <lb/>in professional writing. Journal of Business and Technical <lb/>Communication, 23(1), 61-82. <lb/></div>

			<page>109 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Argument-Driven Inquiry in Fifth-Grade Information Literacy <lb/>Instruction: A Way to Cultivate Students&apos; Argument Skills <lb/></note>
			
			<div type="annex">Wolfe, C. R., Britt, M. A., &amp; Butler, J. A. (2009). Argumentation schema <lb/>and the myside bias in written argumentation. Written Communication, <lb/>26(2), 183-209. <lb/>Yang, U. M. (2013, October 30). Er tong xie zuo guan cha bao gao. <lb/>Mandarin Daily News, 9. [Text in Chinese] </div>


	</text>
</tei>
