<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="j41-2" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			<reference>
				圖書資訊學刊 第13卷第2期 (2015.12) 頁29-66
				<lb />
			</reference>

			<idno>
				doi:10.6182/jlis.2015.13(2).029
				<lb />
			</idno>

			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>
					明代江西地方官府藏書事業研究─ 以各級儒學為考察中心
					<lb />
				</titlePart>
			</docTitle>
			The Book Collecting Activities of the Local Governments in
			<lb />
			the Jiangxi District during the Ming Dynasty: Focusing on the
			<lb />
			Collections of Ruxues, the Government-founded Schools
			<lb />


			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					陳冠至 1
					<lb />
					Kuan-Chih Chen 1
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			摘 要
			<div type="abstract">
				明代是中國古代藏書事業史上的繁榮期，其藏書事業的發展與成就，超過了歷史上以 往的任何時期。就地方官府的藏書事業而言，由於明初諸帝對國家教育與藏書事業的高度 重視，促使各地官府對本地公家藏書事業的經營也都非常積極。本研究聚焦於藏書史研究 者向來甚少著眼，卻為明代進士產量高居全國第三位的江西行省。由於明代地方官府的藏 書事業，主要建立在地方儒學藏書的建設之上，因此，本文便以探索它們的歷史現象及其 對提昇區域學術與文化發展為主題，除了期盼彌補目前明代藏書史研究之不足外，更希望 能以明代江西地方官府藏書事業對區域讀書風氣的推動經驗，作為今日探討地方政府推廣 書香社會和地方圖書館事業的一項參考基礎。</div>
			<lb />
			關鍵字：
			<keyword>
				藏書、儒學、江西、地方官府、明代 Abstract
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			In the Chinese history, Ming dynasty is an era when book collection activities flourished. The
			<lb />
			intensity and achievement of book collecting by governments far exceeded the previous eras and
			<lb />
			arrived at the peak. The emperors&apos; emphasis on education and the widespread of ruxues, government-
			<lb />
			founded schools, had contributed to the development of official book collections all over the country.
			<lb />
			At that time, the Jiangxi province was the third largest source of government officials and bureaucrats.
			<lb />
			The cultural intensity in Jiangxi was of great historical significance. However, the book collecting
			<lb />
			activities in that region and their relations to the flourishing intellectual traditions and achievements
			<lb />
			were hardly studied in existing literatures. Hence, this paper carefully examined the cultural
			<lb />
			phenomenon in that locality based on historical materials in order to bridge the gap. The regional and
			<lb />
			local book collection history may also shed lights on today&apos;s society in terms of promoting libraries
			<lb />
			and book reading.
			<lb />
			Keywords:
	Book Collection; Ruxue; Jiangxi; Local Government; Ming Dynasty
			<lb />
			1
			<byline>
				<affiliation>
					輔仁大學圖書資訊學系
					<lb />
				</affiliation>
			</byline>
			Department of Library and Information Science, Fu Jen Catholic University,
	

	New Taipei, Taiwan
			<lb />
			E-mail:
			<email>080677@mail.fju.edu.tw</email>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>