<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="j42-6" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			<reference>
				圖書資訊學刊 第14卷第1期 (2016.6) 頁151-179
				<lb />
			</reference>

			<idno>
				doi:10.6182/jlis.2016.14(1).151
				<lb />
			</idno>
			<docTitle><titlePart>圖書資訊學領域開放近用期刊之學術傳播速度： 以論文初次被引用時間來衡量</titlePart></docTitle>
			<lb />
			
				
					The Scholarly Communication Speed of Library and Information
					<lb />
					Science Open Access Journals as Measured by First-Citation
					<lb />
				
			

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					尤玳琦 1 
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			<byline><docAuthor>林雯瑤 2<lb /></docAuthor></byline>
			Tai-Chi Yu 1 , Wen-Yau Cathy Lin 2<lb />
			摘 要
			<div type="abstract">
				本研究從期刊論文初次被引用的觀點，利用引用文獻分析法探討圖書資訊學領域開放
				<lb />
				近用(OA)期刊在Scopus與WoS的初次被引用，以探討OA期刊的學術傳播速度。研究範 圍為收錄於2010至2013年版JCR之8種完全OA期刊與13種複合式OA期刊，在2010至2014年 間出版的期刊論文。在完全OA期刊中，Scopus有639篇期刊論文被引用，平均初次被引用
				<lb />
				時間為1.17年，WoS則有434篇期刊論文被引用，平均初次被引用時間為1.37年。在Scopus
				<lb />
				與WoS中，完全OA期刊論文的初次被引用分別有68.24%與60.13%發生在出版當年及出版 後一年。而在複合式OA期刊中，屬於OA機制的期刊論文其平均初次被引用較非OA的文 章快。相較於WoS，收錄於Scopus中的期刊論文平均被引用速度較快。本研究建議未來亦 可利用Altmetrics的概念，擴大初次被引用的定義範圍，從正式與非正式的傳播管道了解 OA期刊的初次被使用速度。
				<lb />
				
			</div>
			關鍵字：
			<keyword>
				初次被引用速度、開放近用期刊、圖書資訊學、Scopus、WoS 
			</keyword>
			Abstract
				<lb />
			Based on the time of journal article first-citation appearance, this study analyzed the citation
			<lb />
			speeds of Open Access (OA) journals within Library and Information Science (LIS) field indexed in
			<lb />
			Scopus and WoS database. Articles published between 2010 and 2014 by a total of 8 Full-OA journals
			<lb />
			and 13 Hybrid-OA journals indexed by 2010-2013 edition of JCR were collected and analyzed in
			<lb />
			June 2015. Results showed that there were 639 articles being cited in Scopus and the average first-
			<lb />
			citation speed was 1.17 year. On the other hand, there were 434 articles being cited in WoS with a
			<lb />
			slightly higher first-time citation rate of 1.37 year. Most of the articles studied were cited for the first
			<lb />
			time in the same year or the year after of its publication. There were some articles being cited even
			<lb />
			1,2
			<byline>
				<affiliation>
					淡江大學資訊與圖書館學系
					<lb />
				</affiliation>
			</byline>
			Department of Information &amp; Library Science, Tamkang University,
	

	New Taipei, Taiwan
			<lb />
			* 通訊作者Corresponding Author: 林雯瑤Wen-Yau Cathy Lin, E-mail:
			<email>
				wylin@mail.tku.edu.tw
				<lb />
			</email>
			before its official publication. Within the Hybrid-OA journals, articles belong to the OA mechanism
			<lb />
			did have shorter speed citation time than non-OA ones. This study suggested that further studies could
			<lb />
			adopt the concept of Altmetrics to investigate the first-usage speeds through the formal and informal
			<lb />
			communication channels.
			<lb />
			Keywords: First-citation Speed; Open Access Journal; LIS; Scopus; WoS
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>