<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="j43-5"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>圖書資訊學刊 第14卷第2期 (2016.12) 頁127-153<lb/></reference>

	<idno>doi:10.6182/jlis.2016.14(2).127<lb/></idno>

	
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>罕見疾病兒童與青少年之主要照護者 資訊需求與資訊行為研究<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>
     A Study of Information Needs and Information Behaviors of the<lb/> Primary Caregivers of Children and Adolescents with Rare Diseases<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>范卉妤 1  </docAuthor>
	</byline>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>邱銘心 2<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>
	Hui-Yu Fan 1 , Ming-Hsin Phoebe Chiu 2<lb/>
	

	摘 要 
	<div type="abstract">罕見疾病為罹患人數極少之疾病，無解的病因讓照護者能收集到的醫護資訊有限，其 承受之照護壓力高於一般身障家庭。本研究希望減少未來罕病家庭對資訊的不確定性，採 半結構式訪談10位罕病兒童與青少年的主要照護者為研究對象。照護者在病友未發病前多 不會注意罕病資訊，歷經診斷與確診後，則開始想了解罕病的資訊。治療與復健階段，照 護者著手找尋減緩病情的治療方式，在確定病患必須終身與病為伍時，照護者會面臨社會 福利及生涯發展的資訊需求。主要照護資訊來源多以醫院與病友協會為主。而照護者皆會 進一步地使用所獲取之資訊，以醫療專業權威、多重資訊來源、自身經驗，擇其一作為辨 識資訊正確性的方法。最後，照護者也樂於和他人分享資訊，然分享資訊的方式會因照護 者平常使用網路的習慣而有所不同。<lb/></div>
	關鍵字： 
	<keyword>罕見疾病、兒童與青少年、主要照護者、資訊需求、資訊行為</keyword>
	Abstract<lb/>
	Rare diseases by definition do not occur often and it is difficult to provide palliative care for<lb/> those affected due to the lack of information and treatment for those rare diseases. The families of<lb/> those with rare diseases bear a heavy burden and have a harder time than even the families of disabled<lb/> people. This research&apos;s goal is to provide the families of those with rare diseases with information on<lb/> how to provide care for their family members. The study uses the qualitative research method of semi-<lb/>structured interview. We interviewed 10 rare disease children and adolescents&apos; primary caregivers.<lb/> The results of the study indicated that if no one suffers from the rare diseases in their family, primary<lb/> caregivers are not aware of the rare disease information. After their initial diagnosis, the caregivers will<lb/> want to know how to best care for their family member, from how best to provide supportive care to<lb/>
    1,2
	<byline>
	<affiliation> 國立臺灣師範大學圖書資訊學研究所<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	
	Graduate Institute of Library and Information Studies, National Taiwan Normal University,
	

	Taipei, Taiwan<lb/>

	* 通訊作者Corresponding Author: 邱銘心Ming-Hsin Phoebe Chiu, E-mail:
	<email>phoebechiu@ntnu.edu.tw<lb/></email>

	providing physical therapy, in order to improve their quality of life and prognosis. When they discover<lb/> their child&apos;s disease is incurable, primary caregivers need information about social welfare and their<lb/> child&apos;s future. The main source of medical care information is provided by hospitals and patient-<lb/>support organizations. Regarding information behavior, primary caregivers employ the information<lb/> which they obtain and they either check the information they obtain with a professional authority,<lb/> multiple sources, or compare it with patient experience to validate if the information is accurate or not.<lb/> Finally, primary caregivers are glad to share what they find with other families that have children with<lb/> a rare disease. They may use different ways of sharing information such as the Internet or face to face.<lb/>

	Keywords:
	Rare Diseases; Children and Adolescents; Primary Caregivers; Information Needs;<lb/> Information Behaviors

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
