<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="j43-2"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>圖書資訊學刊 第14卷第2期 (2016.12) 頁21-57<lb/></reference>

	<idno>doi:10.6182/jlis.2016.14(2).021<lb/></idno>
    
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>電影的情緒療癒效用研究-以失戀之大學生為例<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>
	
	
	A Qualitative Study on the Emotional Healing Efficacy of<lb/> Movies for Undergraduates Suffering Breakups<lb/> 
	

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>陳書梅 1 </docAuthor>
	</byline>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>葉瑋妮 2<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>
    Chen Su-may Sheih 1 , Wei-Ni Yeh 2<lb/>

	摘 要 
	<div type="abstract">失戀係最常困擾大學生的情緒問題之一。大學生在遭遇分手事件時，易衍生負面情 緒，以致影響心理健康，嚴重者甚至會引發社會問題。準此，如何協助失戀大學生走出情 緒低潮，已成為亟需關注的議題。而觀賞適當的電影有助於舒緩負面情緒，此即為「電影 療法」之應用。本研究運用內容分析法，初步挑選劇情與愛情關係結束相關的電影，繼而 徵求14位失戀大學生，對其進行兩次半結構式深度訪談，並媒合一部電影供彼等觀賞。訪 談目的在於了解受訪者之分手原因與情緒困擾問題，並探討受訪者所觀賞的電影，是否能 對其產生認同、淨化、領悟的情緒療癒效用，及其影響因素為何。研究結果顯示，最多受訪 大學生因「欲與對方維持關係之依附程度不同」而分手；且遭遇「因分手而感到空虛孤寂」 之情緒困擾問題者最多。同時，14部受訪者觀賞的電影，皆能使之產生完整情緒療癒效用。 此外，電影讓受訪者達致不同程度情緒療癒效用的影響因素，包括「觀影者個人背景與主角 相似」、「角色表達情緒方式外放」以及「角色呈現具體解決問題的方式」等三項。<lb/> 關鍵字： 電影療法、情緒療癒、失戀、大學生、發展性書目療法 </div>
	Abstract<lb/>
	Breakups with significant others are among the main reasons for emotional disturbance problems<lb/> in Taiwanese undergraduates. Most undergraduates lack emotional regulation; therefore, their negative<lb/> emotions can easily accumulate, influencing their mental health. Exacerbating these effects, the<lb/> accumulation of negative emotions can lead to social problems. Therefore, helping undergraduates<lb/> appropriately cope with negative emotions generated by breakups is a topic worth exploring.<lb/>
     1
	<byline>
	<affiliation> 國立臺灣大學圖書資訊學系<lb/> </affiliation>
	</byline>
	Department of Library and Information Science, National Taiwan University,


	Taipei, Taiwan<lb/>
    2 
	<byline>
	<affiliation>中華民國文化部文化交流司<lb/> </affiliation>
	</byline>
	Department of Cultural Exchange, Ministry of Culture,
	

	New Taipei, Taiwan<lb/>

	* 通訊作者Corresponding Author: 陳書梅Chen Su-may Sheih, E-mail:
	<email>synn@ntu.edu.tw<lb/></email>

	Movie therapy involves watching appropriate movies for soothing negative emotions. To<lb/> investigate the emotional healing efficacy of movies, this study employed content analysis to select<lb/> movies about breakups and recruited 14 undergraduates suffering from breakups. Semi-structured<lb/> in-depth interviews were conducted after the subjects viewed one of the movies, and the emotional<lb/> healing efficacy of movies was analyzed based on whether the subjects experienced the processes of<lb/> identification, catharsis, and insight.<lb/> The findings indicated that 14 movies had emotional healing efficacy. The subjects experienced<lb/> emotional healing from movies that contained three critical elements: similarity of backgrounds<lb/> between the viewer and the movie characters, the extroversive expression of the movie characters&apos;<lb/> emotions, and the characters&apos; demonstration of concrete solutions to the problems.<lb/>

	Keywords:
	Movie Therapy; Emotional Healing; Breakup; Undergraduate; Developmental Bibliotherapy

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
