<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="j45-4"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>圖書資訊學刊 第15卷第2期 (2017.12) 頁67-99<lb/></reference>

	<idno>doi: 10.6182/jlis.2017.15(2).067</idno>

	
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>從資訊來源觀點探討農民資訊尋求行為<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>
    Exploring Farmers&apos; Information Seeking Behavior from the<lb/> Perspectives of Information Channels<lb/> 
	
	
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>張郁蔚 1 邵芷羚 2<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>邵芷羚 2<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>
    Yu-Wei Chang 1 , Jhih-Ling Shao 2<lb/>
	摘 要 
	<div type="abstract">本研究使用深度訪談法及資訊視域圖探討15位臺灣中部地區農民的資訊尋求行為，發 現農民工作角色的增加使得所需的資訊種類相當多樣化，而多樣化的資訊種類係透過六大 類資訊來源取得資訊，其中人際網絡是農民資訊來源的首選，其他農友是最多受訪者優先 考慮對象；其次是農業機構與農民團體，再其次是網路資源，甚少農民會利用圖書館取得 所需資訊。研究發現許多因素相互影響農民選擇資訊來源，加上農民於資訊尋求過程中所 遭遇的困難，建議在農業資訊傳播方面，政府農業相關機關應重視人際網絡對農民傳播農 業資訊的重要性，加強農業推廣人員與農民的溝通，另要提供符合農民需求的訓練課程與 注意開課時間的適當性，以及改善農民的資訊素養能力。<lb/></div> 
	關鍵字： 
	<keyword>農民、資訊來源、資訊尋求行為、農業資訊傳播 </keyword>
	Abstract<lb/>
	This study used an in-depth interview and information horizon maps to investigate information<lb/> seeking behavior of 15 farmers in Central Taiwan. The results show that increased work roles led to<lb/> more categories of information needed by farmers. Six types of information sources were used by<lb/> farmers to obtain agricultural information. Interpersonal network was the most preferred information<lb/> source by farmers. Especially, most farmers contacted other farmers first. Requesting agricultural<lb/> organizations and farmer groups was the second preferred information source, followed by searching<lb/> the Internet. Few farmers obtained information from libraries. Several factors affected farmers to select<lb/> information sources. In addition, barriers to seeking agricultural information faced by farmers were<lb/> identified. To strengthen the effect of agricultural information dissemination, some suggestions were<lb/> made. Government agencies related to agriculture should focus the greatest influence of interpersonal<lb/> network on disseminating agriculture information and improve the communication between<lb/> agricultural extension agents and farmers. The content and time of agricultural courses were set based<lb/> on farmers&apos; needs. Improving farmers&apos; information literacy is an essential issue as well.<lb/>

	Keywords:
	Farmer; Information Source; Information Seeking Behavior; Agricultural Information Dissemination<lb/>
    1
	<byline>
	<affiliation> 國立臺灣大學圖書資訊學系<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>
	Department of Library and Information Science, National Taiwan University,
	

	Taipei, Taiwan<lb/>
    2
	<byline>
	<affiliation> 國立臺灣大學農業陳列館<lb/> </affiliation>
	</byline>
	Agricultural Exhibition Hall, National Taiwan University,
	

	Taipei, Taiwan<lb/>

	* 通訊作者Corresponding Author: 張郁蔚Yu-Wei Chang, E-mail:
	<email>yuweichang2013@ntu.edu.tw</email>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
