<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="j46-5"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>圖書資訊學刊 第16卷第1期 (2018.6) 頁109-139<lb/></reference>

	<idno>doi: 10.6182/jlis.201806_16(1).109</idno>

	
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>合作學習情境中師資培育生教案發展之協作資訊行為<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>
    
	Preservice Teachers&apos; Collaborative Information Behavior while<lb/> Developing Curriculum in Cooperative Learning Contexts<lb/>
	
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>楊琬琳 1 </docAuthor>
	</byline>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>蔡天怡 2<lb/> </docAuthor>
	</byline>
    Wan-Lin Yang 1 , Tien-I Tsai 2<lb/>

	摘 要 
	<div type="abstract">本研究旨在探究師資生於發展教案之協作資訊行為及其合作經驗，針對一所研究型大 學三門以合作發展教案為目標之課程學生進行問卷調查，再從70份有效問卷之參與者中招 募14位師資生進行深度訪談。研究結果顯示，整體而言，師資生進行共同瀏覽、搜尋與組 織資訊等明確的協作資訊行為大多僅發生於合作任務分工之前。合作歷程中，協作資訊行 為發生頻率高者多來自分工與合作並重之組別，且以扮演協調者角色的師資生及投入任務 相關社交時間較多者尤然。具備上述特質的師資生，往往也運用較多種類之線上工具，其 感知合作成果亦較理想。本研究據此針對促成合作學習與協作資訊行為教學實務、師資培 育實務，及未來研究三方面提出具體建議。<lb/></div>
	關鍵字： 
	<keyword>資訊行為、協作資訊行為、合作學習、教案發展、師資培育 </keyword>
	Abstract<lb/>
	The purpose of this study is to examine the collaborative information behavior (CIB) and<lb/> experiences of preservice teachers while developing curriculum in small groups. A survey was<lb/> conducted with 70 students from three courses in a teacher preparation program in Taiwan, and<lb/> followed up with 14 voluntary interviews among survey participants. The three courses that<lb/> participants were taking share the same learning goal-promoting preservice teachers&apos; ability to<lb/> develop curriculum through teamwork. Results show that specific CIBs, such as co-browse and co-<lb/>search, only occurred prior to labor-distribution stage. In the process of curriculum development,<lb/> preservice teachers who exhibited CIB more frequently typically came from teamwork/labor-<lb/>distribution balanced groups, and tended to use a wider variety of online tools; compared to their low-<lb/>frequency CIB counterparts, high-frequency CIB students also held more positive attitudes towards<lb/> their perceived project outcome. Suggestions for facilitating cooperative learning, for future teacher<lb/> education, as well as for future research, are provided based on the findings of the present study.<lb/>

	Keywords:
	Information Behavior; Collaborative Information Behavior; Cooperative Learning;<lb/> Curriculum Development; Teacher Education<lb/>
    1
	<byline>
	<affiliation> 國立成功大學師資培育中心<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>
	Center for Teacher Education, National Cheng Kung University,
	

	Tainan, Taiwan<lb/>
    2 
	<byline>
	<affiliation>國立臺灣大學圖書資訊學系<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>
	Department of Library and Information Science, National Taiwan University,
	

	Taipei, Taiwan<lb/>

	* 通訊作者Corresponding Author: 蔡天怡Tien-I Tsai, E-mail:
	<email>titsai@ntu.edu.tw</email>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
