<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="j47-4"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>圖書資訊學刊 第16卷第2期 (2018.12) 頁103-133<lb/></reference>

	<idno>doi: 10.6182/jlis.201812_16(2).103</idno>

	
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>資訊時代公共圖書館兒童服務館員職能探討<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>
    
	Competencies of Children&apos;s Librarians in Public Libraries<lb/> in the Information Age<lb/>

     
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>彭于萍 1<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>
    Yu-Ping Peng 1<lb/>
	摘 要 
	<div type="abstract">公共圖書館面臨資訊環境變遷帶來的發展及創新，對公共圖書館兒童服務館員之知識 與技能內涵及需求造成顯著影響，圖書館領導者需要兒童服務館員展現較佳職能以因應環 境變化。本研究首先藉由文獻探討瞭解目前國內外兒童服務館員職能研究概況，之後分別 陳述職能模式意涵與價值、圖書資訊學領域職能研究發展概況、資訊時代公共圖書館兒童 服務之角色及價值，以及國內外兒童服務館員職能模式發展概況，再透過內容分析法，探 究公共圖書館兒童服務館員所需具備之專業知識技能、一般知識技能，以及態度及人格特<lb/> 質，歸納整理出資訊時代公共圖書館兒童服務館員職能概念性架構(詳見表一)，期盼研 究結果能有助於未來發展國內資訊時代公共圖書館兒童服務館員職能發展實務之參考。<lb/></div>
	關鍵字： 
	<keyword>職能、兒童服務館員、公共圖書館 </keyword>
	Abstract<lb/>
	The development and innovation of information technologies in recent years have influenced<lb/> service models used in public libraries. To respond to the changing library environment in an<lb/> information era, library leaders require librarians to exhibit proper competencies to keep up with<lb/> rapidly changing environments. This study explored the current researches on the competencies<lb/> children&apos;s librarians, and then stated the meaning and value of the competency model, research on<lb/> competency and competency models in library and information science, and the role and value of<lb/> children&apos;s services in the public library during the information age, and previous competency models<lb/> for children&apos;s librarians in public libraries in the information age. Through content analysis, the study<lb/> explores the special knowledge and skills, general knowledge and skills, as well as the attitudes and<lb/> characteristics required by children&apos;s librarians working in public libraries. Subsequently, this study<lb/> referred to multidimensional competency conceptual framework for children&apos;s librarians working in<lb/> public libraries (See Table 1 for details). Finally, the findings of this study may serve as a reference to<lb/> assist in the development of competency conceptual framework and practice related to competency<lb/> development among children&apos;s librarians working in public libraries in the information age.<lb/>

	Keywords:
	Competency; Children&apos;s Librarian; Public Library<lb/>
    1
	<byline>
	<affiliation> 輔仁大學圖書資訊學系<lb/> </affiliation>
	</byline>
	Department of Library and Information Science, Fu Jen Catholic University,
	

	New Taipei, Taiwan<lb/>

	E-mail:
	<email>084361@mail.fju.edu.tw</email>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
