<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="j47-5" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			<reference>
				圖書資訊學刊 第16卷第2期 (2018.12) 頁135-164
				<lb />
			</reference>

			<idno>doi: 10.6182/jlis.201812_16(2).135</idno>


			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>
					從社會支持觀點探討愛滋線上匿名諮詢問答
					<lb />
				</titlePart>
			</docTitle>
			Exploring Anonymous Online AIDS Q&amp;A Services:
			<lb />
			A Social Support Perspective
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					宜琳 1 
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			<byline>
			<docAuthor>邱銘心 2<lb /></docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Yi-Ling Wen 1 , Ming-Hsin Phoebe Chiu 2
			<lb />
			摘 要
			<div type="abstract">
				隨著醫療技術進步，愛滋病逐漸慢性病化，感染者所關心的議題逐漸轉為權益相關； 但因疾病之特殊性，大部分感染者注重其隱私，因而大多使用網際網路取得資訊。本研究 以露德協會線上匿名留言板為研究對象，希望瞭解現今國內愛滋病相關網站所提供的愛滋 病相關資訊是否滿足愛滋病友需求，並透過社會支持觀點分析愛滋匿名留言板之留言與回 覆，探討留言板中的需求與提供之資訊是否相符；希冀能協助社會支持提供者瞭解目前感 染者主要需求資訊。
				<lb />
			</div>
			關鍵字：
			<keyword>社會支持、愛滋病、線上匿名諮詢問答、內容分析 </keyword>
			Abstract
			<lb />
			Due to medical advancement and innovation, AIDS is gradually becoming a chronic disease.
			<lb />
			The infected people are now more concerned about the patient rights. Nonetheless, because AIDS
			<lb />
			is in some ways a unique disease due to its being concerned with the most intimate and private part
			<lb />
			of a patient&apos;s life, those with AIDS prefer to search for information online because this affords them
			<lb />
			privacy and confidentiality. Therefore, this study aims to explore an anonymous online AIDS question
			<lb />
			and answer (Q&amp;A) service from the social support perspective. The purpose of this study is to find
			<lb />
			out whether the AIDS information provided by the website&apos;s Q&amp;A service in Taiwan satisfy the needs
			<lb />
			of the patients and to discover whether the needs of patients match the information provided from the
			<lb />
			comments on websites. This study provides insights into and understanding of the information needs
			<lb />
			of patients with HIV infection or AIDS from the perspective of social support.
			<lb />
			Keywords:
	Social Support; AIDS; Online Anonymous Q&amp;A Service; Content Analysis
			<lb />
			
			1,2
			<byline>
				<affiliation>
					國立臺灣師範大學圖書資訊學研究所
					<lb />
				</affiliation>
			</byline>
			Graduate Institute of Library and Information Studies, National Taiwan Normal University,
			<lb />
			Taipei, Taiwan
			<lb />
			* 通訊作者Corresponding Author: 邱銘心Ming-Hsin Phoebe Chiu, E-mail:
			<email>phoebechiu@ntnu.edu.tw</email>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>