<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="j48-5"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>圖書資訊學刊 第17卷第1期 (2019.6) 頁151-183<lb/></reference>

	<idno>doi: 10.6182/jlis.201906_17(1).151<lb/></idno>

	

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>社群媒體之食品安全風險溝通行為研究-<lb/>以新浪微博為例 1<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>
    Food Safety Risk Communication Behavior on Social Media:<lb/> The Case of Sina Weibo<lb/> 
	
	
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>胡逸翮 2 <lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>岳修平 2,3</docAuthor>
	</byline>
    Yi-He Hu 2 , Hsiu-Ping Yueh 2,3<lb/>
	摘 要 
	<div type="abstract">近年來中國食品安全事件層出不窮，社群媒體因具備社群關係網絡串聯及立即互動優 勢，往往成為公眾參與風險溝通的主要管道。但民眾於社群媒體中的互動是否真實反映或 實踐有效風險溝通行為，為值得深入探討之議題。本研究選取2016年中國兩起重大食安事<lb/> 件在新浪微博之1,303則貼文，以內容分析法進行分析其中風險溝通的參與主體、貼文內 容與消息來源、互動性、外部網站連結及多媒體使用狀況。結果顯示民眾於微博之風險溝 通具良好互動性、充分利用多媒體，但也存在參與主體及消息來源單一、主題廣度不足、 科學傳播匱乏、負面情緒主導及資訊品質不一等問題。因兩事件性質不盡相同，官方處理 方式與民眾風險溝通行為表現亦有差異，值得後續研究與實務單位參考。<lb/></div>
	關鍵字： 
	<keyword>社群媒體、風險溝通、食品安全、內容分析、微博 </keyword>
	Abstract<lb/>
	This study aims to investigate the role of social media in food safety risk communication. Taking<lb/> two major crisis events happened in 2016 in China, this study adopted content analysis method to<lb/> analyze the information related to these two events and public use behavior on the &quot;Sina Weibo.&quot; In sum,<lb/> 1,303 posts were analyzed; this study found that although risk communication in Weibo has been proved<lb/> highly interactive and make full use of multimedia, the application of social media still has adverse<lb/> respects such as unbalanced participation, single information source, scarcity of science communication,<lb/> vast negative emotion expression and variety information quality. Furthermore, the findings shown that<lb/> due to the difference of the two events, the government presented different risk management strategies,<lb/> and resulting in differences between how public used social media for risk communication. The study<lb/> recommended future researches to look into this phenomenon and provided suggestions for practice.<lb/>

	Keywords:
	Social Media; Risk Communication; Food Safety; Content Analysis; Microblog<lb/>

	
	1 本文修改自筆者於「2018年中華傳播學會年會暨研討會」發表之論文〈社交媒體中食品安全風<lb/> 險溝通與資訊行為研究〉<lb/> 
	2
	<byline>
	<affiliation> 國立臺灣大學生物產業傳播暨發展學系<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>
	
	Department of Bio-Industry Communication and Development, National Taiwan University,
	

	Taipei, Taiwan<lb/>
    3
	<byline>
	<affiliation> 國立臺灣大學心理系<lb/> </affiliation>
	</byline>
	Department of Psychology, National Taiwan University,
	

	Taipei, Taiwan<lb/>

	* 通訊作者Corresponding Author: 岳修平Hsiu-Ping Yueh, E-mail:
	<email>yueh@ntu.edu.tw</email>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
