<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="j48-4"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>圖書資訊學刊 第17卷第1期 (2019.6) 頁117-149<lb/></reference>

	<idno>doi: 10.6182/jlis.201906_17(1).117<lb/></idno>

	
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>樂齡讀者對公共圖書館樂齡學習中心 服務環境偏好研究<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

    Senior Citizens&apos; Servicescape Preferences Regarding Senior<lb/> Active Learning Centers in the Public Libraries<lb/>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>林芷君 1 </docAuthor>
	</byline>
	<byline>
	<docAuthor>邱銘心 2<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>
     Chih-Chun Lin 1 , Ming-Hsin Phoebe Chiu 2<lb/>
	摘 要 
	<div type="abstract">公共圖書館為地方的知識門戶，其設計應反映圖書館服務的功能，並能靈活適應服務 工作的興革，我國自1993年即正式邁入高齡化社會，圖書館樂齡專屬區域的服務環境設 計更顯重要。本研究以臺北市立圖書館之6所樂齡學習中心為研究場域，並以其所屬樂齡 讀者為研究對象，選擇照片引談法為資料蒐集方法，共訪談24位受訪者，徵集到284張照 片，藉此透過照片及訪談瞭解樂齡讀者使用圖書館樂齡中心之服務環境因素偏好，以期能 作為未來公共圖書館樂齡專屬區域規劃之參考。<lb/></div> 
	
	關鍵字： 
	<keyword>樂齡服務、樂齡學習中心、公共圖書館、服務環境、照片引談法 </keyword>
	Abstract<lb/>
	Public libraries are viewed as the local gateway to knowledge, therefore the design of public<lb/> libraries should reflect its function for providing services and adapt the change of environment. Since<lb/> 1993, Taiwan has been included as one of the aging societies, as a result, the servicescape design of<lb/> the senior-exclusive area in libraries becomes a significant issue.<lb/> With this regard, this study aims to understand from the senior users&apos; perspective of the way that<lb/> servicescape should be designed. This study used &quot;Photo-elicitation&quot; as its data collection method.<lb/> Twenty-four senior users, who are the patrons of Senior Active Learning Centers in Taipei Public<lb/> Library were interviewed, and a total of 284 photographs were solicited and used as data source. In<lb/> addition to exploring senior users&apos; preference of servicescape, this study also attempts to construct a<lb/> framework that serves as guidance for designing and evaluating servicescape in public libraries.<lb/>

	Keywords:
	Senior Service; Senior Active Learning Center; Public Libraries; Servicescape;<lb/> Photo Elicitation<lb/>

	1,2 
	<byline>
	<affiliation>國立臺灣師範大學圖書資訊學研究所<lb/> </affiliation>
	</byline>
	Graduate Institute of Library and Information Studies, National Taiwan Normal University,
	

	Taipei, Taiwan<lb/>

	* 通訊作者Corresponding Author: 邱銘心Ming-Hsin Phoebe Chiu, E-mail:
	<email>phoebechiu@ntnu.edu.tw</email>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
