<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="86_5" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			Spotify Last.fm YouTube Vimeo
			<lb />
			A Comparative Usability Study of Four Audio and Video Streaming
			<lb />
			Platforms: Spotify, Last.fm, YouTube, and Vimeo
	
	
			<lb />
			Yun Hsiao
	

	Abstract
			<div type="abstract">
				使用影音串流平台已是人們日常休閒之一。此類平台提供哪些功能，操作流程如何設 計，介面如何呈現，最直覺友善、便於使用？都是值得探究的議題，但國內外在這些方面
				<lb />
				研究卻不多。故本研究採取好用性研究方法，運用 Spotify、Last.fm、YouTube 及 Vimeo 四個影音串流平台，針對不同平台相同功能之操作方式進行評估，以期透過觀察、受測者 回饋與資料分析，得知功能操作流程問題，瞭解使用者對好用平台之期待，提出改善建議， 並建構一兼具效益、效率、滿意度與娛樂性之好用影音串流平台模型。
				<lb />
			</div>
			A variety of audio and video streaming platforms, equipped with streaming technology
			<lb />
			that supports instant usage of media resources in the process of downloading, have become a
			<lb />
			popular part of daily entertainments. Current researches on streaming platforms mostly focus on
			<lb />
			the technical dimension of streaming technology, with much less attention to the usability
			<lb />
			dimension of streaming operation. Nevertheless, issues concerning platform design and
			<lb />
			user-friendly operation are worthy of further exploration. This study selects four currently most
			<lb />
			popular audio and video streaming platforms as research subjects, including Spotify, Last.fm,
			<lb />
			YouTube, and Vimeo. To examine the usability of these platforms, 12 users were arranged to
			<lb />


			<byline>
				<affiliation>
					 國立臺灣大學圖書資訊學系
					<lb />
				</affiliation>
			</byline>
			大學部學生
		 Undergraduate Student, Department of Library &amp; Information Science, National Taiwan University
			<lb />
			E-mail:
			<email>
				yunh26@gmail.com
				<lb />
			</email>

			<reference>
				圖資與檔案學刊
				<lb />
				7:1=86 (June &apos;15) 97-131
				<lb />
			</reference>

			<idno>
				DOI: 10.6575/JILA.2015.86.05
				<lb />
			</idno>
			perform 16 tasks by alternatively applying streaming functions provided on the platforms. Their
			<lb />
			activities and self-report data are observed and analyzed. Research results indicate some
			<lb />
			drawbacks in streaming operations as well as users&apos; expectation for streaming usability. Based
			<lb />
			on the research results, this study proposes some suggestions for improving streaming platform
			<lb />
			design, and furthermore configures a model of streaming platform that incorporates effective,
			<lb />
			efficient, enjoyable, and usable audio and video streaming services.
			<lb />
			關鍵詞 Keyword
			<lb />

			<keyword>
				好用性評估 影音串流平台 使用者研究
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			Usability study；Audio and video streaming platform；User study
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>