<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="87_3" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			Establishment of an E-Portfolio System for Professional Development:
			<lb />
			A Case Study of Library Association of the Republic of China (Taiwan) 
			<lb />
			Meng-Yi Lin 
			<lb />
			Hao-Ren Ke
	

	Abstract
			<div type="abstract">
				近年來臺灣已有許多大專校院將電子化歷程檔案運用於學生學習，但鮮少以專業發展為 取向之電子化歷程檔案供專業從業人員彙整、展示其於專業領域內的各項紀錄與成果。本研 究依循系統開發生命週期瀑布模式，設計並建置屬於中華民國圖書館學會之電子化歷程檔案 系統，並將內容以資源描述框架格式轉換成為鏈結資料，藉此電子化歷程檔案擁有者能將分 散於各處的歷程檔案加以連結與整合。最後，網路問卷調查結果顯示多數使用者對本系統接 受與滿意度頗高。
				<lb />
			</div>
			In recent years, there have been many e-Portfolio systems in Taiwan implemented for students&apos;
			<lb />
			learning in universities yet rarely for professional development. This study aims to design and
			<lb />
			
			<byline>
				<affiliation> 國立臺灣師範大學圖書資訊學研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			碩士生
			<lb />
			MA Student, Graduate Institute of Library and Information Studies,
			<lb />
			National Taiwan Normal University
			<lb />
			E-mail：
			<email>
				oldwetdream@gmail.com
				<lb />
			</email>
			
			<byline>
				<affiliation> 國立臺灣師範大學圖書資訊學研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			教授兼圖書館館長
			<lb />
			Professor &amp; University Librarian, Graduate Institute of Library and Information Studies, National
			<lb />
			Taiwan Normal University
			<lb />
			E-mail：
			<email>
				clavenke@ntnu.edu.tw
				<lb />
			</email>

			<reference>
				圖資與檔案學刊
				<lb />
				7:2=87 (Dec &apos;15) 54-76
				<lb />
			</reference>

			<idno>
				DOI: 10.6575/JILA.2015.87.03
				<lb />
			</idno>
			establish an e-Portfolio system for professional development. Five steps of System Development
			<lb />
			Life Cycle (SDLC) were adopted to build an e-Portfolio system for members of Library Association
			<lb />
			of the Republic of China (Taiwan). In addition, the open-source content management system,
			<lb />
			Drupal, was employed as the development tool. The data in this e-Portfolio system were converted
			<lb />
			into linked data with Resource Description Framework (RDF). Through the system, e-Portfolio
			<lb />
			owners can link and integrate all of their own e-Portfolios dispersed everywhere. Finally, this study
			<lb />
			evaluated the e-Portfolio system with an online questionnaire to understand users&apos; satisfaction with
			<lb />
			the functions and the whole system. The results showed that most users had high acceptance and
			<lb />
			satisfaction with the system.
			<lb />
			關鍵詞 Keyword
			<lb />
			<keyword>
				電子化歷程檔案 專業發展 系統開發生命週期瀑布模式 鏈結資料
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			e-Portfolio；Professional development；System Development Life Cycle；Linked Data
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>