<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="87_4" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			A Study on the Beijing Book Markets in Ming Dynasty 
			<lb />
			Ching-Cheng Huang
	

	Abstract
			<div type="abstract">
				明代北京為全國的政治、經濟、文化、交通中心，其書市之大，他處無一可比。尤其明 初統治者對圖書事業的重視，以及明代中葉以後城市經濟空前發達，為圖書從業者創造了有 利的發展條件。此外，明代刻書事業的發達，讓當時重要的書坊集中地北京，很自然地形成 了圖書市場，加上來自全國各地的文人士子等重要的書籍消費者匯聚於此，更吸引了大量的 圖書從業者紛紛前來，結行成市。另一方面，私家藏書活動的興盛亦有助於圖書市場的發展， 尤其是中葉以後，國家經濟極度繁榮，社會風氣產生變化，尋常百姓們大多渴望閱讀書籍， 對圖書的需求大幅提升。這些條件，都無形地造就了廣大的圖書商機與消費者群體，讓明代 北京的書籍市場順應歷史潮流，得以開展壯大。
				<lb />
			</div>
			Beijing in the Ming Dynasty was a national political, economic, cultural and transportation
			<lb />
			center, and the book market there was beyond comparison in scale. The rulers in the early Ming
			<lb />
			Dynasty especially attaches the great importance to the book cause, and the unprecedentedly
			<lb />
			prosperous economy of the cities after the middle period of the Ming Dynasty also created favorable
			<lb />
			conditions for the development of book practitioners. In addition, the prosperity of book carving
			<lb />
			industry in Ming Dynasty had made Beijin, where many important bookstores were concentrated at
			<lb />
			the time, form a book market naturally. Since many important, highly-educated book consumers
			<lb />
			throughout the country gathered there, a large number of book companies were attracted to form a
			<lb />
			large-scale industry. On the other hand, the thriving private book collection activity was also
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation> 輔仁大學圖書資訊學系研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			碩士生
			<lb />
			MA Student, Department of Library and Information Science, Fu Jen Catholic University
			<lb />
			E-mail:
			<email>
				kaneee2001@gmail.com
				<lb />
			</email>

			<reference>
				圖資與檔案學刊
				<lb />
				7:2=87 (Dec &apos;15) 77-91
				<lb />
			</reference>

			<idno>
				DOI: 10.6575/JILA.2015.87.04
				<lb />
			</idno>
			beneficial to the development of the book market. After mid-Ming Dynasty, in particular, the
			<lb />
			domestic economy extremely flourished so that the social atmosphere had changed and resulted in
			<lb />
			the great desire of book reading among regular people, which raised the demand for books. All of
			<lb />
			these conditions had invisibly created vast business opportunities as well as consumer groups,
			<lb />
			which enabled the book market of Ming Dynasty in Beijin to be well-adjusted to the trend and
			<lb />
			thrive.
			<lb />
			關鍵詞 Keyword
			<lb />

			<keyword>
				明代 北京 書籍市場 藏書
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			Ming dynasty；Beijing；Book market；Book-collecting
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>