<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="88_5" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			A Research on the System of Master Education in Archival Science
			<lb />
			in Mainland China 
			<lb />
			Yan Zhang 
			<lb />
			Mei-Ling Wang
	

	Abstract
			<div type="abstract">
				中國大陸檔案學碩士教育歷經三十餘年發展已經構建了一個比較完整的體系。本文通過
				<lb />
				網站調查法、網站內容分析法對中國大陸現行 29 所檔案學碩士研究生招生系所網站及中國大 陸檔案學碩士教育相關文獻展開調查，重點分析中國大陸檔案學教育發展簡史、檔案學學科 隸屬及學位授予、檔案學碩士研究生招生系所概況、地理分佈、招生年份、入學考試與畢業 條件、師資與學生概況、培養目標與課程設置等八個方面。研究發現：中國大陸檔案學專業 定位已經從歷史學走向管理學，檔案學碩士生的培養也傾向於「一體化」的教育模式。
				<lb />
			</div>
			A relatively complete system of master education in archival science in mainland China has
			<lb />
			been achieved after more than three decades of development. Through surveys on and content
			<lb />
			analysis of websites, websites of current 29 departments which recruit master in archival science
			<lb />
			and relevant literature on master education in mainland China were researched in this study. The
			<lb />
			study emphasized eight aspects of education development history, subject subordination and
			<lb />
			
			<byline>
				<affiliation>政治大學圖書資訊與檔案學研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			博士候選人
			<lb />
			Ph.D. Candidate, Graduate Institute of Library, Information and Archival Studies National Chengchi University
			<lb />
			E-mail:
			<email>
				zhangyan_suda@126.com
				<lb />
			</email>
			
			<byline>
				<affiliation> 政治大學圖書資訊與檔案學研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			教授
			<lb />
			Professor, Graduate Institute of Library, Information and Archival Studies National Chengchi
			<lb />
			University
			<lb />
			E-mail:
			<email>
				meilingw@nccu.edu.tw
				<lb />
			</email>

			<reference>
				圖資與檔案學刊
				<lb />
				8:1=88 (June &apos;16) 61-90
				<lb />
			</reference>

			<idno>
				DOI: 10.6575/JILA.2016.88.04
				<lb />
			</idno>
			academic degrees, geographic distribution of master-recruiting departments, recruitment years,
			<lb />
			entrance qualification and examination, faculty and students, and curriculums of archival science in
			<lb />
			mainland China. It is found that orientation of archival science in mainland China has been
			<lb />
			transformed from history science to management science. Educational mode of masters in archival
			<lb />
			science is inclined to strengthen basic knowledge and expand horizons.
			<lb />
			關鍵詞 Keyword
			<lb />
			<keyword>
				檔案學教育 中國大陸 專業教育 碩士教育
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			Archival education；Mainland China；Professional education；Master&apos;s degree program
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>