<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="89_2" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			A study on the Social Image of Librarians in Taiwan 
			<lb />
			Cheng-Huang Lin 
			<lb />
			Yi-Zhen He 
	
	Abstract
			<div type="abstract">
				隨著時代的進步、社會環境的變遷，在注重精緻、包裝、品牌的行銷時代中，形象的重 要性更值得關切。本研究主要目的在探討民眾對於圖書館員形象的認知與評價，並進一步探 討影響圖書館員社會形象的因素，以及民眾對圖書館員專業形象與專業期待的看法。因此， 本研究採量化研究，透過網問卷的調查方式收集資料，並以社會大眾為研究對象進行調查。 期透過本研究能夠提高圖書館界對圖書館員形象經營的重視。研究結果發現，民眾心目中的 圖書館員是有耐心的、做事有條理的、友善的、親切的；相對於圖書館員的正面形象，民眾 對圖書館員的實際印象中較為相反的形容詞，分別為有點年紀的、撲克臉、保守的、工作忙 碌等。
				<lb />
			</div>
			As time advances and society changes, the importance of the image is especially worth noting
			<lb />
			in the marketing era with the emphasis of sophistication, packaging, and brand. The main purpose
			<lb />
			
			<byline>
				<affiliation>輔仁大學圖書資訊學系</affiliation>
			</byline>
			助理教授
			<lb />
			Assistant Professor,
	
	Department of Library and Information Science, Fu Jen Catholic University
			<lb />
			E-mail:
			<email>
				042574@mail.fju.edu.tw
				<lb />
			</email>
			
			<byline>
				<affiliation>輔仁大學圖書資訊學系</affiliation>
			</byline>

				碩士生
				<lb />
				MA Student, Department of Library and Information Science, Fu Jen Catholic University
				<lb />
			E-mail:
			<email>
				kiki102460@yahoo.com.tw
				<lb />
			</email>

			<reference>
				圖資與檔案學刊
				<lb />
				8:2=89 (Dec &apos;16) 1-24
				<lb />
			</reference>

			<idno>
				DOI: 10.6575/JILA.2016.89.01
				<lb />
			</idno>
			of this study was to explore public awareness and evaluation towards librarian images, and
			<lb />
			furthermore the factors that have influenced the social images of librarians. Therefore, this study
			<lb />
			used quantitative research with the online questionnaire survey to collect data from the members of
			<lb />
			the public as the research subjects. This research is expected to improve the image of librarians and
			<lb />
			to draw more attention to library management.
			<lb />
			關鍵詞 Keyword
			<lb />
			<keyword>
				圖書館員 社會形象 刻版印象 圖書館員形象
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			Librarian；Social image；Stereotype；Librarian images
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>