<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="89_3" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			A Content Analysis of the Communication Between Archives and
			<lb />
			Users with Facebook 
			<lb />
			Chiao-Min Lin 
			<lb />
			Chyi-Kuan Wang
	

	Abstract
			<div type="abstract">
				隨著網路資訊深入社會大眾生活中，檔案館運用社群媒體傳播館藏資訊與服務日益普
				<lb />
				及，社群網站可促進檔案館與使用者溝通，塑造親和形象。目前檔案館多倚重臉書(Facebook) 網站，經營與使用者之間的資訊交流，臉書載文內容形式與互動策略，將影響使用者對於檔 案館之觀感。故本研究以美國、英國、澳洲國家檔案館以及我國之檔案管理局、國史館與國 立故宮博物院之臉書粉絲專頁為分析對象，針對臉書專頁呈現之資訊與使用者互動情形進行
				<lb />
				網頁內容分析，觀察記錄各館 2015 年 10 月至 12 月間所有貼文之回饋速度、動態更新頻率、 發布內容主題、留言形式與分享程度等特性，探討檔案館經營臉書與使用者互動衍生之優劣 問題，最終歸納結論與建議，提供檔案館經營臉書粉絲專頁之參考。
				<lb />
			</div>
				With the public life deeply immersed in the Internet, it is more popular to take advantage of
				<lb />
				social media to disseminate collection information in archives. Social media can facilitate
				<lb />
			
			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立政治大學圖書資訊與檔案學研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			副教授
			<lb />
			Associate Professor, Graduate
	
	Institute of Library, Information and Archival Studies, National
			<lb />
			Chengchi University
			<lb />
			E-mail:
			<email>
				cmlin@nccu.edu.tw
				<lb />
			</email>
			
			<byline>
				<affiliation> 國立政治大學圖書資訊與檔案學研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			碩士生
			<lb />
			MA Student, Graduate Institute of Library, Information and Archival Studies, National Chengchi University
			<lb />
			E-mail:
			<email>
				mzkw0210@gmail.com
				<lb />
			</email>

			<reference>
				圖資與檔案學刊
				<lb />
				8:2=89 (Dec &apos;16) 25-46
				<lb />
			</reference>

			<idno>
				DOI: 10.6575/JILA.2016.89.02
				<lb />
			</idno>
			communication between archives and users and shape the friendly image of archives. Currently,
			<lb />
			most of the archives have used Facebook to disseminate information with users. The content format
			<lb />
			and the interactive strategies of Facebook utilizaion will affect users&apos; perception of archives. This
			<lb />
			paper focused on content analysis of information presentation and user interaction on pages, and the
			<lb />
			US National Archives, The National Archives of UK, National Archives of Australia, and National
			<lb />
			Archives Administration, Academia Historica, and National Palace Museum in Taiwan

	were taken
			<lb />
			as samples to make comparisions. The immediacy of feedback, update frequency, usefulness of
			<lb />
			information, comment form and sharing features of these archives from October to December, 2015
			<lb />
			were analyzed for discussing the pros and cons of operating Facebook in archives. Finally, the
			<lb />
			conclusions and suggestions will be proposed for archives reference.
			<lb />
			關鍵詞 Keyword
			<lb />
			<keyword>
				社群媒體 臉書 粉絲專頁 檔案館 內容分析
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			Social media；Facebook；Page；Archives；Content analysis
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>