<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="89_4" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			A Study on the Professional Growth from Career Development Process
			<lb />
			of the University Library Superior Catalogers 
			<lb />
			Ming-Chu Lu
	

	Abstract
			<div type="abstract">
				本研究藉由探討編目館員的職涯發展，了解編目館員面對職涯機會的選擇、規劃，各階 段的學習與蛻變，探討職涯過程中正式的編目教育、繼續教育和職場的非正式學習對專業成
				<lb />
				長的影響。國家圖書館於 2009 至 2011 年選拔三屆共 30 位圖書館績優編目工作人員，本研究
				<lb />
				資料來自其中 14 位大學圖書館績優編目館員之深度訪談結果。本研究根據這些深度訪談資料
				<lb />
				歸納出四個結論：(1) 績優編目館員多數因大學聯考分數落點就讀圖書資訊學系，但在學時即
				<lb />
				已有擔任圖書館員之意願，並於進入職場後逐漸學習根據個人意願規劃職涯；(2) 績優編目館
				<lb />
				員雖然肯定大學編目教育，但咸認良好的實習經驗可建構館員專業知能與信心；(3) 編目館員 之職場學習重視以一對一的帶領方式、對繼續教育的需求與管道因個人需求與工作單位政策
				<lb />
				而異，職涯發展路徑以員額規模較大之大學圖書館最具發展性；(4) 績優編目館員追求工作的 完美與個人之成就感，秉持學習、創新的態度執行業務，發展出資訊組織專業職務與資訊科 技管理能力。最後，本研究針對圖書資訊學教育、大學圖書館、圖書資訊學專業學會、國家 圖書館與編目館員提出建議。
				<lb />
			</div>

				This study examines the career development of library catalogers with outstanding
				<lb />
				performance in order to understand their career opportunities, career planning, learning and
				<lb />
				transformation at each stage, and to explore the influence of formal cataloging education, continuing
				<lb />
			
			<byline>
				<affiliation>玄奘大學廣播與電視新聞學系</affiliation>
			</byline>
			助理教授
			<lb />
			Assistant Professor,
	
	Department of Broadcasting and Journalism, Hsuan Chuang University
			<lb />
			E-mail:
			<email>
				ming8810@gmail.com
				<lb />
			</email>

			<reference>
				圖資與檔案學刊
				<lb />
				8:2=89 (Dec &apos;16) 47-76
				<lb />
			</reference>

			<idno>
				DOI: 10.6575/JILA.2016.89.03
				<lb />
			</idno>
			education, and informal workplace learning on their professional growth. The data for this study
			<lb />
			comes from in-depth interviews with 14 university library catalogers out of the 30 library catalogers
			<lb />
			elected and awarded by the National Central Library from 2009 to 2011 for their outstanding
			<lb />
			performance.
			<lb />
			The in-depth interviews suggest four conclusions: (1) although most of the catalogers majored
			<lb />
			in library science due to their University Entrance Exam scores, they were willing to become
			<lb />
			librarians during their college years and, after graduating from college, gradually focused on career
			<lb />
			development; (2) catalogers think highly of their university education, and consider the training
			<lb />
			received during their internships important for instilling in them a sense of professionalism and
			<lb />
			confidence at work; (3) catalogers are usually trained in the workplace with a one-on-one coaching
			<lb />
			model; in addition, their learning needs and opportunities for continuing education depend on their
			<lb />
			personal desires as well as institutional policies, with catalogers working at large university libraries
			<lb />
			having the most opportunities for career development; (4) outstanding catalogers always pursue
			<lb />
			excellence and achievement at work, and their constant learning and innovative attitude helps them
			<lb />
			increase their professional competence in information technology and management.
			<lb />
			Finally, this study makes several suggestions to library science education, university libraries,
			<lb />
			the library science associations, the National Central Library, and cataloguers.
			<lb />
			關鍵詞 Keyword
			<lb />
			<keyword>
				績優編目館員 職涯發展 專業成長 職涯發展指南
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			Cataloger with outstanding performance；Career development；Professional growth；
			<lb />
			Career guidance
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>