<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="90_5" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			(Book Review)
			<lb />
			From Book Selection to Collection Development: A Review of
			<lb />
			Collection Development and Management with Thoughts on
			<lb />
			Establishing a Diverse Collection for a New Era
	

	 
			<lb />
			Kun-Hsien Tseng
			<lb />
			王梅玲、范豪英、林呈潢、張郁蔚(2016)。館藏
			<lb />
			發展與管理。新北市：華藝學術出版。(ISBN
			<lb />
			9789864371198)
			<lb />
			
			<byline>
				<affiliation>國家圖書館出版中心</affiliation>
			</byline>
			主任
			<lb />
			Director, Publications Center,
	

	National Central Library, Taiwan
			<lb />
			E-mail:
			<email>
				tkh@ncl.edu.tw
				<lb />
			</email>

			<reference>
				圖資與檔案學刊
				<lb />
				9:1=90 (June &apos;17) 52-67
				<lb />
			</reference>

			<idno>DOI: 10.6575/JILA.2017.90.04</idno>
			Abstract
			<lb />
			<div type="abstract">
				《館藏發展與管理》 (以下簡稱本書)於 2016 年 9 月出版。為我國繼吳明德教授所著《館
				<lb />
				藏發展》(1991)後，睽別 26 年第一本完整探討新世代圖書館館藏發展相關理論與實務的鉅 著。本書內容涵蓋館藏發展與管理概論、學術傳播與出版、館藏發展與管理政策、圖書資料 選擇、圖書資料採訪、電子館藏發展與管理、社區分析與館藏行銷、館藏淘汰、館藏評鑑、
				<lb />
				資料保存與維護、館藏發展組織與合作等 11 章。本文即以此為基礎，分別介紹自 1972 年以 來臺灣出版有關於「館藏發展」及「圖書資料選擇與採訪」兩個主題的專書出版概況，以及
				<lb />
				本書在作者群、內容簡介、編輯體例上，與《館藏發展》、《圖書資訊選擇與採訪》(王梅
				<lb />
				玲等編著)兩書之比較分析，以探討本書的特色及優缺點。最後，提出新時代多元化館藏建 立的一些發想。
				<lb />
			</div>
			The book Collection Development and Management (hereafter named the Book) was
			<lb />
			published in September 2016. Since Professor Wu Mingde&apos;s Library Collection Development
			<lb />
			was published in 1991, the Book is the first significant study of library collection development
			<lb />
			theory and practice in the new generation. The Book offers a comprehensive description of
			<lb />
			library collection development and management, academic communication and publishing,
			<lb />
			collection development and management policy, book materials selection and acquisition,
			<lb />
			electronic resources development and management, community analysis and collection
			<lb />
			marketing, collection weeding out, collection evaluation, preservation and maintenance, and the
			<lb />
			oversight of collection development and cooperation, in 11 chapters.
			<lb />
			Based on the Book, this article reviews the publication about book selection and acquisition
			<lb />
			and collection development in Taiwan since 1972, with a comparative analysis of the Book&apos;s
			<lb />
			authors, contents and organization, as well as a comparative analysis with Library Collection
			<lb />
			Development by Wu Mingde and Library Materials Selection and Acquisition by Wang Meiling, to
			<lb />
			assess their characteristics, strengths and weaknesses. Finally, this article puts forward some ideas
			<lb />
			on establishing diverse collections for a new era.
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>