<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="91_3" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			The Ethical Decision on Information Issues of College Students:
			<lb />
			A Longitudinal Research 
			<lb />
			Tao-Ming Chuang
	

	Abstract
			<div type="abstract">
				臺灣從義務教育到高等教育推行資訊素養教育已有相當基礎，今日學生善於利用各種資 訊工具獲取各類資訊，來滿足人際溝通與訊息傳播等需求。但當學生面對網路訊息傳播、學 術抄襲或智慧著作權議題的對與錯倫理判斷時，台灣大學生會做出何種選擇？學生是採取直 覺選擇或有邏輯性的理性抉擇？本研究目的在了解大學生資訊倫理議題的個人倫理選擇。研
				<lb />
				究對象以世新大學資訊傳播學系學生為主，以四年為一周期進行縱貫式研究，分別在 2008 年、
				<lb />
				2013 年及 2017 年進行資訊倫理個案問卷調查。依據三次調查研究比較發現，不同時期的大學 生、性別與年齡學生對資訊倫理議題的抉擇有所不同。特別在誠實考試部分，越年輕世代的 學生支持率越高。
				<lb />
			</div>
			The promotion of information literacy in schools, colleges, and universities has been a
			<lb />
			foundation of the Taiwan education system. In a modern information society, university students
			<lb />
			remarkably depend on information and communication technology to gather, organize, and utilize
			<lb />
			information to complete their academic works. However, when a conflict of interests happened in
			<lb />
			information gathering and usage, students may be bothered about how making a good choice. The
			<lb />
			purpose of this study is to understand university students how to make ethical decisions on
			<lb />
			information issues, such as information transfer and usage, academic plagiarism, and academic ethics.
			<lb />
			A questionnaire survey, composed of five information cases, was conducted in 2008, 2013 and 2017,
			<lb />
			to the students of Department of Information and Communications at the Shih Hsin University in
	
			<byline>
				<affiliation>世新大學資訊傳播學系</affiliation>
			</byline>
			副教授
			<lb />
			Associate Professor,
	
	Department of Information and Communications, Shih Hsin University
			<lb />
			E-mail:
			<email>
				tmchuang@cc.shu.edu.tw
				<lb />
			</email>

			<reference>
				圖資與檔案學刊
				<lb />
				9:2=91 (Dec &apos;17) 1-19
				<lb />
			</reference>

			<idno>
				DOI: 10.6575/JILA.2017.91.01
				<lb />
			</idno>
			Taiwan. The results indicate that the factors of generation, sex, and age, have an impact on student&apos;
			<lb />
			choice of ethical issues. The younger generation was more supporting academic integrity and honest
			<lb />
			examination.
			<lb />
			關鍵詞 Keyword
			<lb />
			<keyword>
				倫理判斷 倫理價值 倫理兩難 道德衝突
				<lb />
				Ethical judgment；Ethical value；Information ethics；Moral conflict
			</keyword>
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>