<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="91_4" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			20
			<lb />
			Study on Instructional Models and Strategies of Information Literacy
			<lb />
			Online Courses for Higher Education 
			<lb />
			Mei-Ling Wang
	

	Abstract
			<div type="abstract">
				資訊素養對於高等教育很重要，為培養大學生成為批判性思考、獨立學習與終身學習者， 英美各國普遍推動大學資訊素養教育。數位學習與線上教育近年風行，成為新的教育與學習 方式。資訊素養線上教學開始興起，但不同於傳統教室教學，教師與學生不在一起，線上教育 如何使學生主動學習與獲得良好學習互動，均遭遇問題與挑戰。本研究主要探討大學資訊素 養線上教學模式與策略，採用文獻探討與個案研究方法，首先陳述大學資訊素養教學的意涵， 析述資訊素養線上教育的特點與問題，藉由文獻探討歸納大學資訊素養線上課程類型、課程 傳遞方式、教學法與教學策略。最後以個案研究，分析資訊素養自學網、資訊素養數位教材、 資訊素養線上課程、資訊素養磨課師四類五個線上課程，以及實證探討線上教學模式與策略， 最後提出結論與建議。
				<lb />
			</div>
			s
	Information literacy is important for higher education to cultivate undergraduates to be critical
			<lb />
			thinking, independent and lifelong learners. Therefore, information literacy instruction is popular
			<lb />
			among universities in the United States and the United Kingdom. The popularity of digital learning
			<lb />
			and online courses has been welcomed in the recent years as a new way of education and learning.
			<lb />
			Information literacy online instruction has started to develop in the recent years; however, unlike the
			<lb />
			traditional classroom teaching, teachers and students are not in the same place. How online education
			<lb />
			can make students actively learn and lead to good learning interaction is problematic and challenging.
    
			<byline>
				<affiliation> 國立政治大學圖書資訊與檔案學研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			教授
			<lb />
			Professor, Graduate Institute of Library, Information and Archival Studies, National Chengchi University
			<lb />
			E-mail:
			<email>
				meilingw@nccu.edu.tw
				<lb />
			</email>

			<reference>
				圖資與檔案學刊
				<lb />
				9:2=91 (Dec &apos;17) 20-46
				<lb />
			</reference>

			<idno>
				DOI: 10.6575/JILA.2017.91.02
				<lb />
			</idno>
			The article mainly discusses the instruction models and strategies on information literacy online
			<lb />
			courses for higher education with research methods of literature review and case study. Firstly, it
			<lb />
			explores the meaning of information literacy instruction, and then analyzes the characteristics and
			<lb />
			problems of information literacy online instruction. Through literature review, it summarizes the types
			<lb />
			of information literacy online courses, course delivery methods, pedagogies and teaching strategies.
			<lb />
			The article analyzes five cases of information literacy online courses with case study methods
			<lb />
			including an information literacy online tutorial, an information literacy digital object website, an
			<lb />
			information literacy online course and two information literacy MOOCs. This case study empirically
			<lb />
			explores information literacy online courses, instruction, learner interaction and assessment. Finally,
			<lb />
			conclusions and suggestions are proposed.
			<lb />
			關鍵詞 Keyword
			<lb />
			<keyword>
				資訊素養 資訊素養教學 線上課程 數位學習
				<lb />
			</keyword>

				Information literacy；Information literacy instruction；Online courses；E-learning
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>