<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="91_6" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			Analysis of Teachers&apos; Experiences and Challenges
			<lb />
			in Mobile Teaching in Rural Schools 
			<lb />
			Lih-Juan ChanLin 
			<lb />
			Tze-Han Lu
	

	Abstract
			<div type="abstract">
				偏鄉弱勢學童面臨教育資源普遍不足之挑戰，資訊落差情形受到關注。本研究目的在於 探索偏鄉教師行動教學參與經驗與經歷之挑戰。研究藉由深入訪談與問卷調查而蒐集教師之
				<lb />
				反應資料。透過 7 位參與偏鄉行動教學的教師進行深入訪談，以歸納教師對於行動教學推廣
				<lb />
				之關注焦點。而問卷調查則廣泛調查參與行動教學之偏鄉教師反應。在 100 份回收之調查資 料中，針對個人平板電腦教學之因應方面，教師高度反應自己對於科技問題主動找尋相關解 決途徑，以及教師有感於教學資源需要花時間整理篩選之挑戰。未來的建議方面，強調未來 行動教學的推動應增進經驗分享機會，並考量教師各方面的支援與需求，簡化行動教學計畫 申請的程序，以落實行動教學之實務。
				<lb />
			</div>
			Significant challenges in limit resources and digital divide among the great majority of children
			<lb />
			in rural areas have caught much attention. The study explored teachers&apos; experiences and challenges
			<lb />
			in mobile teaching in rural schools. Both interview and survey methods were used to gather research
			<lb />
			data. Interviews conducted among 7 teachers revealed the issues concerning tablet teaching. A survey 
	
			<byline>
				<affiliation>天主教輔仁大學圖書資訊學系</affiliation>
			</byline>
			教授
			<lb />
			Professor,
	
	Department of Library and Information Science, Fu Jen Catholic University
			<lb />
			E-mail:
			<email>lins1005@mail.fju.edu.tw</email>

			<byline>
				<affiliation> 天主教輔仁大學台灣偏鄉教育關懷中心</affiliation>
			</byline>
			主任
			<lb />
			Director, Center of Care Services for Rural Area Education in Taiwan, Fu Jen Catholic University
			<lb />
			E-mail:
			<email>
				sv0002@mail.fju.edu.tw
				<lb />
			</email>

			<reference>
				圖資與檔案學刊
				<lb />
				9:2=91 (Dec &apos;17) 71-96
				<lb />
			</reference>

			<idno>
				DOI: 10.6575/JILA.2017.91.04
				<lb />
			</idno>
			questionnaire was used to obtain reactions from more teachers, and some findings were summarized
			<lb />
			with 100 survey data collected. From their experiences, teachers reacted highly on trying their own
			<lb />
			way on solving technology problems in tablet teaching. They also felt more challenging on selecting
			<lb />
			appropriate teaching resources for use in classroom. For future implementation, teachers strongly
			<lb />
			expected more experience-sharing opportunities and more support and resources provided from the
			<lb />
			society. Simplifying application process for mobile teaching projects and focusing more on mobile
			<lb />
			teaching practices were also suggested.
			<lb />
			關鍵詞 Keyword
			<lb />
			<keyword>
				平板電腦 行動教學 偏鄉教育 科技融入 科技採用
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			Tablet computer；Mobile teaching；Rural education；Technology integration；Technology adoption
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>