<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="91_7" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			A Study of Open Access Development and Implementation in Campus:
			<lb />
			Taking University of California System, Queensland University of
			<lb />
			Technology and University of Calgary as Examples
	

	
			<lb />
			Chia-Ning Li
	

	Abstract
			<div type="abstract">
				本文透過分析美國加州大學系統、澳洲昆士蘭科技大學及加拿大卡加利大學在校園發展
				<lb />
				與實施 OA 的經驗，歸納出 OA 在校園發展與實施的重點，提供國內大專校院作為發展 OA 的
				<lb />
				參考：(1) 機構宜擬定具有規範性的政策；(2) 扣合其他政策，可使政策的執行臻至完整；(3)
				<lb />
				宜有基礎設備作為配套方案；(4) 穩定的挹注補助經費以及 (5) 節省成本，提高發展 OA 的效 益。
				<lb />
			</div>
			This study summarizes five key points of open access development and implementation on
			<lb />
			campus by analyzing the

	
	experience of University of California System, Queensland University of
			<lb />
			Technology and University of Calgary
	

	, which are provided as references for Taiwan universities and
			<lb />
			colleges to develop and implement OA on campus. The five key points are as follows: (1) the
			<lb />
			institution should formulate normative open access policy; (2) the formulated policy should
			<lb />
			coordinate with other national or funder&apos;s open access policies to make policy implementation
    
			<byline>
				<affiliation> 國家實驗研究院科技政策研究與資訊中心</affiliation>
			</byline>
			佐理研究員
			<lb />
			Research Assistant, Science &amp; Technology Policy Research and Information Center, NARL,
			
				Taipei, Taiwan
				<lb />
			
			E-mail:
			<email>
				cnli@stpi.narl.org.tw
				<lb />
			</email>

			<reference>
				圖資與檔案學刊
				<lb />
				9:2=91 (Dec &apos;17) 97-116
				<lb />
			</reference>

			<idno>
				DOI: 10.6575/JILA.2017.91.05
				<lb />
			</idno>
			complete; (3) the institution should build infrastructure for carrying out the open access policy; (4)
			<lb />
			the institution should provide stable funding for developing and implementing open access; (5) the
			<lb />
			institution should save cost and enhance the effectiveness in developing open access.
			<lb />
			關鍵詞 Keyword
			<lb />
			<keyword>
				開放取用 案例探討 美國加州大學系統 澳洲昆士蘭科技大學 加拿大卡加利大學
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			Open access；Case studies；University of California System；Queensland University of
			<lb />
			Technology；University of Calgary
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>