<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="92_4" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			1946-2016
			<lb />
			A Digital Humanities Research on the Method for Periodization of
			<lb />
			History: The Example Based on the Shenzhen-related News Reports in
			<lb />
			the People&apos;s Daily (1946-2016

	) 
			<lb />
			Wei-Yun Chiu 
			<lb />
			Yin-Yee Leong
	

	
			<lb />
			Aaron Hsu
	

	Abstract
			<div type="abstract">
				本文研究目的是希望能從數位人文研究的角度，提出一種質量並重的歷史分期法，以有
				<lb />
				別於過去多從個人主觀視角出發進行定性的歷史分期工作。本文以 1946-2016 年間《人民日
				<lb />
				報》中所有標題中包含「深圳」一詞的報導文章為研究範圍，共有 3,203 篇，運用(1)人工主觀
			</div>
			
			<lb />
			<byline>
				<affiliation>
					山東大學歷史文化學院歷史學系
					<lb />
				</affiliation>
			</byline>
			副研究員
			Associate Professor, Department of Modern Chinese History, Shandong University
			<lb />
			E-mail:
			<email>
				brianchiu@sdu.edu.cn
				<lb />
			</email>
			
			<byline>
				<affiliation> 逢甲大學風險管理與保險學系</affiliation>
			</byline>
			助理教授
			<lb />
			Assistant Professor, Department of Risk Management &amp; Insurance, Feng Chia University
			<lb />
			E-mail:
			<email>yyleong@fcu.edu.tw</email>
			,
			<lb />
			
			<byline>
				<affiliation>英國曼徹斯特大學應用社會研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			博士生
			<lb />
			Ph. D student, Applied Social Research, The University of Manchester
			<lb />
			E-mail:
			<email>
				aaron.hsu@postgrad.manchester.ac.uk
				<lb />
			</email>
			<reference>
				圖資與檔案學刊
				<lb />
				10:
				1=92 (June &apos;18) 22-43
				<lb />
			</reference>

			<idno>
				DOI: 10.6575/JILA.201806_(92).0002
				<lb />
			</idno>

			<div type="abstract">
				分期；(2)數值高峰分期；(3)關鍵詞叢異同分期等三種方法，對為期 70 年的涉深報導進行分期 工作。在研究過程中發現，上述三種分期法雖都可進行歷史分期工作，然皆有其侷限性，即這 些分期法都含有個人主觀性，在進行分期工作時往往因人而異。因此，本文提出第四種歷史 分期法，嘗試以量化數據作為客觀分期之標準，為長時段的歷史研究提供一分期工作上的新 方法與新視野，此即為本文研究結果與價值所在。
				<lb />
			</div>
			This study aims to provide a method of historical periodization based on digital humanities that
			<lb />
			could better combine qualitative and quantitative analysis than previous ones. This study singled out
			<lb />
			3,203 news reports in the People&apos;s Daily, 1946 to 2016, whose headlines contained &quot;Shenzhen&quot; and
			<lb />
			respectively applied 1) artificial periodization, 2) peak number periodization, and 3) keyword cluster
			<lb />
			periodization to these Shenzhen-related news reports. The results show that three methods of
			<lb />
			periodization respectively have their limitations on objectivity. This paper thus suggests an automatic
			<lb />
			periodization based on quantitative datasets and this data-driven method could provide a novel
			<lb />
			perspective for the long-term historical analysis in the future.
			<lb />
			Keyword 關鍵詞
			<lb />
			<keyword>
				深圳 人民日報 歷史分期 轉折點偵測 數位人文
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			Shenzhen ； People&apos;s Daily ； History periodization ； Change point problem ； Digital humanities
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>