<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="92_6" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			Development of a Text Retrieval and Mining System for
			<lb />
			Taiwanese Historical People
	

	
			<lb />
			Shun-Hong Sie 
			<lb />
			Hao-Ren Ke 
			<lb />
			Su-bing Chang 
	Abstract
			<div type="abstract"> 「人物」是歷史學研究重要的實體類型之一，因此，對人物傳記的深入了解有助於歷史 事件的相關研究。目前許多人物傳記資料是以數位文件的形式存在，而要以人力從大量人物 傳記中爬梳、彙整資料頗為曠日廢時，宜妥為運用資訊科技協助歷史學家。此外，儘管臺灣過 去已建置眾多資料庫，也有各種人物傳和可資應用的資料文獻，卻較少進行歷史人物資料庫 勘考、分析工具的開發。有鑑於此，研究者乃組成研究團隊，以《新修彰化縣志‧人物志》為 文本來源，發展資料庫檢索、全文檢索、文本探勘與社會網絡等分析工具，協助歷史人文學進</div>
			
			<byline>
				<affiliation> 國立臺灣師範大學圖書資訊學研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			博士生
			<lb />
			Ph.D. Candidate, Graduate Institute of Library &amp; Information Studies, National Taiwan Normal University
			<lb />
			E-mail:
			<email>
				mayh@ntnu.edu.tw
				<lb />
			</email>
			
			<byline>
				<affiliation> 國立臺灣師範大學圖書資訊學研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			教授
			<lb />
			Professor, Graduate Institute of Library &amp; Information Studies, National Taiwan Normal University
			<lb />
			E-mail:
			<email>
				clavenke@ntnu.edu.tw
				<lb />
			</email>
			
			<byline>
				<affiliation> 國立臺灣師範大學臺灣史研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			教授
			<lb />
			Professor, Graduate Institute of Taiwan History, National Taiwan Normal University
			<lb />
			E-mail:
			<email>
				109682@ntnu.edu.tw
				<lb />
			</email>

			<reference>
				圖資與檔案學刊
				<lb />
				10:1=92 (June &apos;18) 67-87
				<lb />
			</reference>

			<idno>
				DOI: 10.6575/JILA.201806_(92).0004
				<lb />
			</idno>

			<div type="abstract">
				行研究，長期目標為建置「臺灣歷史人物資料庫(Taiwan Biographical Database, TBDB)」。 本研究主旨在於描述「臺灣歷史人物資料庫」現階段所收錄之人物特性，闡述系統架構，以及 說明初步成果。此外，本研究將提出一套演算法辨識《新修彰化縣志‧人物志》中的命名實體
				<lb />
				(named entity) ，並以詩社名稱辨識為例說明。該套演算法的召回率達 96%，精確率則為 65%。 最後，本研究將說明建置「臺灣歷史人物資料庫」過程中習得之經驗和未來發展方向。
				<lb />
			</div>
			Personage is an important kind of entities in the study of history. Comprehensive understanding
			<lb />
			of personage biographies is beneficial for researching into historical events. In the digital era, many
			<lb />
			personage biographies are available in digital formats; as a result, it is time-consuming and labor-
			<lb />
			intensive for researchers to explore invaluable findings from massive personage biographies. Facing
			<lb />
			this situation, researchers may be helped to utilize the information efficiently with information
			<lb />
			technologies. This article introduces the development of a text retrieval and mining system for
			<lb />
			Taiwanese historical people --Taiwan Biographical Database (TBDB). It describes the characteristics
			<lb />
			of personages in TBDB, highlights the system architecture and preliminary achievement of TBDB,
			<lb />
			and proposes a method to recognize named entities in the personage biographies, specifically poetry
			<lb />
			societies, which achieves the recall rate of 96% and the precision rate of 65%. Finally, this article
			<lb />
			elaborates on the lessons learned through the creation of TBDB, and the future plans.
			<lb />
			Keyword 關鍵詞
			<lb />
			<keyword>
				臺灣歷史人物資料庫 文本檢索 文本探勘 社會網絡分析 命名實體辨識
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			Taiwan Biographical Database (TBDB)；Text retrieval；Text mining；Social network
			<lb />
			analysis (SNA)；Name entity recognition
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>