<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="93_3" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			1949-1966
			<lb />
			The Choice at the Crossroads of History: Research on Development
			<lb />
			Path of Archival Education in Mainland China from 1949 to 1966 
			<lb />
			Yan Zhang

	Abstract
			<lb />
			<div type="abstract">
				中國大陸檔案學界主流的觀點認為：中國大陸在 1952 年重構檔案學教育時，面臨「一無
				<lb />
				教員、二無教材、三無經驗」的困境。事實上，自 1934 年到 1949 年間的十六年，民國檔案 學教育在辦學機構、教師和專著三個方面給中國大陸留下了頗具規模的檔案學教育資源。但 這些不符合預期的檔案學教育資源在初期並未被啟用。中國大陸轉而向蘇聯求援，在蘇聯的 幫助下，全盤移植蘇聯檔案學教育模式，而後才開始有選擇的啟用部分民國檔案學教育資源 並著手將蘇聯檔案學教育模式「本土化」，打造符合國情的中國大陸檔案學教育體系。
				<lb />
			</div>
			The mainstream view of archival field in mainland China is, when the archival education was
			<lb />
			reconstructed in 1952, the Chinese mainland faced the dilemma of &quot;no teacher, no textbook and no
			<lb />
			experience&quot;. In fact, within the 16 years from 1934 to 1949, the archival education of the Republic of
			<lb />
			China had left quite a scale of archives education resources to the Chinese Mainland in three aspects,
			<lb />
			namely educational institution, teachers and monographs. However, such resources that deviated from
			<lb />
			the expected values were not used initially. Chinese mainland turned to the Soviet Union for help,
			<lb />
			and completely copied the Soviet archive education model with the help of the Soviet Union. After 
	
			<byline>
				<affiliation>上海大學圖書情報檔案系</affiliation>
			</byline>
			助理教授
			<lb />
			Assistant professor,
	
	Department of Library, Information and Archives, Shanghai University
			<lb />
			E-mail:
			<email>
				zy_shu@126.com
				<lb />
			</email>

			<reference>
				圖資與檔案學刊
				<lb />
				10:2=93 (Dec &apos;18) 1-25
				<lb />
			</reference>

			<idno>
				DOI: 10.6575/JILA.201812_(93).0001
				<lb />
			</idno>
			then, it began to selectively use some of the archive education resources of the Republic of China and
			<lb />
			began to localize the Soviet archival education model, creating an education system for archives in
			<lb />
			mainland China which is in line with China&apos;s national conditions.
			<lb />
			Keyword 關鍵詞
			<lb />
			<keyword>
				檔案學教育 中國大陸 蘇聯 文華圖專 中國人民大學
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			Archive education；Mainland
	
	China；Union of Soviet Socialist Republics；Boone Library
			<lb />
			School；Renmin University of China
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>