<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="10-1-1" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			<reference>
				圖書資訊學研究 10：1 (December 2015)：1-38
				<lb />
			</reference>
			<note type="submission">
				投稿日期：2015 年 5 月 20 日；接受日期：2015 年 7 月 18 日
				<lb />
			</note>
			Email: 王梅玲
			<email>meiling@nccu.edu.tw</email>
			；楊婕
			<email>
				lovejessica44@hotmail.com
				<lb />
			</email>


			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>
					臺灣地區大學圖書館館際互借 服務績效評鑑研究
					<lb />
				</titlePart>
			</docTitle>
			Performance Measurement of Interlibrary Loan
			<lb />
			for University Libraries in Taiwan
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					王梅玲
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Mei-Ling Wang
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立政治大學圖書資訊與檔案學研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			教授
			<lb />
			Professor
			<lb />
			Graduate Institute of Library Information and Archival Studies
			<lb />
			National Chengchi University
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					楊婕
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Chieh Yang
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立政治大學圖書資訊與檔案學研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			研究生
			<lb />
			Graduate Student
			<lb />
			Graduate Institute of Library Information and Archival Studies
			<lb />
			National Chengchi University
			<lb />
			【摘要 Abstract】
			<lb />
			<div type="abstract">
				大學圖書館館際互借是一種資源分享的重要服務，但需要圖 書館支持與投入許多人力與物力。本論文旨在探討大學圖書館館
				<lb />
				際互借服務現況與績效評鑑，研究目的在探討大學圖書館館際互
				<lb />
				借服務現況；用成本效益觀點探討大學圖書館館際互借服務績效
				<lb />
				評鑑；並且探討高績效館際互借服務的圖書館及其作業特徵。本 研究採用問卷調查與績效評鑑方法，運用七種績效指標：申請館
				<lb />
				際互借單位成本、申請館際互借達成率、申請館際互借處理時間、 提供館際互借單位成本、提供館際互借達成率、提供館際互借處
				<lb />
				理時間、提供與申請館際互借比值。本研究於 2014 年 4 月間調
				<lb />
				查 169 所大學圖書館，蒐集其 2013 年館際互借服務現況與績效 資料，並進行績效評鑑分析。研究結果顯示，綜合大學圖書館為
				<lb />
				館際互借服務主體，科技大學重視期刊複印館際互借。每館平均
				<lb />
				館際互借服務量為 993 件，平均申請館際互借量為 484 件；平均
				<lb />
				提供館際互借為 509 件。館際互借績效表現：申請館際互借單位
				<lb />
				成本為 165 元，提供館際互借單位成本為 129 元，申請圖書借閱
				<lb />
				達成率為 81%，申請期刊複印達成率為 78%。申請圖書借閱處理
				<lb />
				時間為 2.09 天，申請期刊複印時間為 1.87 天。圖書館提供與申
				<lb />
				請館際互借比值為 1.1：1，顯示大學圖書館館藏發展合適，足夠
				<lb />
				供應館際互借。本研究顯示圖書館開始提供電子資料庫館際互借 服務，與美國學術圖書館比較，我國大學圖書館館際互借規模小 但速度快與成本低。
				<lb />
			</div>
			The study mainly discusses performance measurements of
			<lb />
			interlibrary loan for university libraries in Taiwan. The purposes of
			<lb />
			the study are: 1. to explore the status of interlibrary loan services
			<lb />
			for university libraries in Taiwan; 2. to collect and analyze current
			<lb />
			data on the performance of ILL services of university libraries; 3. to
			<lb />
			identify and describe characteristics of low-cost, high-performing ILL
			<lb />
			operations. The study used questionnaire surveys and performance
			<lb />
			evaluation method with four performance measures to evaluate
			<lb />
			borrowing and lending services: cost, fill rate, turnaround time, and
			<lb />
			collection sufficiency. In 2014, the researcher sent questionnaires
			<lb />
			to 169 university libraries to collect the interlibrary loan operations
			<lb />
			and performance data in 2013. With the implementation the NDDS
			<lb />
			ILL information system in 2013, the ILL service performance of
			<lb />
			107 participants were assessed, the average ILL transaction per
			<lb />
			library was 993, the average ILL borrowing transaction per library
			<lb />
			was 484, and the average ILL lending transaction per library was
			<lb />
			509. The borrowing unit cost was NT$165, and the lending unit cost
			<lb />
			was NT$129. The borrowing fill rate was 79%, and the lending fill
			<lb />
			rate was 82%. The borrowing turnaround time was 1.98 days, and
			<lb />
			the lending turnaround time was 1.54 days. As the ratio of requests
			<lb />
			received to requests sent out in interlibrary lending was 1.1:1, it
			<lb />
			showed that the collection of university libraries was sufficient and
			<lb />
			adequate. This study carried out a performance measurement of ILL
			<lb />
			service, constructed seven performance indicators and described
			<lb />
			the performance of ILL service for university libraries in Taiwan
			<lb />
			as costing less with a faster turnaround time, higher fill rate and a
			<lb />
			sufficient and adequate collection.
			<lb />
			【關鍵字 Keywords】
			<lb />
			<keyword>
				館際互借；績效評鑑；大學圖書館
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			Interlibrary loan; Performance evaluation; University libraries
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>