<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="10-1-3" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			<reference>
				圖書資訊學研究 10：1 (December 2015)：83-121
				<lb />
			</reference>
			<note type="submission">
				投稿日期：2015 年 3 月 28 日；接受日期：2015 年 9 月 1 日
				<lb />
			</note>
				Email: 鄭惠珍

			<email>hcc@ncl.edu.tw</email>
			；陳雪華 
			<email>sherry@ntu.edu.tw</email>
			<lb />


			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>
					從範疇理論的角度探索中西 圖書分類思維
					<lb />
				</titlePart>
			</docTitle>
			Exploring the Thinking of Books Classification
			<lb />
			between China and the West from the Perspective of
			<lb />
			the Theory of Categorization
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					鄭惠珍
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Hui-Chen Cheng
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國家圖書館館藏發展及書目管理組</affiliation>
			</byline>
			編輯
			<lb />
			<byline>
				<affiliation>輔仁大學進修部圖書資訊學系</affiliation>
			</byline>
			兼任助理教授
			<lb />
			Editor
			<lb />
			Collection Development and Bibliography Management Division,
			<lb />
			National Central Library
			<lb />
			Adjunct Assistant Professor
			<lb />
			CEBA Program, Department of Library and Information Science,
			<lb />
			Fu Jen Catholic University

			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					陳雪華
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Hsueh-Hua Chen
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立臺灣大學圖書資訊學系暨研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			教授兼圖書館館長
			<lb />
			Professor
			<lb />
			Department and Graduate Institute of Library and Information Science,
			<lb />
			National Taiwan University
			<lb />
			Director
			<lb />
			National Taiwan University Library
			<lb />
			【摘要 Abstract】
			<lb />

			<div type="abstract">
				二十世紀時，學者對分類的研究有重大突破，指出除傳統的 古典範疇理論外，尚有一種稱為現代的範疇理論。本研究試圖從
				<lb />
				範疇理論的角度來探索中西圖書分類思維，希冀能有助於跨文化 的研究發展，進而建立中西圖書分類所需之參照，或作為改善圖
				<lb />
				書分類系統參考之用。本文首先闡述範疇理論及其演變；接著從 圖書分類原則，及圖書分類學者的分類主張，分別探討中西方圖
				<lb />
				書分類，以瞭解其所應用之範疇理論。研究結果顯示，西方的圖 書分類屬於「古典」範疇理論，而中國古代圖書分類則具有「現 代範疇理論」的思維。古典與現代範疇理論都是分類圖書時會應
				<lb />
				用的重要觀念，應同時兼顧。
				<lb />
			</div>
			In the twentieth century, scholars had key breakthroughs in
			<lb />
			classification and indicated that categorization theory is not only
			<lb />
			classical but also modern. This study attempts to discover the thinking
			<lb />
			behind book classification in China and the West from the perspective
			<lb />
			of the theory of categorization. It is hoped that this research
			<lb />
			can facilitate a cross-cultural study and then set up a necessary
			<lb />
			reference of comparison, as well as a reference for improving library
			<lb />
			classification systems. Firstly, the study introduces the evolution of
			<lb />
			the theory of categorization; then, from two aspects investigates which
			<lb />
			categorization theory was applied to book classification between China
			<lb />
			and the West. The two aspects include principle of book classification
			<lb />
			and the classification views of scholars in the library field. The result
			<lb />
			shows that the concept of book classification in the West belongs to
			<lb />
			the theory of classical categorization, while that of China shows the
			<lb />
			thinking of the theory of modern categorization. Modern and classical
			<lb />
			category theories should be taken into account when the books are
			<lb />
			classified.
			<lb />
			【關鍵字 Keywords】
			<lb />

			<keyword>
				圖書分類；中國古代圖書分類；西方圖書分類；範疇理論
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			Book classi cation; Chinese ancient book classi cation; Western book
			<lb />
			classi cation; eory of categorization
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>