<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="10-1-5" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			<reference>
				圖書資訊學研究 10：1 (December 2015)：171-211
				<lb />
			</reference>
			通訊作者 : 林奇秀
			<email>
				chishioulin@ntu.edu.tw
				<lb />
			</email>
			<note type="submission">
				投稿日期：2015 年 10 月 22 日 接受日期：2015 年 12 月 7 日
				<lb />
			</note>
			Email：林奇秀
			<email>
				chishioulin@ntu.edu.tw
			</email>
			；黎慧雯
			<email>
				huei0809@gmail.com
				<lb />
			</email>
			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>大學圖書館行動應用程式的 發展概況與使用者需求研究</titlePart>
			</docTitle>

			<lb />
			A Study of the University Library Apps and
			<lb />
			User Needs in Taiwan
			<lb />
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
				黎慧雯
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Hui-Wen Li
			<lb />
			<byline>
				<affiliation>
					國立臺灣大學圖書資訊學系暨研究所研究生
					<lb />
				</affiliation>
			</byline>
			Graduate Student
			<lb />
			Department and Graduate Institute of Library and Information Science
			<lb />
			National Taiwan University
			<lb />
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
				林奇秀
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Chi-Shiou Lin
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>
					國立臺灣大學圖書資訊學系暨研究所副教授
					<lb />
				</affiliation>
			</byline>
			Associate Professor
			<lb />
			Department and Graduate Institute of Library and Information Science
			<lb />
			National Taiwan University
			<lb />
			【摘要 Abstract】
			<lb />
			<div type="abstract">
				行動應用程式(App)是行動載具上的主要服務型態，但統
				<lb />
				計資料顯示國內大學圖書館透過 App 提供服務的狀況並不普及，
				<lb />
				網路商店中，圖書館 App 的低下載次數也顯示使用狀況不佳。為
				<lb />
				深入瞭解國內大學圖書館 App 的發展及使用者需求與期待，本研 究以調查法來瞭解國內大專院校圖書館提供行動服務的狀況，以
				<lb />
				內容分析法探索目前現有圖書館 App 的功能與內容，並以焦點團
				<lb />
				體及深度訪談來歸納比較學生及館員對 App 功能、內容與系統設 定等三大面向的意見異同。
				<lb />
			</div>
			Mobile applications (apps) are now the major service delivery
			<lb />
			channel in mobile devices. However, previous statistics shows that
			<lb />
			few university libraries had provided apps services in Taiwan. Recent
			<lb />
			statistics from the major app stores also shows low popularity of
			<lb />
			library apps. To understand what has been done and what users
			<lb />
			expect in library apps, this study surveyed all of the university and
			<lb />
			college libraries to see whether and how mobile services and apps are
			<lb />
			provided in university libraries. Content analysis of the existing apps
			<lb />
			further revealed the functionalities and information content offered via
			<lb />
			this new type of service mode. To understand what users expect from
			<lb />
			library apps and how realistics the expectations are in implementation,
			<lb />
			this study futher conducted focus groups and in-depth interview
			<lb />
			respectively on graduate students and university librarians to compare
			<lb />
			and contrast the ideas and suggestions regarding the functionalities,
			<lb />
			content, and system settings of university library apps.
			<lb />
			【關鍵字 Keywords】
			<lb />
			<keyword>
				行動應用程式；圖書館行動服務；大學圖書館
				<lb />
			</keyword>
				Mobile applications (Apps); Mobile library services; University libraries

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>