<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="10-1-4" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			<reference>
				圖書資訊學研究 10：1 (December 2015)：123-169
				<lb />
			</reference>
			<note type="submission">
				投稿日期：2015 年 10 月 29 日；接受日期：2015 年 12 月 7 日
				<lb />
			</note>
			Email: 蔡天怡
			<email>
				titsai@ntu.edu.tw
				<lb />
			</email>

			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>
					圖書資訊學領域學生如何說出
					<lb />
					「資訊」的故事：視覺方法之 探索性研究
					<lb />
				</titlePart>
			</docTitle>
			How Do Library and Information Science Students Tell
			<lb />
			the Story of Information: An Exploratory Study Using
			<lb />
			Visual Methods
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					蔡天怡
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Tien-I Tsai
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立臺灣大學圖書資訊學系</affiliation>
			</byline>
			助理教授
			<lb />
			Assistant Professor
			<lb />
			Department and Graduate Institute of Library and Information Science
			<lb />
			National Taiwan University
			<lb />
			【摘要 Abstract】
			<lb />
			<div type="abstract">
				本 研 究 運 用 圖 文 技 巧(draw-and-write technique)， 透
				<lb />
				過 Hartel 之 視 覺 方 法 蒐 集 56 位 學 生 所 繪 製 之「 資 訊 方 塊 」
				<lb />
				(iSquares)及其文字說明，透過主題分析檢視圖書資訊學領域 學生如何以圖文表述「資訊」概念。研究發現資訊方塊表述方式
				<lb />
				多元，包含人的意象、媒體與工具、大自然及情境要素等，除了 呈現資訊理論及資訊行為之概念，亦提及巨量資料之特性；本文
				<lb />
				更透過資訊方塊說出四種不同版本之資訊故事，包括：(一)由
				<lb />
				微觀社會至宏觀社會、由感知上小而大的資訊故事；(二)由具
				<lb />
				象描繪至抽象比喻、由外顯而內化的資訊故事；(三)由靜而動、
				<lb />
				由慢而快的資訊故事；(四)由紊亂至有條理、由不確定至美好
				<lb />
				的資訊故事。文末亦提出可供圖書資訊學教育實務及未來研究參 考之建議。
				<lb />
			</div>
			This study employed Hartel&apos;s draw-and-write technique-
			<lb />
			iSquares-as the visual method to collect data from 56 students in
			<lb />
			Library and Information Science (LIS). Thematic analysis was used to
			<lb />
			examine the iSquare images and descriptions. The iSquares collected
			<lb />
			in this study used a variety of presentations to express the concept of
			<lb />
			information. Main elements appeared in iSquares included the image
			<lb />
			of people, media and tools, the nature and other contextual elements.
			<lb />
			In addition to the concepts in information theories and information
			<lb />
			behavior theories, participants also included characteristics of big data
			<lb />
			in their iSquares. Based on the themes appearing in the iSquares, the
			<lb />
			researcher further illustrated stories of information in four different
			<lb />
			ways: (1) from micro-social to macro-social/from imperceptibly small
			<lb />
			to vast, as suggested by Hartel (2014a);
	(2) from concrete descriptions
			<lb />
			to abstract metaphors/from external to internal; (3) from static to
			<lb />
			mobile/from trickling to rapid; (4) from unorganized to organized/
			<lb />
			uncertain to confident. Suggestions for LIS educators on addressing
			<lb />
			the concept of information and for future iSquare research were also
			<lb />
			provided.
			<lb />
			【關鍵字 Keywords】
			<lb />
			<keyword>視覺方法；主題分析；資訊科學；圖書資訊學</keyword>
			<lb />
			Visual methods; ematic analysis; Information science; Library and
			<lb />
			information science
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>