<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="10-1-2" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			<reference>
				圖書資訊學研究 10：1 (December 2015)：39-81
				<lb />
			</reference>
			<note type="submission">
				投稿日期：2015 年 5 月 2 日；接受日期：2015 年 8 月 8 日
				<lb />
			</note>
			Email: 陳書梅
			<email>
				synn@ntu.edu.tw
				<lb />
			</email>
			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>
					大學圖書館組織創新行為之影響 因素研究
					<lb />
				</titlePart>
			</docTitle>
			A Qualitative Study on Factors in Organizational
			<lb />
			Innovation Behavior of Taiwan&apos;s University Libraries
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					陳書梅
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Chen Su-may Sheih
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立臺灣大學圖書資訊學系暨研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			教授
			<lb />
			Professor
			<lb />
			Department and Graduate Institute of Library and Information Science
			<lb />
			National Taiwan University
			<lb />
			【摘要 Abstract】
			<div type="abstract">
				近年來，面對急遽變遷的社會環境，有關服務業的組織創新
				<lb />
				研究逐漸受到重視，而圖書資訊學相關文獻亦開始探討組織創新 的議題，然而目前仍鮮少實證研究探討大學圖書館之組織創新行
				<lb />
				為。爰此，本研究應用半結構式深度訪談法，以臺灣地區 11 所
				<lb />
				大學圖書館之從業人員作為研究對象，其中包含館長、副館長及
				<lb />
				部門組長等 25 位，藉以探討國內大學圖書館組織創新行為之現 況，以及影響組織創新行為的相關因素。訪談結果發現，受訪大
				<lb />
				學圖書館之組織創新行為，包括技術與管理兩大方面。而影響受 訪大學圖書館組織創新行為的相關因素，則可歸納為館員個人、 圖書館管理階層、圖書館內部組織，以及圖書館外部環境等四個
				<lb />
				面向。最後，本研究根據研究結果提出相關建議，藉供大學圖書 館組織作為施行創新服務之參考。
				<lb />
			</div>
			As the society confronts a rapid change, organizational
			<lb />
			innovations are paramount in today&apos;s service industry. Pursuing
			<lb />
			ceaseless improvement, literatures on library and information science
			<lb />
			are also discussing how to cultivate organizational innovations in
			<lb />
			the library settings. To understand the current state and influential
			<lb />
			factors of innovation activities in Taiwan&apos;s university libraries, semi-
			<lb />
			structured in-depth interviews were deployed in this study. The
			<lb />
			interviewees consisted of 25 employees from 11 university libraries
			<lb />
			in Taiwan. The findings revealed that, technical innovations and
			<lb />
			management innovation are both adopted in the interviewed university
			<lb />
			libraries. The factors influencing organizational innovation behaviors
			<lb />
			were categorized into four perspectives, including librarians&apos; personal
			<lb />
			traits, library management, and the internal organization and external
			<lb />
			factors of libraries. Several suggestions are provided based on the
			<lb />
			research results.
			<lb />
			【關鍵字 Keywords】
			<lb />
			<keyword>
				組織創新行為；組織創新；創新；大學圖書館
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			Organizational innovation behavior; Organizational innovation; Innovation;
			<lb />
			University library
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>