<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="10-2-3" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			<reference>
				圖書資訊學研究 10：2 (June 2016)：87-132
				<lb />
			</reference>
			<note type="submission">
				投稿日期：2015 年 11 月 6 日；接受日期：2016 年 1 月 29 日
				<lb />
				
			</note>
Email：陳海泓
			<email>
				haihon@mail.nutn.edu.tw
				<lb />
			</email>
			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>
					社會領域教師和圖書教師高層
					<lb />
					次協作教學對國民小學六年級
					<lb />
					學生主題探究學習的影響以及 學生的回應
					<lb />
				</titlePart>
			</docTitle>
			The Effects of High-End Collaboration of Teacher and
			<lb />
			Teacher-Librarian on Inquiry-Based Project Reports
			<lb />
			of Sixth-Grade Students and Students&apos; Responses to
			<lb />
			Inquiry-Based Learning
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					陳海泓
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Hai-Hon Chen
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立臺南大學教育學系</affiliation>
			</byline>
			教授
			<lb />
			Professor
			<lb />
			Department of Education
			<lb />
			National University of Tainan
			<lb />
			【摘要 Abstract】
			<div type="abstract">
				本研究旨在探討社會領域教師和圖書教師協作教學對國小六
				<lb />
				年級學生個人和小組主題探究報告的影響以及學生對探究學習的
				<lb />
				回應。以台南市某公立國小兩班學生為對象，實驗組學生 29 位，
				<lb />
				進行教師協作教學；控制組 28 位，教師各自教學。以「主題探 究學習紀錄表」和「主題報告評量規準表」為研究工具，蒐集資
				<lb />
				料，並以 t 考驗進行統計分析。研究結果顯示：教師協作教學， 增進學生個人和小組主題探究報告的成績；學生對主題探究學習
				<lb />
				有正向積極的回應。根據研究結果，提出建議供教師和圖書教師 實施協作教學之參考。
				<lb />
			</div>
			This study investigated the integrated collaborative instruction
			<lb />
			between the content area of social studies teacher and school teacher-
			<lb />
			librarian impact sixth graders on individual and team&apos;s inquiry-based
			<lb />
			project reports as well as students&apos; responses to the inquiry-based
			<lb />
			learning. A quasi-experimental method was adopted, and two classes
			<lb />
			of 57 sixth-grade elementary school students in Tainan city, Taiwan
			<lb />
			were used as samples. Twenty-nine students of the experimental group
			<lb />
			participated in Concept-Oriented Reading Instruction (CORI) and
			<lb />
			were taught by the collaborative instruction of teacher and teacher-
			<lb />
			librarian; whereas 28 students of the controlled group were instructed
			<lb />
			using a didactic teaching method and were taught separately by
			<lb />
			two teachers. The Inquiry-based Learning Records and Inquiry-
			<lb />
			based Assessment Rubrics were used as instruments for collecting
			<lb />
			data. A t test was used to analyze the data. The results indicate that:
			<lb />
			(1) high-end collaboration of two teachers increase individual and
			<lb />
			team&apos;s inquiry-based project scores, and (2) sixth-grade students have
			<lb />
			positive responses toward inquiry-based learning. This paper provides
			<lb />
			suggestions to teachers for further collaborations based on these
			<lb />
			findings.
			<lb />
			【關鍵字 Keywords】
			<lb />
			<keyword>
				社會領域教師；圖書教師；高層次協作教學；探究學習；主題探究報告
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			Social studies teacher; Teacher-librarian; High-end collaboration; Inquiry-based
			<lb />
			learning; Inquiry-based project report
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>