<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="10-2-5" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			<reference>
				圖書資訊學研究 10：2 (June 2016)：181-228
				<lb />
			</reference>
			<note type="submission">
				投稿日期：2015 年 9 月 21 日；接受日期：2016 年 1 月 29 日
				<lb />
			</note>
			Email：唐牧群
Í
			<email>muhchyun.tang@gmail.com</email>
			；謝伊柔
			<email>
				angel2004ntu@gmail.com
				<lb />
			</email>


			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>
					社會導覽工具評估之研究： 以亞馬遜網路書店為例
					<lb />
				</titlePart>
			</docTitle>
			Evaluation of Social Navigation-Based Book Finding
			<lb />
			Tools: A Case Study of Amazon.com
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					唐牧群
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Muh-Chyun Tang
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立臺灣大學圖書資訊學系暨研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			副教授
			<lb />
			Associate Professor
			<lb />
			Department and Graduate Institute of Library and Information Science
			<lb />
			National Taiwan University
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					謝伊柔
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Yi-Jo Hsieh
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立臺灣大學外國語文學系暨研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			博士生
			<lb />
			Ph.D. Student
			<lb />
			Department and Graduate Institute of Foreign Languages and Literatures,
			<lb />
			National Taiwan University
			<lb />
			【摘要 Abstract】
			<lb />
			<div type="abstract">
				本研究嘗試為線上尋書導覽工具設計一套結合主觀認知及客 觀效能的評估方法，並且以實驗法比較一般主題導覽管道和社會
				<lb />
				性導覽管道。所使用的評估面向分為使用者對尋書經驗的主觀感
				<lb />
				受，以及對搜尋結果的評價。其中搜尋結果的評估採取了「選擇 集合」模型，其優點在於能夠同時考慮尋書結果的精確性和新穎
				<lb />
				性。此外也考慮了使用者對不同尋書管道的主觀感受，包括不可 替代性、滿意度、是否能幫助尋找到更多有趣的衍生作品以及擴
				<lb />
				展閱讀視野等。本研究之發現：當受試者以社會性導覽工具進行 尋書任務時比較能夠帶給受試者有趣的瀏覽經驗，能夠幫助受試
				<lb />
				者認識更多新穎且有趣的書籍，並且幫助他們更容易判斷書籍的 品質。
				<lb />
			</div>
			The study applied a set of novel criteria to compare search
			<lb />
			effectiveness and user experiences between subject-based and social
			<lb />
			navigational tools in an online bookstore setting. Two mock interfaced
			<lb />
			were created using data retrieved from Amazon.com. The baseline
			<lb />
			interface afforded subject and author search whereas the experimental
			<lb />
			interface provided collaborative filtering generated recommendations.
			<lb />
			A 2 x 2 Latin-square design was adopted where the interfaces and the
			<lb />
			genres served as the within-subject factors. A total of 30 participants
			<lb />
			took part in the study where they were asked to perform two searches,
			<lb />
			one fiction, the other, non-fiction, from a &quot;seed&quot; book of their
			<lb />
			choosing. Both subjective and objective criteria were used to evaluate
			<lb />
			performance. The objective criteria were based on &quot;choice set&quot; model
			<lb />
			in marketing where the performance was measured by the ratios
			<lb />
			between itemed chosen by and made aware to the users. The social
			<lb />
			navigational tool was shown to be more effective in terms of brings
			<lb />
			more interesting titles to users&apos; attention. The participants also reported
			<lb />
			to gain more knowledge about the related literature and achieve higher
			<lb />
			user satisfaction when using the social navigation tool. No interaction
			<lb />
			effect was found between the interface and genre factors except the
			<lb />
			consideration and awareness ratio. The methodological implications
			<lb />
			for future evaluation were discussed.
			<lb />
			【關鍵字 Keywords】
			<keyword>
				社會性導覽；推薦系統；系統評估
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			Social navigation; System evaluation; Recommender system; User experience
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>