<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="10-2-1" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			<reference>
				圖書資訊學研究 10：2 (June 2016)：1-43
				<lb />
			</reference>
			通訊作者 : 張郁蔚
			<email>
				yuweichang2013@ntu.edu.tw
				<lb />
			</email>
			<note type="submission">
				投稿日期：2016 年 2 月 28 日；接受日期：2016 年 6 月 6 日
				<lb />
			</note>
			Email：張郁蔚
			<email>yuweichang2013@ntu.edu.tw</email>
			；孫雲倩
			<email>
				yunqiansun@gmail.com
				<lb />
			</email>
			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>
					國家檔案館檔案資源商業開發 之初探
					<lb />
				</titlePart>
			</docTitle>
			Commercial Exploitation of Archival Resources
			<lb />
			in National Archives
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					張郁蔚
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Yu-Wei Chang
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立臺灣大學圖書資訊學系暨研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			副教授
			<lb />
			Associate Professor
			<lb />
			Department and Graduate Institute of Library and Information Science
			<lb />
			National Taiwan University
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					孫雲倩
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Yun-Qian Sun
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立臺灣大學圖書資訊學系暨研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			研究生
			<lb />
			Graduate Student
			<lb />
			Department and Graduate Institute of Library and Information Science
			<lb />
			National Taiwan University
			<lb />
			【摘要 Abstract】
			<lb />
			<div type="abstract">
				檔案館館藏資源的商業開發是一種檔案加值，有利於使用者 的資源近用，增加檔案館收入。本文透過英國、芬蘭、加拿大、
				<lb />
				美國、澳洲、紐西蘭、新加坡及日本 8 個國家檔案館的網站資訊
				<lb />
				探討該等檔案館檔案資源商業開發現狀。研究結果發現檔案資源 商業開發類型包括檔案數位複製、圖書出版、檔案周邊商品、檔
				<lb />
				案資料庫及研究服務 5 類，檔案館商業開發優先選擇家族史、歷
				<lb />
				史事件、研究和教學相關主題的檔案，以及 8 個國家檔案館中， 英國的檔案資源商業開發程度最高。
				<lb />
			</div>
			The commercial exploitation of archives, adding values to
			<lb />
			archives, facilitates access of archives and increases the income of
			<lb />
			archives. This study investigated the status of commercial exploitation
			<lb />
			of eight national archives based on information revealed in websites of
			<lb />
			national archives, namely UK,

	Finland, Canada, USA, Australia, New
			<lb />
			Zealand, Singapore and Japan. The findings show that five types of
			<lb />
			commercial exploitation were identified: digital copies, publications,
			<lb />
			archives merchandises, archival databases, and research services.
			<lb />
			The topics of archives used for commercial exploitation cover family
			<lb />
			history, historical events, and research and teaching. Among the eight
			<lb />
			archives surveyed, the national archives of UK has involved more
			<lb />
			commercial exploration than any other national archives.
			<lb />
			【關鍵字 Keywords】
			<lb />
			<keyword>
				國家檔案館；檔案館網站；檔案加值；商業開發
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			National archives; Archives websites; Value-added archival information;
			<lb />
			Commercial exploitation
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>