<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="10-2-2" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			<reference>
				圖書資訊學研究 10：2 (June 2016)：45-85
				<lb />
			</reference>
			通訊作者：林奇秀
			<email>
				chishioulin@ntu.edu.tw
				<lb />
			</email>
			<note type="submission">
				投稿日期：2016 年 3 月 1 日；接受日期：2016 年 5 月 17 日
				<lb />
			</note>
			Email：林奇秀
			<email>chishioulin@ntu.edu.tw</email>
			；林慶隆
			<email>cllin@mail.naer.edu.tw</email>
			；邵婉卿
			<email>
				maria@mail.naer.edu.tw；
				<lb />
			</email>
			張婕妤
			<email>r00126001@ntu.edu.tw</email>
			；陳彥如
			<email>r99126014@ntu.edu.tw</email>

			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>
					人文學者心目中理想的學術摘要
					<lb />
				</titlePart>
			</docTitle>
			What Constitutes a Good Abstract for the
			<lb />
			Humanities Researchers?
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					林奇秀
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Chi-Shiou Lin
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立臺灣大學圖書資訊學系</affiliation>
			</byline>
			副教授
			<lb />
			Associate Professor
			<lb />
			Department and Graduate Institute of Library and Information Science
			<lb />
			National Taiwan University
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					林慶隆
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Ching-Lung Lin
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>
					國家教育研究院編譯發展中心研究員
					<lb />
				</affiliation>
			</byline>
			Research Fellow
			<lb />
			Development Center for Compilation and Translation
			<lb />
			National Academyfor Educational Research
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					邵婉卿
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Wang-Ching Shaw
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國家教育研究院圖書館</affiliation>
			</byline>
			執行秘書
			<lb />
			Executive Secretary
			<lb />
			Library, National Academy for Educational Research
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					張婕妤
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Chieh-Yu Chang
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立臺灣大學圖書資訊學系</affiliation>
			</byline>
			研究生
			<lb />
			Graduate Student
			<lb />
			Department and Graduate Institute of Library and Information Science
			<lb />
			National Taiwan University
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					陳彥如
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Yen-Ju Chen
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立臺灣大學圖書資訊學系</affiliation>
			</byline>
			研究生
			<lb />
			Graduate Student
			<lb />
			Department and Graduate Institute of Library and Information Science
			<lb />
			National Taiwan University
			<lb />
			【摘要 Abstract】
			<div type="abstract">
				現行摘要書寫規範多從科學論文角度出發，未必能滿足人文
				<lb />
				學者的需求和期待。有鑑於此，本研究的目的便是了解人文學者 心目中理想的學術摘要樣態，如應包含哪些資訊元素？適用科學
				<lb />
				與社會科學中常見的結構性摘要嗎？在摘介較長篇幅的人文論著 如學術專書時，摘要的涵蓋內容與摘寫策略應如何調整？本研究
				<lb />
				採立意抽樣與深度訪談方式，訪談 15 位人文學者對於摘要的看
				<lb />
				法，並以紮根理論分析歸納其意見，形成研究結論。研究結果顯
				<lb />
				示，人文學者要求學術摘要應具備五類基本資訊元素：1. 問題意
				<lb />
				識或主題關懷；2. 研究對象與研究素材；3. 研究方法或理論觀點；
				<lb />
				4. 與既有文獻的關聯；5. 研究的創見、成果或結論。在結構性摘
				<lb />
				要上，所有受訪者都認同，若能提供作者有系統的摘要寫作指引， 建議其在摘要中呈現哪些資訊元素，摘要品質應該會更好，但要
				<lb />
				避免干涉其呈現方式。同時，人文學者也認為，摘要書寫時應用 字精準，語意明確，是一篇敘事流暢精彩的獨立短文；在佈局上，
				<lb />
				摘要應完整、平衡地呈現五類基本資訊，並且凸顯研究賣點。而
				<lb />
				為長篇論著(如學術專書)撰寫摘要時，則應額外闡釋論著的旨
				<lb />
				趣、核心內容與篇章結構，提供讀者更細緻微觀的描述。文末也 根據研究發現，為人文學者和學術期刊提供摘要書寫建議。
				<lb />
			</div>
			Abstracts are surrogate information that facilitates the
			<lb />
			dissemination and exchange of scholarly information. However,
			<lb />
			existing abstracting guides do not fully meet the needs of the
			<lb />
			humanities research. This study explored what types of information
			<lb />
			need to be included in a humanities research abstract and whether the
			<lb />
			increasingly popular structured abstract is appropriate for humanities
			<lb />
			works. It goes on to discuss on the content inclusion and writing
			<lb />
			presentation of humanities abstracts of varying lengths. Based on the
			<lb />
			in-depth interviews with 15 humanities scholars, this study derived
			<lb />
			five content elements to be included in a humanities abstract: research
			<lb />
			questions or research focus; study subjects and materials; research
			<lb />
			methods or research perspectives; relations to the existing literatures;
			<lb />
			research achievement, insights, and/or conclusion. A good humanities
			<lb />
			research abstract also demonstrates good writing and wording,
			<lb />
			comprehensive and balanced in content coverage, magnifying the
			<lb />
			research focus and major theses, and can be viewed as a stand-alone
			<lb />
			text. For lengthier abstracts such as those for books, theses, and longer
			<lb />
			reports, additional macro and micro descriptions of the works may be
			<lb />
			offered aside from compliance to the aforementioned principles.
			<lb />
			【關鍵字 Keywords】
			<lb />
			<keyword>
				人文學；學術摘要；摘要寫作
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			Humanities research; Scholarly abstract; Abstracting
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>