<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="11-1-1" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			<reference>
				圖書資訊學研究 11：1 (December 2016)：1-46
				<lb />
			</reference>

			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>
					公共圖書館讀者服務館員遭遇 問題讀者之情緒勞務研究
					<lb />
				</titlePart>
			</docTitle>
			The Emotional Labor of Public Service Librarians
			<lb />
			Encountered Problem Patrons in Taiwan&apos;s Public
			<lb />
			Libraries: A Quantitative Study
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					陳書梅
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Chen Su-may Sheih
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立臺灣大學圖書資訊學系暨研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			教授
			<lb />
			Professor
			<lb />
			Department and Graduate Institute of Library and Information Science
			<lb />
			National Taiwan University
			<lb />
			【摘要 Abstract】
			<div type="abstract">
				公共圖書館的讀者服務館員係高情緒勞務工作者，館員的情
				<lb />
				緒勞務攸關圖書館的整體形象與服務品質。倘若遭遇問題讀者， 則館員更需付出情緒勞務，可能使之產生情緒耗竭的現象。有鑑 於此，本研究首先運用半結構式深度訪談法，探討讀者服務館員
				<lb />
				遭遇的問題讀者類型；之後，則奠基於訪談結果編製問卷，由情 緒勞務層面切入，針對分佈於臺灣各縣市的公共圖書館讀者服務 館員，進行研究，探討館員遭遇問題讀者之頻次、問題讀者對館
				<lb />
				員工作情緒的影響、館員處遇問題讀者之情緒勞務，以及遭遇問
				<lb />
				題讀者頻次、工作情緒、情緒勞務負荷與情緒耗竭之間是否有關 聯性。限於期刊篇幅，本文僅呈現量化的問卷調查結果。
				<lb />
				研究結果發現，館員處遇問題讀者之情緒勞務居高，而館員 遭遇問題讀者的頻次、問題讀者對於館員工作情緒的影響、館員
				<lb />
			</div>
			<note type="submission">
				投稿日期：2016 年 8 月 3 日；接受日期：2016 年 10 月 31 日
				<lb />
			</note>
			Email：陳書梅
			<email>
				synn@ntu.edu.tw
				<lb />
			</email>

			<div type="abstract">
				的情緒耗竭皆居中等程度。另外，遭遇問題讀者頻次對館員情緒 耗竭程度具正向顯著影響力，問題讀者對館員工作情緒的影響則
				<lb />
				與館員情緒耗竭程度有正向顯著關係，而處理個人負面情緒構面
				<lb />
				會正向顯著影響館員之情緒耗竭程度，但表達個人正面情緒對情 緒耗竭程度具有負向顯著的影響力。
				<lb />
			</div>
			For public service librarians, emotional labor refers to their
			<lb />
			devoting considerable effort to controlling their emotions in order
			<lb />
			to maintain the library image and provide patrons with satisfactory
			<lb />
			service. Librarians perform considerable emotional labor when
			<lb />
			encountering problem patrons while engaging in library tasks.
			<lb />
			However, emotional labor endured for extended periods may cause
			<lb />
			librarians to experience emotional exhaustion, which further leads
			<lb />
			to negative conditions such as fatigue or losing emotional resources
			<lb />
			completely. By administering a questionnaire and using public service
			<lb />
			librarians as subjects, this study explored the concerns about problem
			<lb />
			patrons from the aspect of emotional labor. According to the results,
			<lb />
			librarians perform high levels of emotional labor when encountering
			<lb />
			problem patrons, whereas the frequency of their encountering problem
			<lb />
			patrons, the influence of problem patrons on their emotions, and the
			<lb />
			degree of emotional exhaustion are at moderate levels. Furthermore,
			<lb />
			the frequency of encountering problem patrons positively and
			<lb />
			noticeably influences the degree of emotional exhaustion. There is
			<lb />
			a positive correlation between the influence of problem patrons on
			<lb />
			the emotions and emotional exhaustion of librarians. In addition,
			<lb />
			controlling negative emotions positively influences emotional
			<lb />
			exhaustion among librarians, but expressing one&apos;s positive emotions
			<lb />
			negatively influences the extent of emotional exhaustion.
			<lb />
			【關鍵字 Keywords】
			<lb />
			<keyword>
				問題讀者；讀者服務館員；情緒勞務；公共圖書館
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			Problem patron; Challenging patron; Public service librarian; Emotional labor;
			<lb />
			Public library
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>