<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="11-1-2" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			<reference>
				圖書資訊學研究 11：1 (December 2016)：47-84
				<lb />
			</reference>

			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>
					短文回應的主題自動歸類在 行動教育活動上之應用初探
					<lb />
				</titlePart>
			</docTitle>
			A Preliminary Study of Short Text Responses Clustering
			<lb />
			for Mobile Educational Activities
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					李龍豪
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Lung-Hao Lee
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立臺灣師範大學圖書資訊學研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			博士後研究員
			<lb />
			Postdoctoral Fellow
			<lb />
			Graduate Institute of Library and Information Studies
			<lb />
			National Taiwan Normal University
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					簡佑達
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Yu-Ta Chien
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立臺灣師範大學科學教育中心</affiliation>
			</byline>
			博士後研究員
			<lb />
			Postdoctoral Fellow
			<lb />
			Science Education Center
			<lb />
			National Taiwan Normal University
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					張俊彥
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Chun-Yen Chang
			<lb />
			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立臺灣師範大學科學教育研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			講座教授
			<lb />
			Chair Professor
			<lb />
			Graduate
	Institute of Science Education
			<lb />
			National Taiwan Normal University
			<lb />
			通訊作者：曾元顯
			<email>
				samtseng@ntnu.edu.tw
				<lb />
			</email>
			<note type="submission">
				投稿日期：2016 年 11 月 6 日；接受日期：2016 年 12 月 15 日
				<lb />
			</note>
			Email：李龍豪
			<email>lhlee@ntnu.edu.tw</email>
			；簡佑達
			<email>yutachien@ntnu.edu.tw</email>
			；張俊彥
			<email>changcy@ntnu.edu.tw</email>
			；
			<lb />
			李宗諺
			<email>yan@ntnu.edu.tw</email>
			；曾元顯
			<email>samtseng@ntnu.edu.tw</email>


			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					李宗諺
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Tsung-Yen Li
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立臺灣師範大學科學教育中心</affiliation>
			</byline>
			專任研究助理
			<lb />
			Research Assistant
			<lb />
			Science Education Center
			<lb />
			National Taiwan Normal University
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					曾元顯
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Yuen-Hsien Tseng
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立臺灣師範大學圖書資訊學研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			教授
			<lb />
			Professor
			<lb />
			Graduate Institute of Library and Information Studies
			<lb />
			National Taiwan Normal University
			<lb />
			【摘要 Abstract】
			<div type="abstract">
				文字歸類是用來偵測文件語料涵蓋的主題，以便於資訊瀏
				<lb />
				覽、分析、組織的資訊檢索技術。而近年教室中即時反饋系統
				<lb />
				(Instant Response System, IRS)的運用越來越普遍，以強化學生
				<lb />
				專注參與的情形，進而增進其學習成效。然而目前的 IRS 較缺乏 學生自由回應的簡短文字之歸類處理功能，以致無法進一步發揮
				<lb />
				其功效。本文的目的，在探討 IRS 現況以及短文回應的特性與問
				<lb />
				題、回顧短文主題歸類自動處理的技術與應用情形、提出一套可
				<lb />
				行的搭配系統供 IRS 整合運用，並展示我們目前實作的結果範例， 以做為後續運用、研究的參考。本文比較了三種自動歸類方法，
				<lb />
				結果顯示影響歸類成效的因素眾多，理論上較好的歸類方法，不 見得會有較佳的結果，還需其他因素或處理流程的配合。
				<lb />
			</div>
			Text clustering is a powerful information retrieval technique to
			<lb />
			detect topics from document corpora, so as to provide information
			<lb />
			browsing, analysis, and organization. On the other hand, the Instant
			<lb />
			Response System (IRS) has been widely used in recent years to
			<lb />
			enhance student engagement in class and thus improve their learning
			<lb />
			effectiveness. However, the lack of functions to process short text
			<lb />
			responses from the IRS prevents the further application of IRS in
			<lb />
			classes. Therefore, this article aims to discuss the current status of
			<lb />
			IRS application, illustrate the characteristics of short text responses
			<lb />
			from the IRS, review current short text processing techniques, propose
			<lb />
			a proper short text clustering module for the IRS, and demonstrate
			<lb />
			our implemented techniques through real-world examples, so as to
			<lb />
			provide experiences and insights for further study. In particular, we
			<lb />
			have compared three clustering methods and the result shows that
			<lb />
			theoretically better methods need not lead to better results, as there are
			<lb />
			various factors that may affect the final performance.
			<lb />
			【關鍵字 Keywords】
			<lb />
			<keyword>
				文字歸類；短文；即時回應系統；資訊組織；行動教育
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			Text Clustering; Short Texts; Instant Response Systems; Information
			<lb />
			Organization; Mobile Education
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>