<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="11-2-4" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			<reference>
				圖書資訊學研究 11：2 (June 2017)：139-179
				<lb />
			</reference>

			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>
					基於詞性組合規則結合維基百科 進行中文命名實體辨識與消歧義
					<lb />
				</titlePart>
			</docTitle>
			Using Part-of-Speech Tagging Based Approach with
			<lb />
			Wikipedia to Assist Chinese Named Entity Recognition
			<lb />
			and Disambiguation
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					黃純敏
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Chuen-Min Huang
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>雲林科技大學資管系</affiliation>
			</byline>
			副教授
			<lb />
			Associate Professor
			<lb />
			Department of Information Management
			<lb />
			National Yunlin University of Science and Technology
			<lb />
			【摘要 Abstract】
			<lb />
			<div type="abstract">
				傳統命名實體辨識多採用規則與機率的方法，然而礙於
				<lb />
				語義混淆特性與未知詞的增長，精確率難以有效提高。本研
				<lb />
				究藉由詞性組合定義命名規則，並加入姓名鏈結演算法及透
				<lb />
				過維基百科文本編輯特性，以協助辨識及消歧義。研究發現
				<lb />
				應用姓名鏈結機率公式結合句法規則，可大幅提高人名辨識
				<lb />
				精確率；對於「地名」/「組織名」，由於二者命名規則相似，
				<lb />
				過去研究需藉助詞庫及特殊詞幹集區別，本研究透過簡易地
				<lb />
				名規則並結合維基輔助分歧。實驗結果顯示本研究在精確
				<lb />
				率、 召 回 率、F-measure 分 別 達 86.32%、75.33%、80.33%， 相較於其他大規模規則的判斷研究，及採用人工標註結合
				<lb />
			</div>
			作者：黃純敏
			<email>
				jennyhuang921@gmail.com
				<lb />
			</email>

			<note type="submission">
				投稿日期：2017 年 5 月 16 日；接受日期：2017 年 6 月 23 日
				<lb />
			</note>
			<div type="abstract">
				HMM 機器學習的研究，本研究所歸納的規則不僅精簡，整 體表現亦毫不遜色，尤其以精確率最為突出。
				<lb />
			</div>
			Traditional Named Entity Recognition (NER) adopts rule-based
			<lb />
			and/or probabilistic models in morphological analysis, while it still
			<lb />
			exists the problem of low accuracy due to the problem of semantic
			<lb />
			ambiguity and the growth of unknown words. In this study, we
			<lb />
			applied syntax rules of names and places to process Chinese NER,
			<lb />
			and extracted features from Wikipedia to assist disambiguation and
			<lb />
			thereby help to improve recognition accuracy. Our study found that the
			<lb />
			recognition accuracy is raised because of a combination of syntax rule
			<lb />
			with name algorithm. In addition, since the location and organization
			<lb />
			names usually follow some particular verbs, we only configured basic
			<lb />
			rules for location ER and referred to the geographical directories of
			<lb />
			Infobox in Wikipedia to verify their identities. In our overall system
			<lb />
			evaluation, the precision rate achieves 86.32%, recall reaches 75.65%,
			<lb />
			and F-measure reaches 80.4%. Compared with other automatic rule
			<lb />
			construction and quasi-machine learning methods, we have a better
			<lb />
			performance particularly on the precision rate.
			<lb />
			【關鍵字 Keywords】
			<lb />
			<keyword>
				命名實體辨識、命名實體消歧義、詞性組合、句法規則、維基百科
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			Named Entity Recognition; Name Entity Disambiguation; POS Combination,;
			<lb />
			Syntax Rules; Wikipedia
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>