<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="11-2-3" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			<reference>
				圖書資訊學研究 11：2 (June 2017)：95-138
				<lb />
			</reference>

			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>
					臺灣社會科學學者資料再用行為 之研究
					<lb />
				</titlePart>
			</docTitle>
			Data Reuse Behavior among Taiwan Social Scientists
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					林奇秀
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Chi-Shiou Lin
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立臺灣大學圖書資訊學系暨研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			副教授
			<lb />
			Associate Professor
			<lb />
			Department of Library and Information Science,
			<lb />
			National Taiwan University
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					賴璟毅
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Ching-Yi Lai
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立臺灣大學圖書資訊學研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			研究生
			<lb />
			Graduate Student
			<lb />
			Graduate Institute of Library and Information Science,
			<lb />
			National Taiwan University
			<lb />
			【摘要 Abstract】
			<lb />
			<div type="abstract">
				近年來學術資料分享呼籲漸盛，學者的資料再用行為也開始 受到關注，但相對於自然與應用科學，社會科學的資料再用研究
				<lb />
				相對較少。本文以深度訪談來瞭解臺灣社會科學學者的資料再用
				<lb />
				行為，共訪談 14 位具有量化數據再用經驗的社會、政治、教育、 經濟與心理學者。研究發現，在再用動機方面，學者取用既有資
				<lb />
			</div>
			通訊作者：林奇秀
			<email>
				chishioulin@ntu.edu.tw
				<lb />
			</email>
			<note type="submission">
				投稿日期：2016 年 11 月 29 日；接受日期：2017 年 3 月 22 日
				<lb />
			</note>
			<div type="abstract">
				料，理由可能是因為無法自行蒐集大規模或長期性資料、取用來 自權威單位的資料比較具有公信力、取用既有資料可免除研究倫
				<lb />
				理審查的煩擾、可探索潛在研究題目、能拓展既存的研究議題、 學科領域文化的鼓勵或阻撓等。在獲知管道方面，學者可能透過
				<lb />
				五種管道來掌握資料的消息，包含學術文獻、同儕與指導教授、 政府與學術機構網站、學會或調查機構的推廣活動、紙本統計資
				<lb />
				料等。在資料評估方面，學者常用的評估策略包含評估問卷工具 品質、評估樣本品質、評估資料蒐集過程、評估資料新穎度、評 估資料易得性、以及評估分析結果的發表潛力。在資料處理上，
				<lb />
				學者會先對資料集進行描述統計與信效度檢驗，確認資料基本品 質後，再進行基本數據校正處理，有時還必須合併多組資料集並 尋求或補足資料集缺乏的變數。
				<lb />
			</div>
			is article describes the ndings from a qualitative study on
			<lb />
			social scientists&apos; data reuse behavior in Taiwan. In recent years,
			<lb />
			data sharing has been a salient topic in the scholarly communities.
			<lb />
			Empirical studies on how scientists use existing data have also
			<lb />
			emerged. However, data reuse in social sciences is less studied
			<lb />
			than in natural and applied sciences. This study focused on the
			<lb />
			reuse of existing quantitative data by Taiwan&apos;s social scientists.
			<lb />
			Semi-structured, in-depth interview was used to understand the
			<lb />
			experiences of 14 researchers from sociology, political science,
			<lb />
			education, economics, and psychology. The results show that, in
			<lb />
			regards to motivations, participants re-used existing data for the
			<lb />
			following reasons: unable to collect large-scaled or long-term data,
			<lb />
			higher credibility of data released by authoritative sources, free from
			<lb />
			harassment of IRB reviews, exploring potential research questions,
			<lb />
			carrying on existing research directions, and the encouragement
			<lb />
			or discouragement of the disciplinary cultures. Participants had
			<lb />
			relied on ve di erent channels to nd existing data, i.e., research
			<lb />
			literatures, peers and advisors, government agencies or academic
			<lb />
			institutions&apos; websites, promotional activities of scholarly
			<lb />
			associations and survey institutes, and statistical publications.
			<lb />
			Participants also reported six evaluation strategies prior to the
			<lb />
			actual use of the located data, including the evaluation of survey
			<lb />
			instrument quality, sample quality, data collection procedures,
			<lb />
			timeliness of data, availability of data, and the potential value
			<lb />
			for publication of the re-use analysis. Finally, in data processing,
			<lb />
			participants rst inspected the descriptive statistics and the validity
			<lb />
			and reliability of the dataset and then proceeded to correct, amend,
			<lb />
			or convert the data. They might also need to combine multiple
			<lb />
			datasets and ll in further needed variables from external sources or
			<lb />
			by using various techniques.
			<lb />
			【關鍵字 Keywords】
			<lb />
			<keyword>
				資料再用、資料取用、量化資料、社會科學
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			Data reuse; Data access; Quantitative data; Social sciences
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>