<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="11-2-2" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			<reference>
				圖書資訊學研究 11：2 (June 2017)：51-94
				<lb />
			</reference>


			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>
					國際志工投入公益旅行之動機 與資訊需求研究
					<lb />
				</titlePart>
			</docTitle>
			A Study on the Motivations and Information Needs of
			<lb />
			International Volunteer Tourists
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					張煦
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Sheu Chang
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立臺灣師範大學圖書資訊學研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			研究生
			<lb />
			Graduate Student
			<lb />
			Graduate Institute of Library and Information Studies
			<lb />
			National Taiwan Normal University
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					柯皓仁
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Hao-Ren Ke
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立臺灣師範大學圖書資訊學研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			教授
			<lb />
			Professor
			<lb />
			Graduate Institute of Library and Information Studies
			<lb />
			National Taiwan Normal University
			<lb />
			【摘要 Abstract】
			<lb />
			<div type="abstract">
				本研究目的在瞭解從事國際公益旅行者之動機與資訊需求，
				<lb />
				並探討動機與資訊需求的相關性。研究採用問卷調查法，針對
				<lb />
				2012 年至 2015 年從事國際公益旅行者調查。研究發現：(1)參
				<lb />
				與動機以專案動機為優先，利他動機和旅遊動機次之；(2)參
				<lb />
			</div>
			通訊作者：柯皓仁
			<email>
				clavenke@ntnu.edu.tw
				<lb />
			</email>
			<note type="submission">投稿日期：2016 年 3 月 1 日；接受日期：2016 年 5 月 17 日</note>
			<lb />
			Email：柯皓仁
			<email>
				clavenke@ntnu.edu.tw
			</email>
			；張煦
			<email>
				themartixkimo@gmail.com
				<lb />
			</email>
			<div type="abstract">
				與動機以外在證明動機分別與生涯成長動機和旅遊動機相關性較
				<lb />
				顯著；(3)從事公益旅行者之資訊需求以國家基本資訊最高，
				<lb />
				其次為旅行個人準備和服務執行內容；(4)資訊需求主題之國
				<lb />
				家基本資訊和探索與分享各自與其他主題較具有相關性；(5)
				<lb />
				動機與資訊需求存在三種典型相關；(6)七項背景變項對動機 或資訊需求主題具有差異。依據上述，針對志工招募單位管理和 個人準備公益旅行提出建議。
				<lb />
			</div>
			This study attempts to reveal motivations and information needs
			<lb />
			of international volunteer tourists, and explore the kinds of correlations
			<lb />
			between motivations and information needs. Questionnaire surveys
			<lb />
			were employed. The findings of this paper are as follows: (1) The main
			<lb />
			reason of participating international volunteer tourism is the purpose
			<lb />
			of the specific service project. The second and third motivations are
			<lb />
			altruism and travel respectively. (2) Several correlations between
			<lb />
			motivations of international volunteer tourists are found, with the
			<lb />
			highest statistical significance being firstly the combination of the
			<lb />
			desire to travel with that for external acknowledgment, followed by
			<lb />
			the combination of career and professional enhancement with external
			<lb />
			acknowledgement. (3) The primary information need of international
			<lb />
			volunteer tourists is destination nation information. The second and
			<lb />
			third needs are individual travel preparation and required knowledge
			<lb />
			for service respectively. (4) The information needs &quot;destination
			<lb />
			nation basic information&quot; and &quot; exploring and sharing&quot; are highly
			<lb />
			relevant with other needs, while required knowledge for service is
			<lb />
			quite independent. (5) There are three canonical correlations between
			<lb />
			motivations and information needs. (6) Volunteers with different
			<lb />
			demographic information have significant differences in motivations
			<lb />
			and information needs. On the basis of the research results, this study
			<lb />
			proposes several suggestions for volunteer recruitment organizations
			<lb />
			and volunteers.
			<lb />
			【關鍵字 Keywords】
			<lb />
			<keyword>
				公益旅行；國際志工；動機；資訊需求
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			Volunteer tourism; International volunteer; Motivation; Information need
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>