<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="11-2-1" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			<reference>
				圖書資訊學研究 11：2 (June 2017)：1-49
				<lb />
			</reference>

			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>
					青少年輕小說閱讀動機與閱讀
					<lb />
					行為之研究-以新北市為例
					<lb />
				</titlePart>
			</docTitle>
			A Study on Reading Motivations and Reading Behaviors
			<lb />
			of Light Novel for Adolescents : The Example of New
			<lb />
			Taipei City
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					林巧敏
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Chiao-Min Lin
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立政治大學圖書資訊與檔案學研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			教授
			<lb />
			Professor
			<lb />
			Graduate Institute of Library, Information and Archival Studies
			<lb />
			National Chengchi University
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					葉一蕾
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Yi-Lei Yeh
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國家教育研究院圖書館</affiliation>
			</byline>
			館員
			<lb />
			Librarian of The National Academy for Education Research
			<lb />
			【摘要 Abstract】
			<lb />

			<div type="abstract">
				本研究旨在探討青少年輕小說閱讀動機與閱讀行為，並分析 性別、年齡及家庭社經地位等三個背景變項在閱讀動機與閱讀行
				<lb />
				為的差異情形。為達上述目的，本研究以問卷調查法蒐集資料，
				<lb />
				採分層抽樣及集叢抽樣向新北市國中生及高中生施測，回收有效
				<lb />
				問卷計 1,160 份，其中有輕小說閱讀經驗者計 736 份，經統計分
				<lb />
			</div>
			通訊作者：林巧敏
			<email>
				cmlin@nccu.edu.tw
				<lb />
			</email>

			<note type="submission">
				投稿日期：2017 年 1 月 24 日；接受日期：2017 年 4 月 7 日
				<lb />
			</note>
			<div type="abstract">
				析結果顯示：(一)青少年之輕小說閱讀動機以「休閒享受」為
				<lb />
				主，「社會互動」為次要動機。(二)男生比女生具有較強之輕
				<lb />
				小說閱讀動機，且花更多時間在閱讀輕小說。(三)青少年首愛
				<lb />
				之輕小說主題為「奇幻冒險」，次為「浪漫戀愛」、 「青春校園」，
				<lb />
				且不同性別及家庭社經地位青少年在輕小說主題之偏愛上並無差
				<lb />
				異。(四)青少年閱讀輕小說的媒介載體，仍以紙本書為主。
				<lb />
			</div>
			The study aims to investigate the reading motivations and
			<lb />
			behaviors of light novels for adolescents and to analyze the differences
			<lb />
			between reading motivations and behaviors of light novels for
			<lb />
			adolescents were analyzed in three background variables like gender、
			<lb />
			age and family socioeconomic status. In order to achieve the purposes,
			<lb />
			a questionnaire survey was employed as the major research method.
			<lb />
			Under stratified sampling and cluster sampling, the data are collected
			<lb />
			by questionnaire from 1,160 Junior high school students and high
			<lb />
			school students who study in New Taipei City. Among them, there are
			<lb />
			736 valid samples with reading experiences of light novel. Through
			<lb />
			statistical analysis, the conclusion is summarized as followings:
			<lb />
			1. Adolescents has high reading motivations of light novels, and
			<lb />
			&quot;relaxation and enjoyment&quot; as the main motivation, &quot;social
			<lb />
			interaction&quot; as a secondary motivation.
			<lb />
			2.
			<lb />
			e reading motivations of light novels for boys are stronger than
			<lb />
			girls, and the boys also spend more time in reading light novels.
			<lb />
			3. &quot;Fantasy adventure&quot; is adolescents&apos; favorite theme of light
			<lb />
			novels, followed by &quot;romantic love&quot;, &quot;younth campus&quot;, and
			<lb />
			the preference for topic type of light novels is no difference
			<lb />
			between adolescents with different gender and different family
			<lb />
			socioeconomic status.
			<lb />
			4. Paper Books is still the main medium for adolescents to read light novels
			<lb />
			【關鍵字 Keywords】
			<lb />
			<keyword>
				青少年、輕小說、閱讀動機、閱讀行為
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			Adolescents; Light novel; Reading motivations; Reading behaviors
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>