<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="12-1-5" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			<reference>
				圖書資訊學研究 12：1 (December 2017)：139-172
				<lb />
			</reference>


			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>
					1950-1960 年代臺灣行政改革主 張中的檔案管理政策發展
					<lb />
				</titlePart>
			</docTitle>
			The Study of Archives Management Policy Development
			<lb />
			in Taiwan Administrative Reform Proposition During the
			<lb />
			1950s and 60s
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					吳宇凡
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Yu-Fan Wu
			<lb />
			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立政治大學圖書資訊與檔案學研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			博士
			<lb />
			Ph.D.
			<lb />
			Graduate Institute of Library, Information and Archival Studies
			<lb />
			National Chengchi University
			<lb />
			【摘要 Abstract】
			<div type="abstract">
				近代檔案事業發展研究學者普遍認為，戰後臺灣檔案管理制
				<lb />
				度因國內局勢動盪而未有明顯發展。事實上，隨著韓戰爆發，總 統蔣中正趁此喘息之際，令黃季陸、王雲五等人參酌美國胡佛委 員會行政改革之成果，針對我國中央行政效能及行政組織架構進
				<lb />
				行檢討。在黃季陸與王雲五有關總務議題的報告中，文書與檔案 管理相關建議不僅提出設置中央主管機關的看法，更轉化、結合 美國檔案管理思維從而建立臺灣公文書系統，成為我國檔案事業
				<lb />
				發展歷程中特殊的一頁。為探究戰後美國檔案管理思維對於我國
				<lb />
				的影響，本研究針對政府遷臺後為進行行政改革而仿效美國胡佛 委員會之各項作為中，檔案管理核心移轉及其相關制度建立進行
				<lb />
				論述，整理並耙梳 1950 至 1960 年代相關文獻內容，以瞭解戰後
				<lb />
			</div>
			作者：吳宇凡
			<email>
				watchband@gmail.com
				<lb />
			</email>
			<note type="submission">
				投稿日期：2017 年 7 月 21 日；接受日期：2017 年 10 月 11 日
				<lb />
			</note>

			<div type="abstract">
				臺灣在面對檔案管理各項問題所開拓出來的新制度作為，從而構 建戰後臺灣行政改革與檔案管理制度發展之歷史。
				<lb />
			</div>
			Researchers of archival undertaking history have often indicated
			<lb />
			that the official documents system of Taiwan did not develop obviously
			<lb />
			because of social unrest in the country after World War II. With the
			<lb />
			outbreak of the Korean War, in fact, President CHIANG KAI-SHEK
			<lb />
			took the opportunity to commission HUANG CHI-LU and WANG
			<lb />
			YUN-WU to refer to the achievements of Hoover Commission to
			<lb />
			improve administrative efficiency and analyze administrative structure
			<lb />
			of ROC government. In HUANG&apos;s and WANG&apos;s reports, the records
			<lb />
			and archives management are part of the general services topic, and
			<lb />
			its related suggestion not only established the Executive Yuan institute
			<lb />
			General Services Committee, the official documents authority of
			<lb />
			Taiwan, but also made Taiwan official documents system reformed and
			<lb />
			merged with American perspectives. It is an important achievement
			<lb />
			in Taiwan archival undertaking history, however, the government had
			<lb />
			classified these achievements secret and made many people believe
			<lb />
			the official documents system of China after World War II still keeps
			<lb />
			the same situation as before. Research which has documented the link
			<lb />
			between American and Taiwan records perspectives after World War II
			<lb />
			is scant, therefore, the aim of this article attempts to explore what the
			<lb />
			Impact of Hoover Commission on Taiwan official documents system
			<lb />
			after World War II by analyzing the reports, records, publication,
			<lb />
			papers, diaries and autobiographies related to Taiwan administrative
			<lb />
			reform proposition during the 1950s and 60s.
			<lb />
			【關鍵字 Keywords】
			<lb />
			<keyword>
				行政改革；胡佛委員會；檔案管理；黃季陸；王雲五
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			Administrative reform; Hoover commission; Archives management;
			<lb />

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>