<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="12-1-4" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			<reference>
				圖書資訊學研究 12：1 (December 2017)：111-137
				<lb />
			</reference>


			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>
					圖書館資料倉儲應用模式之研究 以客製化報表為例
					<lb />
				</titlePart>
			</docTitle>
			The Study of Data Warehouse Application Model in Libraries
			<lb />
			A Case Study of Customized Reports
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					楊依婷
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Yi-Ting Yang
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立臺灣師範大學圖書資訊學研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			博士生
			<lb />
			Ph.D. Student
			<lb />
			Graduate Institute of Library and Information Studies
			<lb />
			National Taiwan Normal University
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>謝建成</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			✽
			<lb />
			Jiann-Cherng Shieh
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立臺灣師範大學圖書資訊學研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			教授
			<lb />
			Professor
			<lb />
			Graduate Institute of Library and Information Studies
			<lb />
			National Taiwan Normal University
			<lb />
			【摘要 Abstract】
			<lb />
			<div type="abstract">
				圖書館客製化報表是圖書館管理者亟欲解決的問題之一， 圖書館自動化系統廠商對此至今依舊難有具成本效益之解決方
				<lb />
				案。近幾年，ExLibris 公司針對其自動化系統 Aleph 開發報表系統
				<lb />
				ARC，提供客戶超過 100 種事先定義的報表。然此報表系統僅支
				<lb />
			</div>
			✽ 通訊作者 : 謝建成
			<email>
				jcshieh@ntnu.edu.tw
				<lb />
			</email>
			<note type="submission">
				投稿日期：2017 年 3 月 12 日；接受日期：2017 年 6 月 30 日
				<lb />
			</note>
			<div type="abstract">
				援 Aleph 系統，對國內多數非 Aleph 系統圖書館報表需求毫無助 益，且無法滿足各館即時性多元報表需求。在基於成本效益及客
				<lb />
				製化需求，本研究提出以 SQL Server 之資料倉儲應用模式解決以 上困境。本研究以實際案例驗證模式之可行性。
				<lb />
			</div>
			The development of library customized reports has always been
			<lb />
			one of the intractable problems that library managers urgently seek
			<lb />
			to solve. Similarly, library automation system manufacturers are
			<lb />
			bruised on this issue, not only the high cost of development services,
			<lb />
			but also the frequent changes in demand. The problem is still difficult
			<lb />
			to have by a cost-effective solution. In recent years, ExLibris has
			<lb />
			developed an add-on system Aleph Reporting Center (ARC) for its
			<lb />
			library automation system Aleph to provide Aleph customers more
			<lb />
			than 100 pre-defined statistical reports. However, such reporting
			<lb />
			systems only support specific automation systems, and cannot fully
			<lb />
			meet the customized needs of libraries&apos;. Data warehouse technology
			<lb />
			has been quite mature since the 1970s. Most database management
			<lb />
			systems such as SQL Server also provide tools to support the
			<lb />
			establishment of data warehouses. Considering the cost-effectiveness
			<lb />
			and the demand elasticity of customization, this study proposes the
			<lb />
			data warehouse application model of libraries to solve the above
			<lb />
			dilemma. The application model proposed in this research, the system
			<lb />
			environment is constructed by Microsoft SQL Server, EXCEL; design
			<lb />
			and development are mainly accomplished by the librarian and system
			<lb />
			librarian. This study concludes with a practical case to verify the
			<lb />
			feasibility of the proposed model.
			<lb />
			【關鍵字 Keywords】
			<lb />
			<keyword>
				資料倉儲；圖書館自動化；客製化報表
				<lb />
			</keyword>
				Data Warehouse; Library automation system; Customized reports

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>