<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="12-1-3" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			<reference>
				圖書資訊學研究 12：1 (December 2017)：79-109
				<lb />
			</reference>

			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>
					從 SCORM 數位學習教材標準
					<lb />
					看 EPUB 做為電子教科書檔案 格式之特性與挑戰
					<lb />
				</titlePart>
			</docTitle>
			Understanding the Features and Challenges of Using
			<lb />
			EPUB E-textbook in Education through the Comparison
			<lb />
			of EPUB and SCORM content models
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					張玄菩
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Hsuan-Pu Chang
			<lb />
			<byline>
				<affiliation>淡江大學資訊與圖書館學系</affiliation>
			</byline>
			助理教授
			<lb />
			Assistant Professor
			<lb />
			Department of Information and Library Science
			<lb />
			Tamkang University
			<lb />
			【摘要 Abstract】
			<lb />

			<div type="abstract">
				EPUB 數位出版品標準為電子教科書工業帶來正面效益，期
				<lb />
				望能提升電子教科書的生產效率及更廣泛地使用。然而，有別於
				<lb />
				一般閱讀刊物的需求，要做為校園中的正式教學教材，EPUB 檔 案格式的特性是否有助於在教育目的上的製作、應用及管理值得
				<lb />
				深入的探討跟釐清。本文從過往的相關文獻，分析不同電子教科
				<lb />
				書檔案格式對教育學習的影響，再藉由與 SCORM 數位學習內容
				<lb />
				模型的比較，深入探討 EPUB 檔案格式做為電子教科書的特性與
				<lb />
				挑戰。最後基於研究發現，給予欲採用 EPUB 電子教科書之教材 製作與管理者、系統開發人員以及教師建議。
				<lb />
			</div>
			作者：張玄菩
			<email>
				musicbubu@gmail.com
				<lb />
			</email>
			<note type="submission">
				投稿日期：2017 年 5 月 8 日；接受日期：2017 年 10 月 20 日
				<lb />
			</note>
			Many publishers and scholars believe that the digital publication
			<lb />
			standard, Electronic Publication (EPUB), will bring the positive impact
			<lb />
			to the e-textbook industry and also expect it to improve the efficiency
			<lb />
			of e-textbook production and its wider adoption. However, being the
			<lb />
			primary file format used for official education, we need to further
			<lb />
			investigate whether its features can help facilitate educational resource
			<lb />
			production and the management of these educational resources.
			<lb />
			The previously conducted studies in the following article reviews,
			<lb />
			allow us to analyze how the different features of the e-textbook file
			<lb />
			formats have significantly affected users in teaching and learning.
			<lb />
			In order to understand the significant features of and some of the
			<lb />
			common challenges faced by users, when using EPUB e-textbooks for
			<lb />
			educational purposes, we conducted the following study by comparing
			<lb />
			the EPUB e-textbook and SCORM e-learning content models,
			<lb />
			primarily focusing on these three elements: 1) content presentation,
			<lb />
			2) metadata, 3) content package structure. Finally, the suggestions are
			<lb />
			made to education practitioners on EPUB e-textbook adoption.
			<lb />
			【關鍵字 Keywords】
			<keyword>
				EPUB；SCORM；電子教科書；內容模型
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			EPUB; SCORM; E-book; Content Model
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>