<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="12-1-2" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			<reference>
				圖書資訊學研究 12：1 (December 2017)：37-78
				<lb />
			</reference>

			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>
					概念導向閱讀教學(CORI)對 國中生閱讀投入影響之研究
					<lb />
				</titlePart>
			</docTitle>
			A Research of Effects upon Reading Engagement Using
			<lb />
			CORI in Middle School in Taiwan
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>陳昭珍</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			✽
			<lb />
			Chao-Chen Chen
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立臺灣師範大學圖書資訊學研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			教授
			<lb />
			Professor
			<lb />
			Graduate Institute of Library and Information Studies
			<lb />
			National Taiwan Normal University
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					林吟燕
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Yin-Yen Lin
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立臺灣師範大學圖書資訊學研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			<lb />
			Graduate Institute of Library and Information Studies
			<lb />
			National Taiwan Normal University
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					陳雅萍
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Ya-Ping Chen
			<lb />
			<byline>
				<affiliation>
					臺北市立西松高中附屬國中部
					<lb />
				</affiliation>
			</byline>
			Taipei Municipal XiSong Senior High School
			<lb />
			✽ 通訊作者 : 陳昭珍
			<email>
				joycechaochen@gmail.com
				<lb />
			</email>
			<note type="submission">
	投稿日期：2017 年 3 月 29 日；接受日期：2017 年 8 月 20 日 
	</note>
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					高榛澧
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Zhen-Li Gao
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>
					臺南市立復興國中
					<lb />
				</affiliation>
			</byline>
			Tainan Municipal Fusing Junior High School
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					張羽芳
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Yu-Fang Chang
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>
					國立臺灣師範大學圖書資訊學研究所
					<lb />
				</affiliation>
			</byline>
			Graduate Institute of Library and Information Studies
			<lb />
			National Taiwan Normal University
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					梁鴻栩
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Hong-Shiu Liang
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立臺灣師範大學圖書資訊學研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			<lb />
			Graduate Institute of Library and Information Studies
			<lb />
			National Taiwan Normal University
			<lb />
			【摘要 Abstract】
			<lb />
			<div type="abstract">
				閱讀投入(reading engagement)是影響學習表現和閱讀
				<lb />
				能力的重要因素，閱讀投入度愈高，閱讀成就及在校成績
				<lb />
				愈高。閱讀投入包括閱讀動機、閱讀行為與閱讀策略三個面
				<lb />
				向。概念導向閱讀教學(CORI)是美國國家閱讀研究中心
				<lb />
				(NRRC)所發展的閱讀教學框架，希望利用此框架引導學
				<lb />
				生投入閱讀，從提高動機開始，進而強化閱讀策略的使用。
				<lb />
			</div>
			<div type="abstract">
				CORI 在美國已被證明是可提升學生閱讀投入的教學法，但
				<lb />
				對以升學為目標的台灣國中生是否也有效，教師及學生對此
				<lb />
				種深度閱讀教學模式的反應如何，是值得研究的問題。因此，
				<lb />
				本研究以準實驗研究設計，邀請兩位兩所國中教師，由同一
				<lb />
				位教師進行實驗組及控制組之閱讀教學，實驗組採用 CORI 閱讀教學，控制組採一般常用的閱讀策略教學。教學實施前
				<lb />
				後，以問卷調查學生的閱讀投入度，實驗結束後也訪談兩位
				<lb />
				教師，瞭解學生的反應及教師的教學心得。研究結果發現，
				<lb />
				實施八週 CORI 閱讀教學後，在閱讀動機整體構面，實驗組
				<lb />
				顯著優於控制組，但在閱讀行為及閱讀策略方面未達顯著差
				<lb />
				異。此外根據教師的觀察，發現學生對於 CORI 這種探索式
				<lb />
				課程感到有趣，但由於學生對於初次接觸的策略不熟悉，在
				<lb />
				閱讀策略的運用上，稍有挫折感，不過會將所學到的策略應 用於後來的學習。
				<lb />
			</div>
			Reading engagement is an important factor that influences
			<lb />
			student&apos;s reading performance and reading ability. Students with higher
			<lb />
			degree of reading engagement perform higher learning achievement.
			<lb />
			Reading engagement contains three aspects: reading motivation,
			<lb />
			reading behavior and reading strategies. Concept-Oriented Reading
			<lb />
			Instruction (CORI) is a reading instructional framework developed by
			<lb />
			the National Reading Research Center (NRRC). This framework is
			<lb />
			aimed to encourage students&apos; reading engagement, inspiring reading
			<lb />
			motivation first and then strengthening the use of learning strategies.
			<lb />
			Research studies in the United States have shown the effectiveness
			<lb />
			of CORI on deepening students&apos; reading engagement. However,
			<lb />
			this study is interested in whether CORI has the same effect in the
			<lb />
			examination-dominated culture as in Taiwan. This study took quasi-
			<lb />
			experimental design. Two teachers from different junior high schools
			<lb />
			participated in this study. Each of them taught experiment group and
			<lb />
			control group in their school. CORI was conducted in experiment class
			<lb />
			and reading strategy pedagogy in control class. Reading engagement
			<lb />
			questionnaires were distributed before and after the experiment. Both
			<lb />
			participated teachers were interviewed after the experiment to collect
			<lb />
			students&apos; reaction and teachers&apos; reflection. This study shows that,
			<lb />
			after eight weeks, the experiment group is superior to control group
			<lb />
			in reading motivation with statistical significance. However, there is
			<lb />
			no statistical significant difference in reading behavior and reading
			<lb />
			strategies. According to teachers&apos; observation, students enjoyed and
			<lb />
			were interested in inquiry teaching like CORI. Though felt frustrated
			<lb />
			in the application of reading strategies at the beginning, they soon
			<lb />
			learned how to applied strategies in later learning.
			<lb />
			【關鍵字 Keywords】
			<lb />
			<keyword>
				概念導向閱讀教學；閱讀投入；閱讀動機；閱讀行為；閱讀策略
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			Concept-Oriented Reading Instruction; CORI; Reading engagement;
			<lb />
			Reading motivation; Reading behavior; Reading strategy
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>