<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="12-2-4" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			<reference>
				圖書資訊學研究 12：2 (June 2018)：111-159
				<lb />
			</reference>


			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>
					未婚中年婦女健康知多少？
					<lb />
					網路健康資訊行為與健康促進 生活型態之研究
					<lb />
				</titlePart>
			</docTitle>
			Understanding Unmarried Middle-Aged Women
			<lb />
			Through the Lenses of Health Information Behavior on
			<lb />
			the Internet and the Health Promoting Lifestyle
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					陳怡穎
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Yi-Ying Chen
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>
					國立臺灣師範大學圖書資訊學研究所碩士生
					<lb />
				</affiliation>
			</byline>
			Graduate Student
			<lb />
			Graduate Institute of Library and Information Studies
			<lb />
			National Taiwan Normal University
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>邱銘心</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			✽
			<lb />
			Ming-Hsin Phoebe Chiu
			<lb />


			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立臺灣師範大學圖書資訊學研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			副教授
			<lb />
			Associate Professor
			<lb />
			GraduateInstitute of Library and Information Studies
			<lb />
			National Taiwan Normal University
			<lb />
			【摘要 Abstract】
			<lb />
			<div type="abstract">本研究旨在探討未婚中年婦女對於自身健康的追求，並藉 由網路健康資訊行為及健康促進生活型態兩個觀點作為分析的視</div>
			✽
			<lb />
			通訊作者：邱銘心
			<email>
				phoebechiu@ntnu.edu.tw
				<lb />
			</email>

			<note type="submission">
				投稿日期：2017 年 10 月 26 日；接受日期：2018 年 4 月 13 日
				<lb />
			</note>
			<div type="abstract">
				角。研究採用問卷調查法，以 40-65 歲從未有過婚姻關係之婦女
				<lb />
				作為研究對象，以立意抽樣法與滾雪球法徵求研究參與者，於
				<lb />
				2015 年 5 月至 7 月間進行問卷調查，共回收 385 份有效問卷。研 究發現未婚中年婦女普遍自覺擁有電腦操作能力，偏好網路作為
				<lb />
			</div>

			<div type="abstract">
				主要資訊來源，而認為判斷網路健康資訊的正確性最為困難。健 康促進生活型態分量表分析結果顯示未婚中年婦女對心靈層面較
				<lb />
				為正向亦重視飲食健康。研究建議未婚中年婦女應多參加社團活 動加強歸屬感，而衛福與社福機構則應針對此族群開設資訊素養 課程，強化利用資訊解決健康問題之能力。
				<lb />
			</div>
			The purpose of this study was to investigate the pursuit of
			<lb />
			health and well-being of unmarried middle-aged women, through
			<lb />
			the analytical lenses of health information behavior on the Internet
			<lb />
			and health-promoting lifestyle. The research participants were never-
			<lb />
			married women aged from 40 to 65 in Taiwan, they were recruited
			<lb />
			through both theoretical and snowball sampling strategies with
			<lb />
			structured questionnaire from May to July, 2015. Data collected
			<lb />
			included research participants&apos; demographic data, Internet health
			<lb />
			information behavior, and health promoting lifestyle. 385 completed
			<lb />
			questionnaires were confirmed as valid. The findings suggested
			<lb />
			that the unmarried middle-aged women thought that they had basic
			<lb />
			computer literacy and preferred Internet as the primary health
			<lb />
			information source. However, they found evaluating accuracy of the
			<lb />
			Internet health information a difficult task. The health-promoting
			<lb />
			lifestyle short scale (HPLP-S) revealed that the unmarried middle-
			<lb />
			aged women felt positive spiritually and cared about healthy diets.
			<lb />
			Based on the findings of this study, unmarried middle-aged women are
			<lb />
			encouraged to participate in group activities in order to increase sense
			<lb />
			of belonging, and healthcare and welfare organizations are advised to
			<lb />
			offer information literacy training sessions to unmarried middle-aged
			<lb />
			women to develop ability to solve health problems with information
			<lb />
			technology.
			<lb />
			【關鍵字 Keywords】
			<keyword>
				未婚中年婦女；健康資訊行為；健康促進生活型態；網路健康資訊行為
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			Unmarried middle-aged women; Health information behavior; Health-
			<lb />
			promoting lifestyle; Health information behavior on the Internet
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>