<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="12-2-1" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			<reference>
				圖書資訊學研究 12：2 (June 2018)：1-36
				<lb />
			</reference>

			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>
					中國大陸圖書資訊學領域
					<lb />
					「作者群研究」之學術論文探析：
					<lb />
					以 CNKI 收錄之中文學術論文 為例
					<lb />
				</titlePart>
			</docTitle>
			An Exploration Study of the Authorship Literatures of
			<lb />
			Library and Information Science in China: A Case Study
			<lb />
			based on CNKI
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					葉淑慧
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Shu-Hwei Yeh
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立政治大學圖書資訊與檔案學研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			博士生
			<lb />
			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立故宮博物院圖書文獻處</affiliation>
			</byline>
			助理研究員
			<lb />
			Ph. D. Student
			<lb />
			Graduate Institute of Library, Information and Archival Studies
			<lb />
			National Chengchi University
			<lb />
			Assistant Curator
			<lb />
			Dept. of Rare Books and Documents, National Palace Museum
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>蔡明月</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			✽
			<lb />
			Ming-Yueh Tsay
			<lb />


			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立政治大學圖書資訊與檔案學研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			特聘教授
			<lb />
			Distinguished Professor
			<lb />
			GraduateInstitute of Library, Information and Archival Studies
			<lb />
			National Chengchi University

	✽
			<lb />
			通訊作者：蔡明月
			<email>
				mytsay@nccu.edu.tw
				<lb />
			</email>
			<note type="submission">
				投稿日期：2017 年 4 月 6 日；接受日期：2018 年 4 月 16 日
				<lb />
			</note>
			摘要 Abstract】
			<lb />
			<div type="abstract">
				評估國家、機構、學科主題之研究人力與發表論文作者乃 屬書目計量學研究的目標之一，目的即統計分析作者群的發展 趨勢、核心作者的研究陣容，並解析作者間跨國、跨機構、跨
				<lb />
				學科的知識交流現況。本研究利用「中國知網」(CNKI)之「中
				<lb />
				國期刊全文數據庫」蒐集期刊論文，統整中國大陸圖書資訊學
				<lb />
				領域作者群研究之相關中文學術文獻，自 1991 年至 2016 年合
				<lb />
				計 241 篇，運用內容分析法及書目計量法，解析作者群學術論 文的出版年代、研究方法、資料來源、研究對象及主題等研究 現況，並且以計量方法臚列主要的分析項目，最後舉例並歸納
				<lb />
				本研究蒐集的學術論文有關作者機構、職稱、性別分布、作者 合作度及國際合著的量化數據及研究結果，以揭示作者群間的 組成結構及消長，進而得致觀察與結論。經歸納與分析，中國
				<lb />
				圖書資訊學領域作者群研究在質與量上皆具備研究設計與分析 面向的多樣化，呈現研究主力上的人力結構的發展現況，並且 注重研究人才的知識交流與科研合作研究議題的發展，是值得 參考的研究趨勢與方向。
				<lb />
			</div>
			Bibliometrics is a quantitative study of literature to evaluate
			<lb />
			and quantify research productivity and authorship from the angles of
			<lb />
			countries, institutional affiliations, and subjects so as to further analyze
			<lb />
			the developmental trend of contributors and the main authors, and to
			<lb />
			understand the existing situation of international, interdisciplinary
			<lb />
			and cross-institution knowledge exchange with a simple statistical
			<lb />
			method of bibliography counting. In this study, CNKI database was
			<lb />
			selected and we got a total of 241 Chinese articles published from
			<lb />
			1991 to 2016. With the documentary analysis and content Analysis,
			<lb />
			the bibliography counting results include published years, research
			<lb />
			methods, research designs and samplings, and subject of literatures.
			<lb />
			After retrieving specific parts of data, we conclude authors&apos; institution
			<lb />
			distributions, professional titles, gender distribution, degress of co-
			<lb />
			authorship and the collaboration between international authors to
			<lb />
			reveal constitution and growth ratio among authorship. The quality
			<lb />
			and quantity of research productivity and authorship of library and
			<lb />
			information science in China have been researched a certain level.
			<lb />
			Nowadays, the research show not only the human structure of
			<lb />
			authorship but knowledge exchange and cooperation research topic
			<lb />
			development, which also shows the importance of the coopeation and
			<lb />
			communication of researchers among different subjects in the future
			<lb />
			study.
			<lb />
			【關鍵字 Keyword】
			<lb />
			<keyword>
				圖書資訊學；研究生產力；作者；中國；書目計量學；合著
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			Library and information science; Research productivity; Authorship; China;
			<lb />
			Bibliometrics; Collaboration
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>