<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="12-2-2" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			<reference>
				圖書資訊學研究 12：2 (June 2018)：37-62
				<lb />
			</reference>


			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>
					九大工業國研究補助論文影響力 之探討
					<lb />
				</titlePart>
			</docTitle>
			The Effect of Research Funding in G9 Countries
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					黃慕萱
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Mu-Hsuan Huang
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立臺灣大學圖書資訊學系暨研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			特聘教授
			<lb />
			Distinguished Professor
			<lb />
			Department and Graduate Institute of Library and Information Science
			<lb />
			National Taiwan University
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>黃玫溱</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			✽
			<lb />
			Mei-Jhen Huang
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立臺灣大學圖書資訊學系暨研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			博士生
			<lb />
			Ph.D. Student
			<lb />
			Department and Graduate Institute of Library and Information Science
			<lb />
			National Taiwan University
			<lb />
			【摘要 Abstract】
			<lb />
			<div type="abstract">
				本研究分析美國、英國、法國、德國、日本、義大利、加 拿大、俄羅斯及中國大陸等九大工業國研究補助影響力，統計九
				<lb />
				國 2009 年至 2014 年 3,693,488 篇獲研究補助論文及 2,163,256 篇
				<lb />
				未獲研究補助論文。從國家及領域面向分析發現，獲研究補助論 文平均被引次數高於未獲研究補助論文，達顯著差異，研究補助
				<lb />
				有助於提高論文影響力。中國大陸研究補助率遠高於其他國家， 但獲研究補助論文平均被引次數偏低，研究成果還待提升。生命
				<lb />
			</div>
			* 通訊作者：黃玫溱
			<email>
				mjhuang01@gmail.com
				<lb />
			</email>
			<note type="submission">
				投稿日期：2017 年 6 月 30 日；接受日期：2018 年 1 月 17 日
				<lb />
			</note>

			<div type="abstract">
				科學、農業及自然科學領域之研究補助率在各領域中較高，但與 該領域平均被引次數無明顯關連，平均被引次數最高為臨床醫學
				<lb />
				領域。此外，在研究補助下，各領域相對活躍程度最高國家皆與 平均被引次數最高國家不同，研究補助產出活躍性高未必影響力
				<lb />
				也較高。從機構面向分析則發現，研究補助機構主要補助本國論 文，但受補助之本國論文影響力卻不如受補助之其他國家論文影 響力。
				<lb />
			</div>
			This study analyzed the journal articles from the G9 countries (the
			<lb />
			United States,	the United Kingdom, France, Germany, Japan, Italy,
			<lb />
			Canada, Russia,	and China) to identify the effect of research funding
			<lb />
			on citation impact in these countries. 3,693,488 funded articles and
			<lb />
			2,163,256 unfunded articles published between 2009 and 2014 were
			<lb />
			used. The results showed that funded articles were cited more than
			<lb />
			unfunded articles, and research funding had significant positive
			<lb />
			effects on the number of citations. Although China had the highest
			<lb />
			funding ratio, its citations per funded article were low. Funding ratios
			<lb />
			in Life Sciences, Agriculture, and Natural Sciences ranked as the top
			<lb />
			three, but didn&apos;t apparently impact on citation counts. In addition,
			<lb />
			the country with the most research outputs was not the same as that
			<lb />
			with the highest number of citations in each subject field. The funding
			<lb />
			agencies in each country provided the majority of funds to internal
			<lb />
			research. However, the effect of research funding for internal research
			<lb />
			was lower than that for external research.
			<lb />
			【關鍵字 Keywords】
			<lb />
			<keyword>
				研究補助；被引次數；九大工業國
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			Research funding; Citation counts; G9
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>