<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="12-2-3" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			<reference>
				圖書資訊學研究 12：2 (June 2018)：63-109
				<lb />
			</reference>


			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>
					我國編目館員編目專業能力認知 與工作績效研究
					<lb />
				</titlePart>
			</docTitle>
			Study on Cataloging Librarians&apos; Perceptions of
			<lb />
			Professional Competencies and Job Performances in
			<lb />
			Libraries of Taiwan
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>王梅玲</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			✽
			<lb />
			Mei-Ling Wang
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立政治大學圖書資訊與檔案學研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			教授
			<lb />
			Professor
			<lb />
			Graduate Institute of Library, Information and Archival Studies
			<lb />
			National Chengchi University
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					張艾琦
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Ai-Chi Chang
			<lb />
			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立政治大學圖書資訊與檔案學研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			碩士生
			<lb />
			Master, Graduate 
	Institute of Library, Information and Archival Studies
			<lb />
			National Chengchi University
			<lb />
			【摘要 Abstract】
			<div type="abstract">
				本實證研究旨在探討數位時代圖書館編目館員的編目能力認
				<lb />
				知與工作績效評鑑。編目館員對工作績效的自我評鑑在概念上可
				<lb />
				視為編目工作品質的指標。本論文研究目的包括：(1)探討編
				<lb />
				目館員工作任務與編目專業能力；(2)探討編目館員對於專業
			</div>
			✽
			<lb />
			通訊作者：王梅玲
			<email>
				meilingw@nccu.edu.tw
				<lb />
			</email>
			<note type="submission">
				投稿日期：2017 年 8 月 25 日；接受日期：2017 年 12 月 1 日
				<lb />
			</note>

			<div type="abstract">
				能力的認知；(3)探討編目館員工作績效自我評鑑；(4)探討
				<lb />
				影響編目館員工作績效的因素。本研究的 30 項編目專業能力分
				<lb />
				為資訊組織原理、記述編目、主題分析與權威控制、詮釋資料編 目及編目管理與科技五類。本研究採用問卷調查，設計「我國編
				<lb />
				目館員工作需求、能力認知與工作表現調查問卷」，於 2017 年 4
				<lb />
				月至 5 月間紙本郵寄發送至抽樣的 48 所大學圖書館、9 所公共圖
				<lb />
				書館以及 1 所國家圖書館的 366 位編目館員，問卷回收 288 份，
				<lb />
				278 份有效問卷，回收率為 75.9%。問卷調查顯示受測者的編目工作任務涵蓋中文編目、西文編目
				<lb />
				及非書資料與電子資源編目。有關受測編目館員對編目專業
				<lb />
				能力認知，整體重要性平均數為 4.19。有關編目館員自評編目能
				<lb />
				力，整體平均數為 3.62，館員自評五類編目能力由高至低依序為：
				<lb />
				資訊組織原理、記述編目、主題分析與權威控制、編目科技與管
				<lb />
				理、詮釋資料編目。受測編目館員能力滿意度整體平均為 3.48，
				<lb />
				編目工作績效滿意度整體平均為 3.43，編目工作滿意度整體平均
				<lb />
				為 3.57，館員編目的意義看法整體平均為 4.08。編目館員的專業 經驗和圖書館類型在館員編目五類能力自評與工作績效有差異。 多元迴歸分析顯示編目館員的主題分析與權威控制能力自評以及
				<lb />
				館員整體編目能力滿意度是其工作績效的兩個可預測因素。編目 館員記述編目能力自評以及編目管理與科技能力自評是館員能力 滿意度的兩個預測因素。本研究結果顯示編目館員的能力與工作 績效有關，並提供未來編目工作與資訊組織教育參考。
				<lb />
			</div>
			This exploratory study investigated catalogers&apos; perception of
			<lb />
			cataloging competencies and job performance evaluation at digital age in
			<lb />
			Taiwan. Cataloger&apos;s self-evaluation on their own job performance was
			<lb />
			conceptualization as an indicator of cataloging quality. The objectives
			<lb />
			of this article were as follows: (1)to explore cataloging tasks of
			<lb />
			catalogers and cataloging competencies; (2) to explore the catalogers&apos;
			<lb />
			perception of cataloging competency; (3) to explore cataloger&apos;s self-
			<lb />
			evaluation on their own job performance; (4) to explore the factors
			<lb />
			affect the job performance of catalogers. A total of 30 competencies
			<lb />
			were clustered in to five groups: information organization basics,
			<lb />
			descriptive cataloging, subject analysis and authority control,
			<lb />
			cataloging management and technologies, and metadata. Catalogers
			<lb />
			subjects were randomly selected from the library statistics systems,
			<lb />
			366 catalogers were invited to participate and questionnaires were sent
			<lb />
			to their libraries. The overall response was 75.9%. The survey showed
			<lb />
			that the subjects&apos; cataloging tasks covered Chinese cataloging, western
			<lb />
			cataloging, non-book materials and electronic resources cataloging.
			<lb />
			The average of overall importance of the cataloging competency was
			<lb />
			4.19, and the five types of cataloging competency perception from high
			<lb />
			to low were: information organization basics, description cataloging,
			<lb />
			subject analysis and authority control, cataloging management &amp;
			<lb />
			technology and metadata. The average of catalogers&apos; self-evaluation
			<lb />
			of cataloging competency was 3.62. The overall average competency
			<lb />
			satisfaction degree of the surveyed librarians is 3.48, and the overall
			<lb />
			satisfaction of the job performance is 3.43, and the overall average
			<lb />
			of the job satisfaction was 3.57, and the average meaning view of
			<lb />
			cataloging was 4.08.Multiple regression analysis found the catalogers&apos;
			<lb />
			self-assessment of subject analysis and authority control, and
			<lb />
			catalogers overall satisfaction with their own cataloging competencies
			<lb />
			were two significant predictors of catalogers&apos; own job performance.
			<lb />
			Catalogers&apos; self-assessment on descriptive cataloging and cataloging
			<lb />
			management and technologies contributed to catalogers&apos; levels of
			<lb />
			overall satisfaction with their own cataloging competency. The results
			<lb />
			of this study showed that cataloging competency was related to the
			<lb />
			job performance of catalogers and provided reference for future
			<lb />
			development on cataloging and information organization curricula and
			<lb />
			education.
			<lb />
			【關鍵字 Keywords】
			<lb />
			<keyword>
				編目館員；專業能力；編目能力；編目評鑑；工作績效
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			Caterger professional; Competency; Cataloging competency; Cataloging
			<lb />
			evaluation; Job performance
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>