<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="13-1-1" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			<reference>
				圖書資訊學研究 13：1 (December 2018)：1-50
				<lb />
			</reference>


			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>國民中小學閱讀與資訊素養融入 教學現況調查</titlePart>
			</docTitle>
			<lb />
			The Current Status of Reading and Information Literacy
			<lb />
			Integrated with Teaching in Taiwan&apos;s Elementary and
			<lb />
			Junior High Schools
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					陳海泓
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Hai-Hon Chen
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立臺南大學教育學系</affiliation>
			</byline>
			教授
			<lb />
			Professor
			<lb />
			Department of Education
			<lb />
			National University of Tainan
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					陳昭珍
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Chao-Chen Chen
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立臺灣師範大學圖書資訊學研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			教授
			<lb />
			Professor
			<lb />
			Graduate Institute of Library and Information Studies
			<lb />
			National Taiwan Normal University
			<lb />
			【摘要 Abstract】
			<lb />
			<div type="abstract">
				閱讀能力和資訊素養讓學習無所不在，具備閱讀能力及資訊 素養，學生得以延伸課堂所學，擴展知識領域，其重要性不言而
				<lb />
				喻。近十年來，我國國民中小學逐漸重視閱讀及資訊素養教學， 然而過去有關國民中小學閱讀與資訊素養教育之調查，主要以某
				<lb />
			</div>
			作者：陳海泓
			<email>
				haihon@mail.nutn.edu.tw
				<lb />
			</email>
			；陳昭珍 
			
			<email>cc4073@ntnu.edu.tw</email>

			<note type="submission">
				投稿日期：2017 年 9 月 8 日；接受日期：2018 年 8 月 15 日
				<lb />
			</note>
			<div type="abstract">
				一地區為主，或以圖書教師為調查對象，而未有進行全國性普查 者，以致於無法全面掌握全國中小學實施閱讀及資訊素養教學之
				<lb />
				現況。本研究以研究者和全國圖書教師團隊自編的「國民小學閱 讀教學及資訊素養融入教學現況調查」問卷以及「國民中學閱讀
				<lb />
				教學及資訊素養融入教學現況調查」問卷為研究工具，針對全國
				<lb />
				2,633 所國小和 733 所國中問卷調查，用以蒐集資料。國小和國
				<lb />
				中回收問卷分別是 1,593(60.50%)和 531(72.44%)；有效問
				<lb />
				卷分別是 1,540(96.67%)和 526(99.06%)。以次數分配和百 分比進行資料處理，以了解臺灣地區國民中小學教師的閱讀教學
				<lb />
				與資訊素養融入教學現況，以作為政府當局、教師專業養成、學 校課程規劃等之參考，及未來進一步研究之基礎。
				<lb />
			</div>
			Reading competency and information literacy are used greatly
			<lb />
			in our daily life. They enable students to extend what they learn from
			<lb />
			the class and expand their knowledge field. It shows the importance
			<lb />
			of reading competency and information literacy. In the recent
			<lb />
			decade, our elementary schools have started to focus on teaching
			<lb />
			reading and information literacy. However, the surveys on reading
			<lb />
			and information literacy of the elementary and junior high school
			<lb />
			conducted in the past often based on a certain area, or only the schools
			<lb />
			with teacher librarians. There is a lack of national census so that the
			<lb />
			current development of the reading competence and information
			<lb />
			literacy in elementary and junior high school is not clear. This study
			<lb />
			applied the questionnaires that designed by the researcher and the
			<lb />
			teacher librarian group as research tools. The questionnaire is about
			<lb />
			the reading instruction and information literacy integrated into the
			<lb />
			teaching in elementary and junior high schools. The questionnaires
			<lb />
			were distributed to all the 2,633 elementary schools and 733 junior
			<lb />
			high schools. The collected responses were 1,593 (60.50%) from
			<lb />
			elementary schools and 531 (72.44%) from junior high schools. The
			<lb />
			valid responses are 1,540 (96.67%) from elementary schools and 526
			<lb />
			(99.06%) from junior high schools. The collected data were analyzed
			<lb />
			with frequency distribution and percentage. The results show the
			<lb />
			current status of the reading instruction and information literacy
			<lb />
			integrated with teaching. It could be provided as the reference for the
			<lb />
			government, teachers&apos; professional development, curriculum planning
			<lb />
			and as the base for the further research in the future.
			<lb />
			【關鍵字 Keywords】
			<lb />
			<keyword>
				閱讀教學、資訊素養融入教學、國民小學、國民中學
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			Reading instruction; Information literacy integrated with teaching; Elementary
			<lb />
			school; Junior high school
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>