<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="9-2-5" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			<reference>
				圖書資訊學研究 9：2 (June 2015)：149-189
				<lb />
			</reference>

			<note type="submission">
				投稿日期：2015 年 5 月 17 日；接受日期：2015 年 6 月 30 日
				<lb />
			</note>
			Email: 謝吉隆
			<email>jirlong@gmail.com</email>
			; 沈柏辰
			<email>paichen.shen@gmail.com</email>
			; 楊立偉
			<email>
				wyang@ntu.edu.tw
				<lb />
			</email>


			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>
					輔助新聞檢索之視覺化介面實作 與使用者評估
					<lb />
				</titlePart>
			</docTitle>
			Designing and Evaluating User Interface for Assisting
			<lb />
			News Navigation and Retrieval
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					謝吉隆
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Ji-Lung Hsieh
			<lb />


			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立師範大學圖書資訊學研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			助理教授
			<lb />
			Assistant Professor
			<lb />
			GraduateInstitute of Library and Information Studies
			<lb />
			National Taiwan Normal University
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					沈柏辰
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Bo-Chen Shen
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立師範大學圖書資訊學研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>

			<lb />
			Graduate Institute of Library and Information Studies
			<lb />
			National Taiwan Normal University
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					楊立偉
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Li-Wei Yang
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>龍捲風科技</affiliation>
			</byline>
			董事總經理
			<lb />
			Managing Director
			<lb />
			Tornado Technologies
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立臺灣大學工商管理學系暨商學研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			兼任助理教授
			<lb />
			Adjunct Assistant Professor
			<lb />
			Department and Graduate Institute of Business Administration
			<lb />
			National Taiwan University
			<lb />
			【摘要 Abstract】
			<lb />
			<div type="abstract">
				網路新聞平台使得大眾易於取得多元且大量的新聞資訊，但 卻因搜尋結果所傳回的資訊是依照搜尋準確率排列，無法展現所 得資訊的時間性或其間的關聯性，因而使用者反而需要花更多的 時間去檢索或瀏覽結果，同時也挑戰了使用者的背景知識和檢索
				<lb />
				技巧。著眼於此，本研究開發一套動態新聞視覺化瀏覽系統，企 圖視覺化新聞檢索結果中的資訊關聯性；並嘗試在視覺化介面中
				<lb />
				整合並允許使用者刪修檢索歷程、擴大或縮小搜尋範圍，以降低 搜尋歷程的使用者認知負荷。本研究透過主題式任務來評估本視 覺化系統的使用性，經過訪談與循序序列探勘方法後獲得以下回
				<lb />
				饋：一、 使用者最常用的功能是展開概念網絡中的相關關鍵字以
				<lb />
				發掘更多相關新聞，可達到觸類旁通的功效；二、 使用者認為本 介面所提供的三種相異的網絡視覺化繪圖方法可分別提供其逐一
				<lb />
				檢視相關關鍵字或者觀察概念群集的功能；三、使用者能夠利用 歷程紀錄的功能，一方面修正檢索目標，另一方面則可刪除不必 要的概念以降低參與者的認知負荷。然而，亦有使用者認為操作 不便或因為介面複雜而產生新的認知負荷。
				<lb />
			</div>
			The development of online news website let the public
			<lb />
			obtain news much easier and more convenient. However, retrieved
			<lb />
			information are sorted by relevance, therefore can not display the
			<lb />
			temporal features or relations among information, which poses
			<lb />
			challenges to users&apos; ability of information retrieval skills and their
			<lb />
			background knowledge. To assist users in browsing news, we built
			<lb />
			up a keyword visualization user interface that allows users to browse
			<lb />
			news from different aspects, to control their visit paths and to expand
			<lb />
			or filter information. We conducted interview and applied sequential
			<lb />
			analysis method to evaluate user experience in this study. The results
			<lb />
			show that 1) the function that users used the most is clicking to expand
			<lb />
			related keywords to discover more keywords and related news; 2)
			<lb />
			participants reported that the three network layouts implemented in
			<lb />
			the study can assist them to navigate keywords one by one or to read
			<lb />
			briefly potential keyword categories; 3) by visualizing visit path,
			<lb />
			participants found that they can locate themselves in information
			<lb />
			retrieval process or to alter keywords set for alleviating cognitive
			<lb />
			load. However, the feedback of user study also shows that gathering
			<lb />
			excessive visualization design on an interface may increase cognitive
			<lb />
			load.
			<lb />
			【關鍵字 Keywords】
			<lb />
			<keyword>
				資訊視覺化；新聞導覽；概念圖；資訊檢索歷程
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			Information visualization; News visualization; Information
			<lb />
			visualization evaluation
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>