<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="9-2-2" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			<reference>
				圖書資訊學研究 9：2 (June 2015)：39-66
				<lb />
			</reference>
			* 本文通訊作者
			<lb />
			<note type="submission">
				投稿日期：2015 年 1 月 23 日；接受日期：2015 年 4 月 27 日
				<lb />
			</note>
			Email: 張靖
			<email>zhangj87@mail.sysu.edu.cn</email>
			；張禕
			<email>
				zy4412@126.com
				<lb />
			</email>


			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>
					近三十年中國大陸圖書館 權利發展之分析
					<lb />
				</titlePart>
			</docTitle>
			On the Development of Library Rights in Mainland China
			<lb />
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>張靖</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			*
			<lb />
			Jing Zhang
			<lb />
			<byline>
				<affiliation>中山大學資訊管理學院</affiliation>
			</byline>
			副教授
			<lb />
			Associate Professor
			<lb />
			School of Information Management
			<lb />
			Sun Yat-sen University
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					張禕
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Yi Zhang
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>中山大學資訊管理學院</affiliation>
			</byline>
			碩士研究生
			<lb />
			Graduate Student
			<lb />
			School of Information Management
			<lb />
			Sun Yat-sen University
			<lb />
			【摘要 Abstract】
			<div type="abstract">
				近三十年來逐漸為跨學科領域所認可的將公民權利視作一種
				<lb />
				社會過程的公民權社會學定義，為圖書館權利這一在中國公共文化
				<lb />
				/ 資訊服務獲取領域的包容與歸屬新需求的研究和實踐提供了有益 的啟示。論文採用歷史研究中常用的大事記的方法對中國圖書館權
				<lb />
				利相關的重要事件進行時序和分類梳理，從《圖書館權利法案》及 《公共圖書館宣言》的譯介和研究，宣言式圖書館政策的制訂，圖 書館法律法規的制訂，中國圖書館學會相關會議或報告的關注，相
				<lb />
				關專著、專欄及專案的出現，相關媒體事件的爭論，以及國家政策 法規的涉及等七個方面呈現中國大陸圖書館權利的社會過程。論文
				<lb />
				進而對這一社會過程的整體時間軸進行分析，提出中國圖書館權利
				<lb />
				的社會過程發展至今可以大致劃分為 2002 年前後的自然醞釀和理
				<lb />
				念重建兩個階段，均偏重於學術探討，缺失構成公民權利完整社會 過程的權利實踐和政治活動兩大領域。從這種片面性出發，論文討 論了中國大陸圖書館權利社會過程的未來發展方向。
				<lb />
			</div>
			The sociological definition of citizenship conceptualized as a
			<lb />
			social process has been accepted in interdisciplinary field during the
			<lb />
			last thirty years. It is believed that the study and practice of Chinese
			<lb />
			library rights, a new demand of tolerance and affiliation in the field
			<lb />
			of public cultural and information service, can be inspired from this
			<lb />
			type of citizenship definition. Adopting the historical research method
			<lb />
			of chronicle of events, the paper draws a clear picture of the social
			<lb />
			process of Chinese library rights and time series presented in seven
			<lb />
			aspects: firstly, the translation, introduction and study of &quot;ALAs
			<lb />
			Library Bill of Rights&quot; and &quot;IFLAs Public Library Manifesto&quot; ;
			<lb />
			secondly, the preparation of the library manifesto policies; thirdly, the
			<lb />
			making of the library laws; fourthly, the attention paid by the China
			<lb />
			Society for Library Science through conferences and reports; fifthly,
			<lb />
			the appearance of related monographs, special columns and research
			<lb />
			projects; sixthly, the discussion of related media events; and seventhly,
			<lb />
			the referring in national policies and regulations. Then the paper
			<lb />
			analyzes the timeline of the social process and points out that it can
			<lb />
			be divided into two phases from the beginning until now, the naturally
			<lb />
			brewing phase before 2002 and the idea rebuilding phase after it.
			<lb />
			Both phases favor the academic discussion and therefore, the other
			<lb />
			two sides of an integrated citizenship social process, including rights
			<lb />
			practices and political activities are missing. Last, with a single-sided
			<lb />
			perspective, the paper discusses the future direction of development of
			<lb />
			Chinese library rights as a social process.
			<lb />
			【關鍵字 Keywords】
			<lb />
			<keyword>
				圖書館權利；公民權社會學；公共文化；資訊服務；大事記
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			Library rights; Sociological de nition of citizenship; Public culture;
			<lb />
			Information service; Chronicle of events
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>