<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="9-2-4" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			<reference>
				圖書資訊學研究 9：2 (June 2015)：111-148
				<lb />
			</reference>
			<note type="submission">
				投稿日期：2015 年 6 月 2 日；接受日期：2015 年 6 月 20 日
				<lb />
			</note>
			Email: 林巧敏
			<email>
				cmlin@nccu.edu.tw
				<lb />
			</email>

			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>
					國家檔案館藏使用分析 及其使用者意見調查
					<lb />
				</titlePart>
			</docTitle>
			The Usage Analysis and User Survey of National Archives
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					林巧敏
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Chiao-Min Lin
			<lb />


			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立政治大學圖書資訊與檔案學研究所</affiliation>
			</byline>
			副教授
			<lb />
			Associate Professor
			<lb />
			GraduateInstitute of Library, Information and Archival Studies
			<lb />
			National Chengchi University
			<lb />
			【摘要 Abstract】
			<div type="abstract">
				檔案館需要瞭解使用者需求及其如何與檔案館藏互動的過
				<lb />
				程，才能從使用者的角度，著手規劃並提供滿足使用需求之服 務。本研究以國內典藏國家檔案之檔案館為個案，分析其使用者 背景資料及其館藏調閱紀錄，探討該檔案館使用族群特性，並瞭
				<lb />
				解館藏使用狀況，進而分析各主題館藏數量與調閱比例是否相 稱，以知悉過度使用與不使用之館藏主題。本研究並輔以問卷及 訪談調查，探知檔案館使用者滿意度及其使用過程意見，俾於綜
				<lb />
				合分析。研究發現該檔案館使用者，男多於女，且以 20 至 40 歲 之青壯族群為主，職業以學生及教職者居多，檔案使用目的多為 「學術研究」。檔案館藏內容主題數量偏頗，並呈現多數調閱集
				<lb />
				中在少數特定主題或全宗，尤其以國防及經貿等主題最多；使用 者到館使用頻率不高，館藏內容與取用便利是影響使用意願的主
				<lb />
				要原因，最終擬具建議提供檔案館重塑工作流程與改善讀者服務 作業之參考。
				<lb />
			</div>
			Archives require a greater knowledge of the needs of their
			<lb />
			users as well as a better understanding of how users interact with
			<lb />
			archival collections so as to meet the users&apos; need. This study selected
			<lb />
			a National Archives as the case to analyze the users&apos; registration
			<lb />
			forms and circulation data. The distinguishing characteristics of users
			<lb />
			and user groups are interpreted for realizing the differences between
			<lb />
			users. The amount of collection topics and their access statistics are
			<lb />
			compared for tracking which collections are overused or seldom used.
			<lb />
			The questionnaire and interviews are also adopted for understanding
			<lb />
			the satisfaction and opinions of users.
			<lb />
			This study reveals the users of archive are more male than female.
			<lb />
			Their ages distribution massed on twenty to forty years old. The
			<lb />
			occupations of users were mostly students and faculty. The intentions
			<lb />
			of visiting archives were academic research. The topics of collection
			<lb />
			were severely biased, therefore the most access centralized in a few
			<lb />
			specific topics or fonds, particularly in the defense and economics
			<lb />
			topics. The frequency of visiting archives was not as expect, but the
			<lb />
			quality and available of archival collections were vital factors for
			<lb />
			attracting user visits. Finally, this study proposed suggestions for
			<lb />
			streamlining workflow and improving public services of archives.
			<lb />
			【關鍵字 Keywords】
			<lb />
			<keyword>
				檔案使用研究 ; 使用者調查 ; 調閱分析 ; 國家檔案館
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			Archive use tudy; User survey; Circulation analysis; National archives
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>