<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="9-2-3" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			<reference>
				圖書資訊學研究 9：2 (June 2015)：67-109
				<lb />
			</reference>

			<note type="submission">
				投稿日期：2015 年 5 月 2 日；接受日期：2015 年 6 月 15 日
				<lb />
			</note>
			Email: 林菁
			<email>lingin@mail.ncyu.edu.tw</email>
			；陳耀輝
			<email>
				ychen@mail.ncyu.edu.tw
				<lb />
			</email>


			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>
					應用爭議導向之探究式學習於
					<lb />
					資訊素養課程： 培養國小五年級學生議論能力
					<lb />
				</titlePart>
			</docTitle>
			Argument-Driven Inquiry in Fifth-Grade Information
			<lb />
			Literacy Instruction: A Way to Cultivate Students&apos;
			<lb />
			Argument Skills
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					林菁
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Lin-Ching Chen
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立嘉義大學數位學習設計與管理系</affiliation>
			</byline>
			教授
			<lb />
			Professor
			<lb />
			Department of E-learning Design &amp; Management
			<lb />
			National Chiayi University
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					陳耀輝
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Yaw-Huei Chen
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立嘉義大學資訊工程系</affiliation>
			</byline>
			副教授
			<lb />
			Associate Professor
			<lb />
			Department of Computer Science &amp; Information Engineering
			<lb />
			National Chiayi University
			<lb />
			【摘要 Abstract】
			<lb />
			<div type="abstract">
				本研究旨在應用爭議導向探究於資訊素養課程中，以檢視
				<lb />
				國小五年級學生議論能力的表現。研究現場是一個國小五年級班
				<lb />
				級，共 30 位學生。探究主題是古今中外的爭議性人物，由資訊
				<lb />
				素養老師和班級級任老師協同教學。研究時間為 17 週，主要利 用每週一節的資訊素養課程，再輔以十節國語課程。本研究以參
				<lb />
				與觀察、訪談、測驗和資料分析的方法來蒐集質化和量化資料。 研究結果顯示在國小五年級資訊素養課程中應用爭議性人物主題
				<lb />
				探究，來培養學生議論能力是一可行的方案。學生整體議論能力 有顯著進步，他們瞭解議論文的目的和基本元素。半數學生在議
				<lb />
				論文實際寫作表現優異，能撰寫具有觀點的爭議性人物議論文 章。在口頭發表方面，十組學生中有五組可邏輯性的報告小組觀 點，三組清楚說出小組論點，但論證較不足，另二組則論點和論
				<lb />
				證均弱。最後二位老師建議在資訊素養課程中設計循序漸進爭議 導向的探究學習任務，以有系統的提升學生議論能力。
				<lb />
			</div>
			The purpose of this study was to investigate the effects of
			<lb />
			argument-driven inquiry information literacy instruction on fifth-
			<lb />
			graders&apos; argumentative learning. It was conducted in an elementary
			<lb />
			school and lasted for seventeen weeks. The research site was a fifth-
			<lb />
			grade classroom and the information literacy instruction was taught
			<lb />
			a period of time per week by a teacher librarian, who collaborated
			<lb />
			with a classroom teacher. The classroom teacher taught the basics of
			<lb />
			argumentive texts in Chinese course. They designed an inquiry project,
			<lb />
			titled &quot;Controversial Persons Inquiry&quot; in the information literacy
			<lb />
			and the Chinese course to cultivate students&apos; argument reasoning.
			<lb />
			Research data collected included interviews, participant observations,
			<lb />
			tests, and document analysis. The results showed that using argument-
			<lb />
			driven inquiry in fifth-grade information literacy curriculum was an
			<lb />
			effective project for cultivating students&apos; argument skills. Their overall
			<lb />
			argument performance was improved significantly. They understood
			<lb />
			the purposes and basics of argument writings. Half of students
			<lb />
			performed well in argument writings with insightful claims about the
			<lb />
			controversial figures inquired. In the aspect of speaking, among ten
			<lb />
			groups, five groups presented their findings logically; three groups
			<lb />
			proposed their perspectives clearly, but reasoning was weak. The last
			<lb />
			two groups performed poor in providing claims and warrants. Finally
			<lb />
			teachers suggested that we should systematically design argument-
			<lb />
			driven inquiry projects in information literacy curriculum, so that
			<lb />
			students&apos; argumentative skills can be improved progressively.
			<lb />
			【關鍵字 Keywords】
			<keyword>
				議論能力；爭議導向；資訊素養
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			Argumentative skills; Argument-driven; Information literacy
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>