<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="9-2-1" />
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
			<lb />
			<reference>
				圖書資訊學研究 9：2 (June 2015)：1-38
				<lb />
			</reference>
			* 本文通訊作者
			<lb />
			<note type="submission">
				投稿日期：2014 年 11 月 31 日；接受日期：2015 年 3 月 6 日
				<lb />
			</note>
			Email: 林豐政
			<email>lin@niu.edu.tw；</email>
			李芊芊
			<email>
				sophia-0715@hotmail.com
				<lb />
			</email>
			<docTitle>
				<titlePart>
					數位落差、數位機會 與數位包容之關聯性研究
					<lb />
				</titlePart>
			</docTitle>
			A Study of the
	
	Relationship of Digital Divide,
			<lb />
			Digital Opportunity and Digital Inclusion
			<lb />
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					林豐政
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			*
	Feng-Jeng Lin
			<lb />

			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立宜蘭大學應用經濟與管理學系</affiliation>
			</byline>
			副教授
			<lb />
			Associate Professor
			<lb />
			Department of Applied Economics and Management
			<lb />
			National Ilan University
			<byline>
				<docAuthor>
					李芊芊
					<lb />
				</docAuthor>
			</byline>
			Qian-Qian Li
			<lb />


			<byline>
				<affiliation>國立宜蘭大學應用經濟與管理學系</affiliation>
			</byline>
			研究助理
			<lb />
			Research Assistant
			<lb />
			Department of Applied Economics and Management
			<lb />
			National Ilan University
			<lb />
			【摘要 Abstract】
			<lb />
			<div type="abstract">
				本文旨在提出「資訊近用」、「資訊素養」、「資訊應用」 與「數位機會」的關係模式。研究中除了驗證模式適配能力與說
				<lb />
				明影響效果外，並透過多群組分析探究不同「背景分群」對關係
				<lb />
				模式是否產生干擾效果，藉以評估分群模式構面間的影響性。其 次，進一步探究「數位包容」者上網意願，根據其對於電腦與網
				<lb />
				路的認知與態度，歸納成認知群、興趣群與欲求群；同時，應用 對應分析予以群組化，進而探討「背景分群」與三群體間的關係。
				<lb />
				結果顯示：研究中所提的關係模式在各項指標上皆具良好配適度 與解釋力，不同「年齡層」群與「教育程度」群於關係模式中具
				<lb />
				明顯的干擾效果。在分群模式的影響路徑中，具「老年」、 「少年、 初等學歷」、「中年」以及「老年」特徵者，其分別於「資訊近
				<lb />
				用」對「資訊素養」、「資訊近用」對「資訊應用」、「資訊素 養」對「資訊應用」及「資訊應用」對「數位機會」路徑上影響 力相對較高。在「數位包容」者的上網意願分析中，具「初等學
				<lb />
				歷」者屬「認知群」，具「61 歲以上、男性」者屬「興趣群」，
				<lb />
				具「41-60 歲、女性」者則屬「欲求群」。
				<lb />
			</div>
			In this paper, a model was proposed to investigate the relationship
			<lb />
			among information access, information literacy, information
			<lb />
			application and digital opportunity. Firstly, besides verifying the model
			<lb />
			fit and explaining its influential effects, this study aims to evaluate
			<lb />
			whether different individual traits will have moderating effects on this
			<lb />
			relational model by using a multi-group analysis. Secondly, the study
			<lb />
			will further explore the intention for using the Internet for those people
			<lb />
			who are digital inclusive. We will classify them into three groups in
			<lb />
			light of their awareness of and attitude towards the computer and the
			<lb />
			Internet; these are awareness group, interest group and desire group.
			<lb />
			Meanwhile, the relations between individual traits and these three
			<lb />
			groups will also be discussed by using a correspondence analysis.
			<lb />
			Four important findings are noted as follows: (1) the relational model
			<lb />
			has a good model fit and explanatory ability; (2) different age and
			<lb />
			education levels have significant moderating effects on the relational
			<lb />
			model; (3) the result gleaned from the multi-group model analysis
			<lb />
			indicates that people with old age had higher influential effects on
			<lb />
			how the information access might impact on the information literacy;
			<lb />
			people with young and elementary education had higher influential
			<lb />
			effects on how the information access might impact on the information
			<lb />
			application; people with middle age had higher influential effects
			<lb />
			on how the information literacy might impact on the information
			<lb />
			application; people with old age had higher influential effects on how
			<lb />
			the information application might impact on the digital opportunity;
			<lb />
			(4) the result from the digital inclusion analysis unfolds that people
			<lb />
			with the elementary education was clustered into the awareness
			<lb />
			group; people who are over 61 years old and male was assembled into
			<lb />
			the interest group; people who are between 41 and 60 years old and
			<lb />
			female was classified into the desire group.
			<lb />
			[ 關鍵字 Keywords]
			<lb />
			<keyword>
				資訊近用；資訊素養；資訊應用；數位機會；數位包容
				<lb />
			</keyword>
			Information access; Information literacy; Information application; Digital
			<lb />
			opportunity; Digital inclusion
		</front>
	</text>
</tei>